<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.37.0-wmf.15</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Virginia Woolf</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32742</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1034470318</id>
      <parentid>1032615343</parentid>
      <timestamp>2021-07-20T01:58:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Goszei</username>
        <id>36510957</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Changing [[Wikipedia:Short description|short description]] from "English modernist writer known for use of stream of consciousness" to "English modernist writer" ([[Wikipedia:Shortdesc helper|Shortdesc helper]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="271541" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|English modernist writer}}
{{About|the British modernist author| the American children's author|Virginia Euwer Wolff|the British rock band|Virginia Wolf}}
{{Redirect|Woolf}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2020}}
{{Use British English|date=May 2020}}
{{Infobox writer &lt;!-- for more information see [[:Template:Infobox writer/doc]] --&gt;
| name         = Virginia Woolf
| image        = George Charles Beresford - Virginia Woolf in 1902 - Restoration.jpg
| alt          = Photograph of Virginia Woolf in 1902; photograph by George Charles Beresford
| caption      = Woolf in 1902
| birth_name   = Adeline Virginia Stephen
| birth_date   = {{birth date|df=y|1882|1|25}}
| birth_place  = [[South Kensington]], London, England
| death_date   = {{death date and age|df=y|1941|3|28|1882|1|25}}
| death_place  = [[Lewes]], England
| occupation   = {{hlist|Novelist|essayist|publisher|critic}}
| parents      = {{ubl|[[Leslie Stephen]]|[[Julia Stephen|Julia Prinsep Jackson]]}}
| spouse       = {{marriage|[[Leonard Woolf]]|10 August 1912}}
| alma_mater   = [[King's College London]]
| notableworks = {{plainlist|
*''[[Mrs Dalloway]]'' (1925)
*''[[To the Lighthouse]]'' (1927)
*''[[Orlando: A Biography|Orlando]]'' (1928)
*''[[A Room of One's Own]]'' (1929)
*''[[The Waves]]'' (1931)}}
| relatives    = {{plainlist|
* [[George Herbert Duckworth]] (half-brother)
* Stella Duckworth (half-sister)
* [[Gerald Duckworth]] (half-brother)
* [[Laura Stephen]] (half-sister)
* [[Vanessa Bell|Vanessa Stephen]] (sister)
* [[Thoby Stephen]] (brother)
* [[Adrian Stephen]] (brother)
* [[Katharine Stephen]] (cousin)}}
| signature    = Virginia Woolf signature.svg
| module       = {{Listen| embed=yes |filename = On Craftsmanship - the only surviving recording of Virginia Woolf.flac |title = Woolf's voice |type = speech |description   =[[BBC radio]] broadcast 29 April 1937{{sfn|Woolf|1937}}}}
}}

'''Adeline Virginia Woolf''' ({{IPAc-en|w|ʊ|l|f}};{{sfn|Collins|2018}} {{née|'''Stephen'''}}; 25 January 1882{{snd}} 28 March 1941) was an English writer, considered one of the most important [[modernist literature|modernist]] 20th-century authors and a pioneer in the use of [[Stream of consciousness (narrative mode)|stream of consciousness]] as a narrative device.

Woolf was born into an affluent household in [[South Kensington]], London, the seventh child in a [[blended family]] of eight which included the modernist painter [[Vanessa Bell]]. Her mother was [[Julia Stephen|Julia Prinsep Jackson]] and her father [[Leslie Stephen]]. While the boys in the family received college educations, the girls were home-schooled in English classics and Victorian literature. An important influence in Virginia Woolf's early life was the summer home the family used in [[St Ives, Cornwall]], where she first saw the [[Godrevy Lighthouse]], which was to become central to her novel ''[[To the Lighthouse]]'' (1927).

Woolf's childhood came to an abrupt end in 1895 with the death of her mother and her first mental breakdown, followed two years later by the death of her half-sister and a mother figure to her, Stella Duckworth. From 1897 to 1901, she attended the Ladies' Department of [[King's College London]], where she studied classics and history and came into contact with early reformers of women's higher education and the [[women's rights movement]]. Other important influences were her [[University of Cambridge|Cambridge]]-educated brothers and unfettered access to her father's vast library.

Encouraged by her father, Woolf began writing professionally in 1900. Her father's death in 1904 caused Woolf to have another breakdown. Following his death, the Stephen family moved from Kensington to the more bohemian Bloomsbury, where they adopted a free-spirited lifestyle. It was in [[Bloomsbury]] where, in conjunction with the brothers' intellectual friends, they formed the artistic and literary [[Bloomsbury Group]]. 

In 1912, she married [[Leonard Woolf]], and in 1917 the couple founded the [[Hogarth Press]], which published much of her work. They rented a home in Sussex and moved there permanently in 1940. Woolf also had romantic relationships with women, including [[Vita Sackville-West]], who also published her books through Hogarth Press. Both women's literature became inspired by their relationship, which lasted until Woolf's death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |last1=Haynes |first1=Suyin |title=What to Know About Virginia Woolf's Love Affair With Vita Sackville-West |url=https://time.com/5655270/virginia-woolf-vita-sackville-west-relationship/ |magazine=Time |access-date=22 June 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout her life, Woolf was troubled by her mental illness. She was institutionalised several times and attempted suicide at least twice. Her illness may have been [[bipolar disorder]], for which there was no effective intervention during her lifetime. In 1941, at age 59, Woolf died by drowning herself in the [[River Ouse, Sussex|River Ouse]] at [[Lewes]].

During the interwar period, Woolf was an important part of London's literary and artistic society. In 1915 she published her first novel, ''[[The Voyage Out]]'', through her half-brother's publishing house, [[Gerald Duckworth and Company]]. Her best-known works include the novels ''[[Mrs Dalloway]]'' (1925), ''[[To the Lighthouse]]'' (1927) and ''[[Orlando: A Biography|Orlando]]'' (1928). She is also known for her essays, including ''[[A Room of One's Own]]'' (1929), in which she wrote the much-quoted dictum, "A woman must have money and a room of her own if she is to write fiction." 

Woolf became one of the central subjects of the 1970s movement of feminist criticism and her works have since garnered much attention and widespread commentary for "inspiring [[feminism]]". Her works have been translated into more than 50 languages. A large body of literature is dedicated to her life and work, and she has been the subject of plays, novels and films. Woolf is commemorated today by statues, societies dedicated to her work and a building at the [[University of London]].
{{TOC limit|3}}

== Life ==
=== Family of origin ===
{{see also|Julia Stephen}}
&lt;!-- horizontals standardised to 200/image --&gt;
{{multiple image
| header = Parents
| align = right
| direction = horizontal
| total_width = 340
| float = none
| image1 = Leslie Stephen c1860.jpg
| caption1 = [[Leslie Stephen]], 1860
| alt1 = Photo of her father, Leslie Stephen in 1860
| image2 = Cameron julia jackson.jpg
| caption2 = [[Julia Stephen]], 1867
| alt2 = Photo of her mother, Julia Stephen 1867
}}

Virginia Woolf was born Adeline Virginia Stephen on 25 January 1882 at 22 [[Hyde Park Gate]] in [[South Kensington]], London,{{sfn|Gordon|2004}} to [[Julia Stephen|Julia (née Jackson)]] (1846–1895) and [[Leslie Stephen]] (1832–1904), writer, historian, essayist, biographer and mountaineer.{{sfn|Gordon|2004}} Julia Jackson was born in 1846 in [[Kolkata|Calcutta]], [[British India]] to John Jackson and Maria "Mia" Theodosia Pattle, from two [[Anglo-Indian]] families.&lt;ref name=VineJacksonDiary/&gt; John Jackson [[FRCS]] was the third son of George Jackson and Mary Howard of Bengal, a physician who spent 25 years with the [[Bengal Medical Service]] and [[East India Company]] and a professor at the fledgling [[Calcutta Medical College]]. While John Jackson was an almost invisible presence, the [[#Pattle|Pattle family]] were famous beauties, and moved in the upper circles of Bengali society.{{sfn|Bennett|2002}} The seven Pattle sisters married into important families. [[Julia Margaret Cameron]] was a celebrated photographer, while Virginia married [[Third Earl Somers|Earl Somers]], and their daughter, Julia Jackson's cousin, was [[Lady Henry Somerset]], the temperance leader. Julia moved to England with her mother at the age of two and spent much of her early life with another of her mother's sisters, Sarah Monckton Pattle. Sarah and her husband [[Henry Thoby Prinsep]], conducted an artistic and literary [[Salon (gathering)|salon]] at [[Little Holland House]] where she came into contact with a number of [[Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood|Pre-Raphaelite]] painters such as [[Edward Burne-Jones]], for whom she modelled.{{sfn|Kukil|2011}}

Julia was the youngest of three sisters, and Adeline Virginia was named after her mother's eldest sister Adeline Maria Jackson (1837–1881){{sfn|Smith College|2011}} and her mother's aunt Virginia Pattle (see [[#Pattle|Pattle family tree]]). Because of the tragedy of her aunt Adeline's death the previous year, the family never used Virginia's first name. The Jacksons were a well educated, literary and artistic proconsular middle-class family.{{sfn|Garnett|2004}}&lt;ref name=hauntedintro/&gt; In 1867, Julia Jackson married [[Herbert Duckworth]], a barrister,&lt;ref name=VineDuckworth/&gt; but within three years was left a widow with three infant children. She was devastated and entered a prolonged period of mourning, abandoning her faith and turning to nursing and philanthropy. Julia and Herbert Duckworth had three children:{{sfn|Wood|2017}}
* [[George Herbert Duckworth|George]] (5 March 1868 – 27 April 1934), a senior civil servant, married Lady Margaret Herbert in 1904
* Stella (30 May 1869 – 19 July 1897), died aged 28{{efn|Stella Duckworth was 26 when her mother died, and married Jack Hills (1876–1938) two years later, but died following her honeymoon. She was buried next to her mother.&lt;ref name=Stella/&gt;}}
* [[Gerald Duckworth|Gerald]] (29 October 1870 – 28 September 1937), founder of [[Duckworth Publishing]], married Cecil Alice Scott-Chad in 1921

[[File:Julia Stephen with Virginia on her lap 1884.jpg|thumb|upright|Julia Stephen and Virginia, 1884{{efn|Leslie Stephen treasured this photograph, saying it "makes my heart tremble"&lt;ref name=Kukil36f/&gt;}}|alt= Photo of Julia Stephen with Virginia on her lap in 1884]]
Leslie Stephen was born in 1832 in South Kensington to [[James Stephen (civil servant)|Sir James]] and Lady Jane Catherine Stephen (née Venn), daughter of [[John Venn (priest)|John Venn]], rector of [[Clapham]]. The Venns were the centre of the evangelical [[Clapham Sect]]. Sir James Stephen was the [[under secretary]] at the [[Colonial Office]], and with another Clapham member, [[William Wilberforce]], was responsible for the passage of the [[Slavery Abolition Bill]] in 1833.{{sfn|Gordon|2004}}{{sfn|Himmelfarb|1985}} In 1849 he was appointed [[Regius Professor of Modern History (Cambridge)|Regius Professor of Modern History]] at [[Cambridge University]].&lt;ref name=License12/&gt; As a family of educators, lawyers and writers the Stephens represented the elite intellectual aristocracy. While his family were distinguished and intellectual, they were less colourful and aristocratic than Julia Jackson's. A graduate and fellow of Cambridge University he renounced his faith and position to move to London where he became a notable man of letters.{{sfn|ACAD|STFN850L}} In addition he was a rambler and mountaineer, described as a "gaunt figure with the ragged red brown beard...a formidable man, with an immensely high forehead, steely-blue eyes, and a long pointed nose".{{efn|According to [[Helena Swanwick]], sister of [[Walter Sickert]]}}&lt;ref name=License12/&gt; In the same year as Julia Jackson's marriage, he wed Harriet Marian (Minny) Thackeray (1840–1875), youngest daughter of [[William Makepeace Thackeray]], who bore him a daughter, Laura (1870–1945),{{efn|Laura was born premature, at 30 weeks{{sfn|Koutsantoni|Oakley|2014}}}}{{sfn|Olsen|2012}} but died in childbirth in 1875. Laura was developmentally disabled and eventually institutionalised.{{sfn|Luebering|2006}}{{sfn|Bicknell|1996}}

The widowed Julia Duckworth knew Leslie Stephen through her friendship with Minny's elder sister [[Anne Isabella Ritchie|Anne (Anny) Isabella Ritchie]] and had developed an interest in his agnostic writings. She was present the night Minny died{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=13}} and later, tended to Leslie Stephen and helped him move next door to her on Hyde Park Gate so Laura could have some companionship with her own children.&lt;ref name=Wilson21/&gt;{{sfn|Wilson|1987}}{{sfn|Nadel|2016}}&lt;ref name="Rosner2008/69"/&gt; Both were preoccupied with mourning and although they developed a close friendship and intense correspondence, agreed it would go no further.{{efn|Quention Bell speculates that their relationship formed the background to their mutual friend [[Henry James]]' ''[[Altar of the Dead]]''{{sfn|Bell|1965}}}}{{sfn|Bell|1965}}&lt;ref name=Tolley106/&gt; Leslie Stephen proposed to her in 1877, an offer she declined, but when Anny married later that year she accepted him and they were married on 26 March 1878. He and Laura then moved next door into Julia's house, where they lived till his death in 1904. Julia was 32 and Leslie was 46.{{sfn|Bicknell|1996}}{{sfn|Bloom|Maynard|1994}}

Their first child, [[Vanessa Bell|Vanessa]], was born on 30 May 1879. Julia, having presented her husband with a child, and now having five children to care for, had decided to limit her family to this.{{sfn|Woolf|1940|p=127}} However, despite the fact that the couple took "precautions",{{sfn|Woolf|1940|p=127}} "contraception was a very imperfect art in the nineteenth century"{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=18}} resulting in the birth of three more children over the next four years.{{efn|As Virginia Woolf puts it, they "did what they could to prevent me".{{sfn|Woolf|1940|p=127}}}}&lt;ref name=Bond23/&gt;{{sfn|Garnett|2004}}&lt;ref name=chronology/&gt;

=== 22 Hyde Park Gate (1882–1904) ===

==== 1882–1895 ====
Virginia Woolf provides insight into her early life in her autobiographical essays, including ''Reminiscences'' (1908),{{sfn|Woolf|1908}} ''22 Hyde Park Gate'' (1921),{{sfn|Woolf|1921}} and ''[[A Sketch of the Past]]'' (1940).{{sfn|Woolf|1940}} Other essays that provide insight into this period include ''Leslie Stephen'' (1932).{{sfn|Woolf|1932a}}{{efn|''Leslie Stephen'' was originally published in ''[[The Times]]'' on 28 November 1932 and republished posthumously in 1950 in ''The Captain's death bed: and other essays'', and eventually, in the Collected Essays Volume 5{{sfn|Woolf|1929–1932}}}} She also alludes to her childhood in her fictional writing. In ''[[To the Lighthouse]]'' (1927),{{sfn|Woolf|1927}} her depiction of the life of the Ramsays in the [[Hebrides]] is an only thinly disguised account of the Stephens in Cornwall and the [[Godrevy Lighthouse]] they would visit there.{{sfn|Roe|2011}}{{sfn|Bell|1965}}&lt;ref name=Flint54/&gt; However, Woolf's understanding of her mother and family evolved considerably between 1907 and 1940, in which the somewhat distant, yet revered figure of her mother becomes more nuanced and filled in.{{sfn|Schulkind|1985|p=13}}

[[File:Duckworth Stephen Family 1892.jpg|thumb|Duckworth Stephen Family {{circa|1892}}. Back row: Gerald Duckworth, Virginia, Thoby and Vanessa Stephen, George Duckworth. Front row: Adrian, Julia, Leslie Stephen. Absent: Stella Duckworth, Laura Stephen.]]
In February 1891, with her sister Vanessa, Woolf began the ''Hyde Park Gate News'',{{sfn|Stephens|2005}} chronicling life and events within the Stephen family,{{sfn|BL|2018}}&lt;ref name=chronology/&gt; and modelled on the popular magazine ''[[Tit-Bits]]''. Initially, this was mainly Vanessa's and Thoby's articles, but very soon Virginia became the main contributor, with Vanessa as editor. Their mother's response when it first appeared was "Rather clever I think".&lt;ref name=License19/&gt; Virginia would run the ''Hyde Park Gate News'' until 1895, the time of her mother's death.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The following year the Stephen sisters also used photography to supplement their insights, as did Stella Duckworth.{{sfn|Humm|2006|p=5}} Vanessa Bell's 1892 portrait of her sister and parents in the Library at Talland House (see [[#library|image]]) was one of the family's favourites and was written about lovingly in Leslie Stephen's memoir.{{sfn|Humm|2006a}} In 1897 ("the first really ''lived'' year of my life)"{{sfn|Woolf|1990|loc=1 January 1898 |p=134}} Virginia began her first diary, which she kept for the next twelve years,{{sfn|Woolf|1990}} and a notebook in 1909.{{sfn|Woolf|2003}}

Virginia was, as she describes it, "born into a large connection, born not of rich parents, but of well-to-do parents, born into a very communicative, literate, letter writing, visiting, articulate, late nineteenth century world".{{sfn|Woolf|1940|p=65}} It was a well-connected family consisting of six children, with two half brothers and a half sister (the Duckworths, from her mother's first marriage), another half sister, Laura (from her father's first marriage), and an older sister, [[Vanessa Bell|Vanessa]] and brother [[Thoby Stephen|Thoby]]. The following year, another brother [[Adrian Stephen|Adrian]] followed. The disabled Laura Stephen lived with the family until she was institutionalised in 1891.{{sfn|Meyer|Osborne|1982}} Julia and Leslie had four children together:{{sfn|Wood|2017}}
* [[Vanessa Bell|Vanessa]] "Nessa" (30 May 1879 – 1961), married [[Clive Bell]] in 1907
* [[Thoby Stephen|Thoby]] (9 September 1880 – 1906), founded [[Bloomsbury Group]]
* Virginia "Jinny"/"Ginia" (25 January 1882 – 1941), married [[Leonard Woolf]] in 1912
* [[Adrian Stephen|Adrian]] (27 October 1883 – 1948), married [[Karin Costelloe]] in 1914

[[File:Sir Leslie Stephen 22 Hyde Park Gate Kensington London SW7 5DH.jpg|thumb|upright|22 [[Hyde Park Gate]], 2015{{efn|The line separating the additional floors of 1886 can be clearly seen.&lt;ref name="Rosner2008/69"/&gt;}}|alt= Photograph of 22 Hyde Park Gate with commemorative plaques for the Stephen family]]
Virginia was born at 22 Hyde Park Gate and lived there until her father's death in 1904. Number 22 Hyde Park Gate, South Kensington, lay at the south-east end of Hyde Park Gate, a narrow cul-de-sac running south from [[Kensington Road]], just west of the [[Royal Albert Hall]], and opposite [[Kensington Gardens]] and [[Hyde Park, London|Hyde Park]],{{sfn|Woolf|1940|p=119}} where the family regularly took their walks (see [[#22HPGmap|Map]]; [[#22HPGplan|Street plan]]). Built in 1846 by Henry Payne of [[Hammersmith]] as one of a row of single-family townhouses for the upper middle class,&lt;ref name=SoLHPG/&gt; it soon became too small for their expanding family. At the time of their marriage, it consisted of a basement, two stories, and an attic. In July 1886 Leslie Stephen obtained the services of [[J.&amp;nbsp;W. Penfold]], an architect, to add additional living space above and behind the existing structure. The substantial renovations added a new top floor (see [[#22HPGext|image of red brick extension]]), with three bedrooms and a study for himself, converted the original attic into rooms, and added the first bathroom.&lt;ref name=License19/&gt;{{efn|The [[Survey of London]] considers this renovation an example of insensitive and inappropriate mutilation, adding two brick-faced stories to a stucco-fronted house.&lt;ref name=SoLHPG/&gt;&lt;ref name="Rosner2008/69"/&gt;}} It was a tall but narrow townhouse, that at that time had no running water. Virginia would later describe it as "a very tall house on the left-hand side near the bottom which begins by being stucco and ends by being red brick; which is so high and yet—as I can say now that we have sold it—so rickety that it seems as if a very high wind would topple it over".{{sfn|Woolf|1922|p=179}}

[[File:London-kensington-gardens-the-round-pond-antique-print-1896-146613-p(ekm)400x285(ekm).jpg|thumb|Children sailing boats on the [[Round Pond (London)|Round Pond]], 1896|alt=Children sailing their boats on the Round Pond at Kensington Gardens in 1896]]
The servants worked "downstairs" in the basement. The ground floor had a drawing room, separated by a curtain from the servant's pantry and a library. Above this on the first floor were Julia and Leslie's bedrooms. On the next floor were the Duckworth children's rooms, and above them, the day and night nurseries of the Stephen children occupied two further floors.{{sfn|Marler|1993|p=xxiv}} Finally, in the attic, under the eaves, were the servants' bedrooms, accessed by a back staircase.{{sfn|Olsen|2012}}{{sfn|Woolf|1940}}&lt;ref name="Rosner2008/69"/&gt; Life at 22 Hyde Park Gate was also divided symbolically; as Virginia put it, "The division in our lives was curious. Downstairs there was pure convention: upstairs pure intellect. But there was no connection between them", the worlds typified by George Duckworth and Leslie Stephen.{{sfn|Woolf|1940|p=157}} Their mother, it seems, was the only one who could span this divide.&lt;ref name=Blair70/&gt;&lt;ref name=SOP102/&gt; The house was described as dimly lit and crowded with furniture and paintings.{{sfn|Marler|1993|p=xxv}} Within it, the younger Stephens formed a close-knit group.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{harvnb|Reid}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this, the children still held their grievances. Virginia envied Adrian for being their mother's favourite.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Virginia and Vanessa's status as creatives (writing and art respectively) caused a rivalry between them at times.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Life in London differed sharply from their summers in Cornwall, their outdoor activities consisting mainly of walks in nearby Kensington Gardens, where they would play hide-and-seek and sail their boats on the [[Round Pond (London)|Round Pond]],&lt;ref name=License19/&gt; while indoors, it revolved around their lessons.{{sfn|Gordon|2004}}

Leslie Stephen's eminence as an editor, critic, and biographer, and his connection to William Thackeray, meant his children were raised in an environment filled with the influences of a Victorian literary society. [[Henry James]], [[George Henry Lewes]], [[Alfred Lord Tennyson]], [[Thomas Hardy]], [[Edward Burne-Jones]], and Virginia's honorary godfather, [[James Russell Lowell]], were among the visitors to the house. Julia Stephen was equally well connected. Her aunt was a pioneering early photographer, [[Julia Margaret Cameron]], who was also a visitor to the Stephen household. The two Stephen sisters, Vanessa and Virginia, were almost three years apart in age. Virginia christened her older sister "the saint" and was far more inclined to exhibit her cleverness than her more reserved sister. Virginia resented the domesticity Victorian tradition forced on them far more than her sister. They also competed for Thoby's affections.{{sfn|Garnett|2011|pp=19–21}} Virginia would later confess her ambivalence over this rivalry to [[Duncan Grant]] in 1917: "indeed one of the concealed worms of my life has been a sister's jealousy – ''of'' a sister I mean; and to feed this I have invented such a myth about her that I scarce know one from t'other".{{sfn|Garnett|2011|p=22}}

Virginia showed an early affinity for writing. Although both parents disapproved of formal education for females, writing was considered a respectable profession for women, and her father encouraged her in this respect. Later, she would describe this as "ever since I was a little creature, scribbling a story in the manner of Hawthorne on the green plush sofa in the drawing room at St. Ives while the grown-ups dined". By the age of five, she was writing letters and could tell her father a story every night. Later, she, Vanessa, and Adrian would develop the tradition of inventing a serial about their next-door neighbours, every night in the nursery, or in the case of St. Ives, of spirits that resided in the garden. It was her fascination with books that formed the strongest bond between her and her father.{{sfn|Gordon|2004}} For her tenth birthday, she received an ink-stand, a blotter, drawing book and a box of writing implements.&lt;ref name=License19/&gt;

==== Talland House (1882–1894) ====
[[File:Talland House, c1882–1894.jpg|thumb|Talland House, [[St. Ives, Cornwall|St. Ives]], {{circa|1882}}–1895| alt= Photo of Talland House, St. Ives during period when the Stephen family leased it]]
Leslie Stephen was in the habit of hiking in Cornwall, and in the spring of 1881 he came across a large white house{{sfn|Eagle|Carnell|1981|p=232}} in [[St Ives, Cornwall]], and took out a lease on it that September.{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Chronology |p=189}} Although it had limited amenities,{{efn|There was no furniture upstairs and the cold water tap did not function}} its main attraction was the view overlooking Porthminster Bay towards the [[Godrevy Lighthouse]],{{sfn|Gordon|2004}} which the young Virginia could see from the upper windows and was to be the central figure in her ''To the Lighthouse'' (1927).{{sfn|Woolf|1927}} It was a large square house, with a terraced garden, divided by hedges, sloping down towards the sea.{{sfn|Gordon|2004}} Each year between 1882 and 1894 from mid-July to mid-September the Stephen family leased Talland House{{sfn|Gordon|2004}}&lt;ref name=WOLTalland/&gt;{{efn|{{As of|2018}} the house still stands, though much altered, on Albert Road, off Talland Road}} as a summer residence. Leslie Stephen, who referred to it thus: "a pocket-paradise",{{sfn|Richardson|2015}} described it as "The pleasantest of my memories... refer to our summers, all of which were passed in Cornwall, especially to the thirteen summers (1882–1894) at St Ives. There we bought the lease of Talland House: a small but roomy house, with a garden of an acre or two all up and down hill, with quaint little terraces divided by hedges of [[escallonia]], a grape-house and kitchen-garden and a so-called 'orchard' beyond".&lt;ref name=Kukil37c/&gt; It was in Leslie's words, a place of "intense domestic happiness".{{sfn|Humm|2006|p=6}} Virginia herself described the house in great detail:
{{Quotebox
| align = left
| width = 100em|"Our house was...outside the town; on the hill....a square house, like a child's drawing of a house; remarkable only for its flat roof, and the railing with crossed bars of wood that ran around the roof. It had...a perfect view—right across the Bay to Godrevy Lighthouse. It had, running down the hill, little lawns, surrounded by thick escallonia bushes...it had so many corners and lawns that each was named...it was a large garden—two or three acres at most...You entered Talland House by a large wooden gate...up the carriage drive...to the Lookout place...From the Lookout place one had...a perfectly open view of the Bay....a large lap...flowing to the Lighthouse rocks...with the black and white Lighthouse tower"
| source = ''Reminiscences'' 1908, pp. 111–112{{sfn|Woolf|1908}}
}}

[[File:GodrevyLightHouse.JPG|thumb|[[Godrevy Lighthouse]], 2005|alt=Close up view of Godrevy Lighthouse in 2005]]
{{anchor|library}}{{multiple image | header = Activities at Talland| align = center | direction = horizontal | total_width = 540 | float = none
|image1=Virginia Adrian Stephen cricket.1886.jpg |caption1 = Her brother's keeper:  Virginia and Adrian Stephen playing [[cricket]], 1886|alt1= Virginia and Adrian Stephen playing cricket at Talland House in 1886
|image2=Julia Leslie Virginia.jpg|caption2=Julia, Leslie and Virginia, Library, Talland House, 1892|alt2=Julia, Leslie and Virginia reading in the library at Talland House. Photography by Vanessa Bell
|image3= Virginia Woolf and Vanessa Bell children.jpg|caption3= Virginia and Vanessa, 1894{{sfn|Colman|2014}}| alt3= Virginia playing cricket with Vanessa 1894
}}
In both London and Cornwall, Julia was perpetually entertaining, and was notorious for her manipulation of her guests' lives, constantly matchmaking in the belief everyone should be married, the domestic equivalence of her philanthropy.{{sfn|Garnett|2004}} As her husband observed, "My Julia was of course, though with all due reserve, a bit of a matchmaker".&lt;ref name=Kukil38l/&gt; Amongst their guests in 1893 were the Brookes, whose children, including [[Rupert Brooke]], played with the Stephen children. Rupert and his group of Cambridge Neo-pagans would come to play an important role in their lives in the years before the First World War.&lt;ref name=Read10/&gt; While Cornwall was supposed to be a summer respite, Julia Stephen soon immersed herself in the work of caring for the sick and poor there, as well as in London.&lt;ref name=WOLTalland/&gt;{{sfn|Richardson|2015}}{{efn| A notice was posted to the effect that the St. Ives Nursing Association had hired "a trained nurse ... under the direction of a Committee of Ladies to attend upon the SICK POOR of St Ives free of cost and irrespective of Creed" and that "gifts of old linen" should be sent to Mrs E Hain or Mrs Leslie Stephen, of Talland House and Hyde Park Gate. ''St Ives, Weekly Summary, Visitors' List and Advertiser'' 2 September 1893.{{sfn|Richardson|2015}} The phrase "irrespective of Creed" echoes her axiom "Pity has no creed" in ''Agnostic Women'' 1880 (see [[#quotes|Quotations]])}} Both at Hyde Park Gate and Talland House, the family mingled with much of the country's literary and artistic circles.{{sfn|Woolf|1940}} Frequent guests included literary figures such as [[Henry James]] and George Meredith,&lt;ref name=Kukil38g/&gt; as well as James Russell Lowell, and the children were exposed to much more intellectual conversations than at their mother's Little Holland House.{{sfn|Marler|1993|p=xxv}} The family did not return, following Julia Stephen's death in May 1895.{{sfn|Richardson|2015}}

For the children, it was the highlight of the year, and Virginia's most vivid childhood memories were not of London but of Cornwall. In a diary entry of 22 March 1921,{{sfn|Woolf|1920–1924}} she described why she felt so connected to Talland House, looking back to a summer day in August 1890. "Why am I so incredibly and incurably romantic about Cornwall? One's past, I suppose; I see children running in the garden … The sound of the sea at night … almost forty years of life, all built on that, permeated by that: so much I could never explain".{{sfn|Woolf|1920–1924}}{{sfn|Gordon|2004}}{{sfn|British Library|2018}} Cornwall inspired aspects of her work, in particular the "St Ives Trilogy" of ''[[Jacob's Room]]'' (1922),{{sfn|Woolf|1922a}} ''To the Lighthouse'' (1927),{{sfn|Woolf|1927}} and ''[[The Waves]]'' (1931).{{sfn|Woolf|1931}}{{sfn|Saryazdi|2017}}

==== 1895–1904 ====
[[File:Virginia Woolf with her father, Sir Leslie Stephen.jpg|thumb|Virginia and Leslie Stephen, 1902|alt=Portrait of Virginia Woolf with he rfather Leslie Stephen in 1902, by Beresford]]
Julia Stephen fell ill with influenza in February 1895, and never properly recovered, dying on 5 May,{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Chronology |p=190}} when Virginia was 13. This was a pivotal moment in her life and the beginning of her struggles with mental illness.{{sfn|Gordon|2004}} Essentially, her life had fallen apart.&lt;ref name=MP230/&gt; The Duckworths were travelling abroad at the time of their mother's death, and Stella returned immediately to take charge and assume her role. That summer, rather than return to the memories of St Ives, the Stephens went to [[Freshwater, Isle of Wight]], where some of their mother's relatives lived. It was there that Virginia had the first of her many nervous breakdowns, and Vanessa was forced to assume some of her mother's role in caring for Virginia's mental state.{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Chronology |p=190}} Stella became engaged to Jack Hills the following year and they were married on 10 April 1897, making Virginia even more dependent on her older sister.

George Duckworth also assumed some of their mother's role, taking upon himself the task of [[debut (society)|bringing them out into society]].&lt;ref name=MP230/&gt; First Vanessa, then Virginia, in both cases an equal disaster, for it was not a rite of passage that resonated with either girl and attracted a scathing critique by Virginia regarding the conventional expectations of young upper-class women: "Society in those days was a perfectly competent, perfectly complacent, ruthless machine. A girl had no chance against its fangs. No other desires – say to paint, or to write – could be taken seriously".{{efn|The first edition has somewhat different wording "Society in those days was a very competent machine. It was convinced that girls must be changed into married women. It had no doubts, no mercy; no understanding of any other wish; of any other gift. Nothing was taken seriously"&lt;ref name=SOP135/&gt; }}{{sfn|Woolf|1940|p=157}} Rather her priorities were to escape from the Victorian conventionality of the downstairs drawing room to a "room of one's own" to pursue her writing aspirations.&lt;ref name=MP230/&gt; She would revisit this criticism in her depiction of Mrs. Ramsay stating the duties of a Victorian mother in ''To the Lighthouse'' "an unmarried woman has missed the best of life".&lt;ref name=Dunn76/&gt;

The death of Stella Duckworth on 19 July 1897, after a long illness,{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Chronology |p=191}} was a further blow to Virginia's sense of self, and the family dynamics.{{sfn|Garnett|2011|p=21}} Woolf described the period following the death of both her mother and Stella as "1897–1904 – the seven unhappy years", referring to "the lash of a random unheeding flail that pointlessly and brutally killed the two people who should, normally and naturally, have made those years, not perhaps happy but normal and natural".&lt;ref name=SOP136/&gt;&lt;ref name=MP230/&gt; In April 1902, their father became ill, and although he underwent surgery later that year he never fully recovered, dying on 22 February 1904.{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Chronology |pp=193–194}} Virginia's father's death precipitated a further breakdown.{{sfn|Banks|1998}} Later, Virginia would describe this time as one in which she was dealt successive blows as a "broken chrysalis" with wings still creased.{{sfn|Gordon|2004}} Chrysalis occurs many times in Woolf's writing but the "broken chrysalis" was an image that became a metaphor for those exploring the relationship between Woolf and grief.{{sfn|Drummer|1989}}&lt;ref name=Panken19/&gt; At his death, Leslie Stephen's net worth was £15,715 6s. 6d.{{efn|Equivalent to £900,000 in 2005{{sfn|Archives|2018a}}}} (probate 23 March 1904){{efn|STEPHEN sir Leslie of 22 Hyde Park-gate Middlesex K.C.B. probate London 23 March to George Herbert Duckworth and Gerald de L'Etang Duckworth esquires Effects £15715 6s. 6d.{{sfn|Archives|2018}}}}{{sfn|Bell|2012}}

==== Education ====
In the late 19th century, education was sharply divided along gender lines, a tradition that Virginia would note and condemn in her writing. Boys were sent to school, and in upper-middle-class families such as the Stephens, this involved private boys schools, often boarding schools, and university.&lt;ref name=Kukil38a/&gt;&lt;ref name=Dunn33/&gt;&lt;ref name="Rosner2014/3"/&gt;{{efn|George Duckworth had been sent to [[Eton College|Eton]], followed by his brother Gerald. Thoby was sent to Evelyn's [[Preparatory school (United Kingdom)|Preparatory School]], [[Hillingdon]] in January 1891 and Adrian followed the next year. Thoby went on to Public School at [[Clifton College]], Bristol in September 1894 and Adrian to [[Westminster School]] in September 1896. Thoby went up to [[Trinity College, Cambridge]] (1899–1902){{sfn|ACAD|STFN899JT}} and Adrian in 1902,{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Chronology |pp=189–192}} where George Duckworth had gone earlier (1886–1889), as had his father, Herbert Duckworth,{{sfn|ACAD|DKWT851H}} while Gerald Duckworth went up to [[Clare College, Cambridge|Clare]] (1889–1892), although their father, Leslie Stephen, was at [[Trinity Hall, Cambridge|Trinity Hall]] (1850–1854){{sfn|ACAD|STFN850L}}{{sfn|ACAD|DKWT886GH}}{{sfn|ACAD|DKWT889GD}}}} Girls, if they were afforded the luxury of education, received it from their parents, governesses and tutors.{{sfn|Burstyn|2016}} Virginia was educated by her parents who shared the duty. There was a small classroom off the back of the drawing room, with its many windows, which they found perfect for quiet writing and painting. Julia taught the children Latin, French and History, while Leslie taught them mathematics. They also received piano lessons.&lt;ref name=Curtis58/&gt; Supplementing their lessons was the children's unrestricted access to Leslie Stephen's vast library, exposing them to much of the literary canon,&lt;ref name=hauntedintro/&gt; resulting in a greater depth of reading than any of their Cambridge contemporaries, Virginia's reading being described as "greedy".&lt;ref name="Rosenbaum1/130"/&gt; Later, she would recall {{quote|Even today there may be parents who would doubt the wisdom of allowing a girl of fifteen the free run of a large and quite unexpurgated library. But my father allowed it. There were certain facts – very briefly, very shyly he referred to them. Yet "Read what you like", he said, and all his books...were to be had without asking.{{sfn|Woolf|1932a|p=72}}}} After [[Public school (United Kingdom)|public school]], the boys in the family all attended [[Cambridge University]]. The girls derived some indirect benefit from this, as the boys introduced them to their friends. Another source was the conversation of their father's friends, to whom they were exposed. Leslie Stephen described his circle as "most of the literary people of mark...clever young writers and barristers, chiefly of the radical persuasion...we used to meet on Wednesday and Sunday evenings, to smoke and drink and discuss the universe and the reform movement".&lt;ref name=License12/&gt;
{{multiple image | header = Education| align = center | direction = horizontal | total_width = 400 | float = none
|image1= Julia and the children at lessons 1894.jpg|caption1= Virginia (3rd from left) with her mother and the Stephen children at their lessons, Talland House, {{circa|1894}}{{efn|Virginia recreated this scene in ''To the Lighthouse''{{sfn|Woolf|1927}}{{sfn|Gordon|2004}}}}| alt1= Julia Stephen at Talland House supervising Thoby, Vanessa, Virginia and Adrian doing their lessons, summer 1894
|image2=St Johns House, Kensington Square (geograph 3339076).jpg|caption2=13 Kensington Square, former home of the Ladies' Department, King's College|alt2=Photograph of 13 Kensington Square where Virginia attended classes of the Ladies' Department, King's College
}}
Later, between the ages of 15 and 19, Virginia was able to pursue higher education. She took courses of study, some at degree level, in beginning and advanced Ancient Greek, intermediate Latin and German, together with continental and English history at the Ladies' Department of [[King's College London]] at nearby 13 [[Kensington Square]] between 1897 and 1901.{{efn|King's College began providing lectures for women in 1871, and formed the Ladies' Department in 1885. In 1900 women were allowed to prepare for degrees. Later it became [[Queen Elizabeth College]]{{sfn|Maggio|2010}}}} She studied Greek under the eminent scholar George Charles Winter Warr, professor of Classical Literature at King's.&lt;ref name=Prins39/&gt; In addition she had private tutoring in German, Greek and Latin. One of her Greek tutors was [[Clara Pater]] (1899–1900), who taught at King's.{{sfn|King's College, London|2017}}{{sfn|Maggio|2010}}{{sfn|Jones|Snaith|2010a}} Another was [[Janet Elizabeth Case|Janet Case]], who involved her in the [[women's rights movement]], and whose obituary Virginia would later write in 1937. Her experiences there led to her 1925 essay "On Not Knowing Greek".{{sfn|Lee|1999|pp=141–142}} Her time at King's also brought her into contact with some of the early reformers of women's higher education such as the principal of the Ladies' Department, [[Lilian Faithfull]] (one of the so-called [[steamboat ladies]]), in addition to Pater.{{sfn|Jones|Snaith|2010a}} Her sister Vanessa also enrolled at the Ladies' Department (1899–1901). Although the Stephen girls could not attend Cambridge, they were to be profoundly influenced by their brothers' experiences there. When Thoby went up to Trinity in 1899, he befriended a circle of young men, including [[Clive Bell]], [[Lytton Strachey]], Leonard Woolf (whom Virginia would later marry) and [[Saxon Sydney-Turner]], that he would soon introduce to his sisters at the [[Trinity May Ball]] in 1900.{{efn|The Stephen sisters attended the May Ball in 1900 and 1901,{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=I:192}} where they had to be chaperoned by their cousin, [[Katharine Stephen]], then librarian at [[Newnham College]]. Newnham had admitted women since 1871{{sfn|Hill-Miller|2001|p=187}}
}}&lt;ref name=Zimring160/&gt; These men formed a reading group they named the Midnight Society.{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=12}}&lt;ref name=Moggridge217/&gt;

==== Relationships with family ====
Although Virginia expressed the opinion her father was her favourite parent, and although she had only turned thirteen when her mother died, she was profoundly influenced by her mother throughout her life. It was Virginia who famously stated that "for we think back through our mothers if we are women",&lt;ref name=mothers/&gt; and invoked the image of her mother repeatedly throughout her life in her diaries,{{sfn|Woolf|1977–1984}} her letters{{sfn|Woolf|1975–1980}} and a number of her autobiographical essays, including ''Reminiscences'' (1908),{{sfn|Woolf|1908}} ''22 Hyde Park Gate'' (1921){{sfn|Woolf|1921}} and ''[[A Sketch of the Past]]'' (1940),{{sfn|Woolf|1940}} frequently evoking her memories with the words "I see her ...".&lt;ref name=Ender218/&gt; She also alludes to her childhood in her fictional writing. In ''[[To the Lighthouse]]'' (1927),{{sfn|Woolf|1927}} the artist, Lily Briscoe, attempts to paint Mrs. Ramsay, a complex character based on Julia Stephen, and repeatedly comments on the fact that she was "astonishingly beautiful".&lt;ref name=lighthouse1109/&gt; Her depiction of the life of the Ramsays in the [[Hebrides]] is an only thinly disguised account of the Stephens in Cornwall and the [[Godrevy Lighthouse]] they would visit there.{{sfn|Roe|2011}}{{sfn|Bell|1965}}&lt;ref name=Flint54/&gt; However, Woolf's understanding of her mother and family evolved considerably between 1907 and 1940, in which the somewhat distant, yet revered figure becomes more nuanced and filled in.{{sfn|Schulkind|1985|p=13}}

While her father painted Julia Stephen's work in terms of reverence, Woolf drew a sharp distinction between her mother's work and "the mischievous philanthropy which other women practise so complacently and often with such disastrous results". She describes her degree of sympathy, engagement, judgement and decisiveness, and her sense of both irony and the absurd. She recalls trying to recapture "the clear round voice, or the sight of the beautiful figure, so upright and distinct, in its long shabby cloak, with the head held at a certain angle, so that the eye looked straight out at you".&lt;ref name=Rem14/&gt; Julia Stephen dealt with her husband's depressions and his need for attention, which created resentment in her children, boosted his self-confidence, nursed her parents in their final illness, and had many commitments outside the home that would eventually wear her down. Her frequent absences and the demands of her husband instilled a sense of insecurity in her children that had a lasting effect on her daughters.&lt;ref name=Curtis17/&gt; In considering the demands on her mother, Woolf described her father as "fifteen years her elder, difficult, exacting, dependent on her" and reflected that this was at the expense of the amount of attention she could spare her young children, "a general presence rather than a particular person to a child",{{sfn|Woolf|1940|p=83}}&lt;ref name=talland/&gt; reflecting that she rarely ever spent a moment alone with her mother, "someone was always interrupting".&lt;ref name=Briggs37/&gt; Woolf was ambivalent about all this, yet eager to separate herself from this model of utter selflessness. In ''To the Lighthouse'', she describes it as "boasting of her capacity to surround and protect, there was scarcely a shell of herself left for her to know herself by; all was so lavished and spent".&lt;ref name=lighthouse44/&gt; At the same time, she admired the strengths of her mother's womanly ideals. Given Julia's frequent absences and commitments, the young Stephen children became increasingly dependent on Stella Duckworth, who emulated her mother's selflessness, as Woolf wrote "Stella was always the beautiful attendant handmaid ... making it the central duty of her life".{{sfn|Woolf|1908|p=42}}

Julia Stephen greatly admired her husband's intellect. As Woolf observed "she never belittled her own works, thinking them, if properly discharged, of equal, though other, importance with her husband's". She believed with certainty in her role as the centre of her activities, and the person who held everything together,{{sfn|Garnett|2004}} with a firm sense of what was important and valuing devotion. Of the two parents, Julia's "nervous energy dominated the family".{{sfn|Garnett|2011|p=16}} While Virginia identified most closely with her father, Vanessa stated her mother was her favourite parent.{{sfn|Gillespie|1987}} [[Angelica Garnett]] recalls how Virginia asked Vanessa which parent she preferred, although Vanessa considered it a question that "one ought not to ask", she was unequivocal in answering "Mother"{{sfn|Garnett|2011|p=16}} yet the centrality of her mother to Virginia's world is expressed in this description of her "Certainly there she was, in the very centre of that great Cathedral space which was childhood; there she was from the very first".{{sfn|Woolf|1940|p=81}} Virginia observed that her half-sister, Stella, the oldest daughter, led a life of total subservience to her mother, incorporating her ideals of love and service.{{sfn|Garnett|2011|p=20}} Virginia quickly learned, that like her father, being ill was the only reliable way of gaining the attention of her mother, who prided herself on her sickroom nursing.&lt;ref name=Curtis17/&gt;&lt;ref name=Briggs37/&gt;

Another issue the children had to deal with was Leslie Stephen's temper, Woolf describing him as "the tyrant father".{{sfn|Woolf|1940|p=116}}&lt;ref name=Rose5/&gt; Eventually, she became deeply ambivalent about her father. He had given her his ring on her eighteenth birthday and she had a deep emotional attachment as his literary heir, writing about her "great devotion for him". Yet, like Vanessa, she also saw him as victimiser and tyrant.&lt;ref name=Panken43/&gt; She had a lasting ambivalence towards him through her life, albeit one that evolved. Her adolescent image was of an "Eminent Victorian" and tyrant but as she grew older she began to realise how much of him was in her "I have been dipping into old letters and father's memoirs....so candid and reasonable and transparent—and had such a fastidious delicate mind, educated, and transparent",&lt;ref name=writer346/&gt; she wrote (22 December 1940). She was in turn both fascinated and condemnatory of Leslie Stephen " She [her mother] has haunted me: but then, so did that old wretch my father. . . . I was more like him than her, I think; and therefore more critical: but he was an adorable man, and somehow, tremendous".{{efn|3 May 1927 to Vita Sackville-West{{sfn|Woolf|1923–1928|p=374}}}}{{sfn|Gordon|2004}}&lt;ref name=BicknellIntro6/&gt;

==== Sexual abuse ====
Much has been made of Virginia's statements that she was continually sexually abused during the whole time that she lived at 22 Hyde Park Gate, as a possible cause of her mental health issues,&lt;ref name=Parkes250/&gt;{{sfn|Terr|1990}} although there are likely to be a number of contributing factors. She states that she first remembers being molested by Gerald Duckworth when she was six years old. It has been suggested that this led to a lifetime of sexual fear and resistance to
masculine authority.{{sfn|Gordon|2004}} Against a background of over-committed and distant parents, suggestions that this was a dysfunctional family must be evaluated. These include evidence of sexual abuse of the Stephen girls by their older Duckworth stepbrothers, and by their cousin, [[James Kenneth Stephen]] (1859–1892), at least of Stella Duckworth.{{efn|James Kenneth Stephen was the son of [[James Fitzjames Stephen]], Leslie Stephen's older brother}} Laura is also thought to have been abused.{{sfn|Lee|2015}} The most graphic account is by [[Louise DeSalvo]],{{sfn|DeSalvo|1989}} but other authors and reviewers have been more cautious.{{sfn|Poole|1991}}{{sfn|Beattie|1989}} Lee states that, "The evidence is strong enough, and yet ambiguous enough, to open the way for conflicting psychobiographical interpretations that draw quite different shapes of Virginia Woolf's interior life".{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=156}}

=== Bloomsbury (1904–1940) ===

==== Gordon Square (1904–1907) ====
[[File:46 Gordon Square London.jpg|thumb|upright|46 Gordon Square| alt=Photograph of 46 Gordon Square, Virginia's home from 1904 to 1907]]
On their father's death, the Stephens' first instinct was to escape from the dark house of yet more mourning, and this they did immediately, accompanied by George, travelling to [[Manorbier]], on the coast of Pembrokeshire on 27 February. There, they spent a month, and it was there that Virginia first came to realise her destiny was as a writer, as she recalls in her diary of 3 September 1922.{{sfn|Woolf|1920–1924}} They then further pursued their new found freedom by spending April in Italy and France, where they met up with [[Clive Bell]] again.{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Chronology |p=193}} Virginia then suffered her second nervous breakdown, and first suicidal attempt on 10 May, and convalesced over the next three months.{{sfn|Bell|1972|pp=89, 193}}

Before their father died, the Stephens had discussed the need to leave South Kensington in the [[West End of London|West End]], with its tragic memories and their parents' relations.{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=87}} George Duckworth was 35, his brother Gerald 33. The Stephen children were now between 24 and 20. Virginia was 22. Vanessa and Adrian decided to sell 22 Hyde Park Gate in respectable South Kensington and move to Bloomsbury. Bohemian Bloomsbury, with its characteristic leafy squares seemed sufficiently far away, geographically and socially, and was a much cheaper neighbourhood to rent in. They had not inherited much and they were unsure about their finances.{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=95}} Also, Bloomsbury was close to the [[Slade School]] which Vanessa was then attending. While Gerald was quite happy to move on and find himself a bachelor establishment, George who had always assumed the role of quasi-parent decided to accompany them, much to their dismay.{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=95}} It was then that Lady Margaret Herbert{{efn|Lady Margaret was the second daughter of [[Henry Herbert, 4th Earl of Carnarvon]].}} appeared on the scene, George proposed, was accepted and married in September, leaving the Stephens to their own devices.{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=96}}

Vanessa found a house at 46 [[Gordon Square]] in Bloomsbury, and they moved in November, to be joined by Virginia now sufficiently recovered. It was at Gordon Square that the Stephens began to regularly entertain Thoby's intellectual friends in March 1905. The circle, which largely came from the Cambridge Apostles, included writers ([[Saxon Sydney-Turner]], [[Lytton Strachey]]) and critics (Clive Bell, [[Desmond MacCarthy]]) with Thursday evening "At Homes" that became known as the ''Thursday Club'', a vision of recreating Trinity College ("Cambridge in London"&lt;ref name=Froula19/&gt;).{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=210}} This circle formed the nucleus of the intellectual circle of writers and artists known as the [[Bloomsbury Group]].{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=12}}&lt;ref name=Moggridge217/&gt;{{sfn|Bell|1972|pp=89, 194}} Later, it would include [[John Maynard Keynes]] (1907), [[Duncan Grant]] (1908), [[E.M. Forster]] (1910), [[Roger Fry]] (1910),[Leonard Woolf (1911) and [[David Garnett]] (1914).{{efn|Much later, in the 1960s, Leonard Woolf lists those people he considered as being "Old Bloomsbury" as: Vanessa and Clive Bell, Virginia and Leonard Woolf, Adrian and [[Karin Stephen]], Lytton Strachey, Maynard Keynes, Duncan Grant, E. M Forster, Sydney Saxon-Turner, Roger Fry, Desmond and [[Molly MacCarthy]] and later David Garnett and [[Julian Bell|Julian]], [[Quentin Bell|Quentin]] and [[Angelica Garnett|Angelica Bell]]. Others add [[Ottoline Morrell]], [[Dora Carrington]] and [[James Strachey|James]] and [[Alix Strachey]]. The "core" group are considered to be he Stephens and Thoby's closest Cambridge friends, Leonard Woolf, Clive Bell, Lytton Strachey and Saxon Sydney-Turner.{{sfn|Wade|2015}}{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=263}} }}{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=263}}{{sfn|Knights|2015}}
{{multiple image | header = The Stephens and their Bloomsbury Friends| align = center | direction = horizontal | total_width = 770 | float = none
| image1 =George-Beresford,-Vanessa-Bell.jpg| caption1 = Vanessa Stephen 1902|alt1=Portrait of Vanessa Stephen in 1902, by George Beresford
| image2 = Thoby Stephen by George Charles Beresford.jpeg |caption2 = Thoby Stephen 1902| alt2=Photograph of Thoby Stephen in 1902
| image3 = Adrian Karin 1914.jpg|caption3 = Adrian Stephen&lt;br /&gt;Karin Stephen 1914 |alt3=Photograph of Adrian Stephen with his wife Karin Costelloe in 1914, the year they were married
| image4 = Clive-bell-c-1913.jpg| caption4= Clive Bell 1910|alt4=Photo of Clive Bell, seated, around 1910
| image5 = Lytton Sydney17.jpg| caption5= Lytton Strachey, {{nowrap|Sydney Saxon-Turner}} 1917|alt5=Snapshot by Ray Strachey of her brother, Lytton Strachey with Sydney Saxon-Turner, reclining at the beach
| image6 = Desmond MacCarthy 1912a.jpg| caption6= Desmond MacCarthy 1912|alt=Photograph of Desmond MacCarthy sitting on steps, from 1912
}}
In 1905, Virginia and Adrian visited Portugal and Spain. Clive Bell proposed to Vanessa, but was declined, while Virginia began teaching evening classes at [[Morley College]] and Vanessa added another event to their calendar with the ''Friday Club'', dedicated to the discussion of and later exhibition of the fine arts.{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=12}}{{sfn|Bell|1972|pp=105, 194–195}} This introduced some new people into their circle, including Vanessa's friends from the Royal Academy and Slade, such as [[Henry Lamb]] and [[Gwen Darwin]] (who became secretary),&lt;ref name="Spalding2010/163"/&gt; but also the eighteen-year-old [[Katherine Laird Cox|Katherine Laird ("Ka") Cox]] (1887–1938), who was about to [[:wikt:go up|go up]] to [[Newnham College|Newnham]].{{efn|Katherine Laird ("Ka") Cox (1887–1938): The orphaned daughter of a wealthy stockbroker, Ka attended [[Newnham College]], Cambridge and was the second treasurer of the Cambridge [[Fabian Society]], one of Rupert Brooke's lovers, she became both friend and nurse to Virginia Woolf.&lt;ref name=Hale62/&gt;{{sfn|King's College, Cambridge|2018}}{{sfn|McNicol|2016}}}}{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=220}} Although Virginia did not actually meet Ka until much later, Ka would come to play an important part in her life. Ka and others brought the Bloomsbury Group into contact with another, slightly younger, group of Cambridge intellectuals to whom the Stephen sisters gave the name [[#Neo-pagans|"Neo-pagans"]]. The ''Friday Club'' continued until 1913.{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=172}}

The following year, 1906, Virginia suffered two further losses. Her cherished brother Thoby, who was only 26, died of typhoid, following a trip they had all taken to Greece, and immediately after Vanessa accepted Clive's third proposal.{{sfn|Fallon|2016}}{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=195}} Vanessa and Clive were married in February 1907 and as a couple, their interest in [[avant-garde]] art would have an important influence on Woolf's further development as an author.{{sfn|Briggs|2006a|pp=69–70}} With Vanessa's marriage, Virginia and Adrian needed to find a new home.{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=196}}

==== Fitzroy Square (1907–1911) ====
[[File:Virginia Woolf and George Bernard Shaw (5025918683).jpg|thumb|upright|29 Fitzroy Square|alt=Photo of 29 Fitzroy Square, Virginia's home from 1907 to 1910]]

Virginia moved into 29 [[Fitzroy Square]] in April 1907, a house on the west side of the street, formerly occupied by [[George Bernard Shaw]]. It was in [[Fitzrovia]], immediately to the west of Bloomsbury but still relatively close to her sister at Gordon Square. The two sisters continued to travel together, visiting Paris in March. Adrian was now to play a much larger part in Virginia's life, and they resumed the Thursday Club in October at their new home, while Gordon Square became the venue for the Play Reading Society in December. During this period, the group began to increasingly explore progressive ideas, first in speech, and then in conduct, Vanessa proclaiming in 1910 a libertarian society with sexual freedom for all.{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=170}}

Meanwhile, Virginia began work on her first novel, ''Melymbrosia'', that eventually became ''[[The Voyage Out]]'' (1915).{{sfn|Woolf|1915}}{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=196}} Vanessa's first child, [[Julian Bell|Julian]] was born in February 1908, and in September Virginia accompanied the Bells to Italy and France.{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=197}} It was during this time that Virginia's rivalry with her sister resurfaced, flirting with Clive, which he reciprocated, and which lasted on and off from 1908 to 1914, by which time her sister's marriage was breaking down.{{sfn|Garnett|2011|pp=26–28}} On 17 February 1909, Lytton Strachey proposed to Virginia and she accepted, but he then withdrew the offer.{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=13}}

It was while she was at Fitzroy Square that the question arose of Virginia needing a quiet country retreat, and she required a six-week rest cure and sought the countryside away from London as much as possible. In December, she and Adrian stayed at [[Lewes]] and started exploring the area of Sussex around the town. She started to want a place of her own, like St Ives, but closer to London. She soon found a property in nearby [[Firle]] (see [[#Sussex|below]]), maintaining a relationship with that area for the rest of her life.{{sfn|Bell|1972|pp=166–167}}{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=292}}

===== ''Dreadnought'' hoax 1910 =====
{{main|Dreadnought hoax}}
[[File:Dreadnought hoax larger photo.png|thumb|The [[Dreadnought hoax|''Dreadnought'' hoaxers]] in [[Ethiopian Empire|Abyssinian]] regalia, 1910 (Virginia Stephen far left with beard)|alt=Bearded Virginia Woolf in Ethiopian costume 1910, in the Dreadnought Hoax ]]

Several members of the group attained notoriety in 1910 with the [[Dreadnought hoax|''Dreadnought'' hoax]], which Virginia participated in disguised as a male [[Ethiopian Empire|Abyssinian]] royal. Her complete 1940 talk on the hoax was discovered and is published in the memoirs collected in the expanded edition of ''The Platform of Time'' (2008).{{sfn|Woolf|2008}}

==== Brunswick Square (1911–1912) ====
In October 1911, the lease on Fitzroy Square was running out and Virginia and Adrian decided to give up their home on Fitzroy Square in favour of a different living arrangement, moving to a four-storied house at 38 [[Brunswick Square]] in Bloomsbury proper{{efn|Demolished in 1936 to make way for the [[UCL School of Pharmacy|Pharmacy School]]&lt;ref name=Wilson181/&gt;{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=11}} A commemorative plaque on the school now marks the site (see [[#38BS|image]]){{sfn|Bloomsbury Squares|2015}} }} in November. Virginia saw it as a new opportunity; "We are going to try all kinds of experiments", she told [[Ottoline Morrell]].{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=292}} Adrian occupied the second floor, with Maynard Keynes and Duncan Grant sharing the ground floor.{{sfn|Woolf|1964|pp=50–51}} This arrangement for a single woman was considered scandalous, and George Duckworth was horrified. The house was adjacent to the [[Foundling Hospital]], much to Virginia's amusement as an unchaperoned single woman.&lt;ref name=Wilson181/&gt; Originally, Ka Cox was supposed to share in the arrangements, but opposition came from [[Rupert Brooke]], who was involved with her and pressured her to abandon the idea.{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=292}} At the house, Duncan Grant decorated Adrian Stephen's rooms (see [[#DG12|image]]).{{sfn|Grant|1912}}

=== Marriage (1912–1941) ===
[[File:Virginia and Leonard Woolf, 1912 (borderless crop).jpg|thumb|upright|[[Engagement]] photograph, Virginia and her husband [[Leonard Woolf]], 23 July 1912|alt=Virginia and Leonard on their engagement in July 1912]]
[[Leonard Woolf]] was one of Thoby Stephen's friends at Trinity College, Cambridge, and noticed the Stephen sisters in Thoby's rooms there on their visits to the May Ball in 1900 and 1901. He recalls them in "white dresses and large hats, with parasols in their hands, their beauty literally took one's breath away". To him, they were silent, "formidable and alarming".{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=209}}

Woolf did not meet Virginia formally till 17 November 1904 when he dined with the Stephens at Gordon Square, to say goodbye before leaving to take up a position with the civil service in [[Ceylon]], although she was aware of him through Thoby's stories. At that visit he noted that she was perfectly silent throughout the meal, and looked ill.{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=101}} In 1909, Lytton Strachey suggested to Woolf he should make her an offer of marriage. He did so, but received no answer. In June 1911, he returned to London on a one-year leave,{{sfn|Woolf|1964|p=15}} but did not go back to Ceylon. In England again, Leonard renewed his contacts with family and friends. Three weeks after arriving he dined with Vanessa and Clive Bell at Gordon Square on 3 July, where they were later joined by Virginia and other members of what would later be called "Bloomsbury", and Leonard dates the group's formation to that night.{{sfn|Woolf|1964|pp=15, 26, 33}} In September, Virginia asked Leonard to join her at Little Talland House at Firle in Sussex for a long weekend. After that weekend, they began seeing each other more frequently.{{sfn|Woolf|1964|p=48}}

On 4 December 1911, Leonard moved into the ménage on Brunswick Square, occupying a bedroom and sitting room on the fourth floor, and started to see Virginia constantly and by the end of the month had decided he was in love with her.{{sfn|Woolf|1964|pp=51–52}} On 11 January 1912, he proposed to her; she asked for time to consider, so he asked for an extension of his leave and, on being refused, offered his resignation on 25 April, effective 20 May.{{sfn|Woolf|1964|p=68}} He continued to pursue Virginia, and in a letter of 1 May 1912 (''which see''){{sfn|The American Reader}} she explained why she did not favour a marriage. However, on 29 May, Virginia told Leonard that she wished to marry him, and they were married on 10 August at the [[St Pancras, London|St Pancras]] [[Register Office]].{{sfn|History|2018}}{{sfn|Woolf|1964|p=69}} It was during this time that Leonard first became aware of Virginia's precarious mental state.{{sfn|Woolf|1964|p=75}} The Woolfs continued to live at Brunswick Square until October 1912, when they moved to a small flat at 13 [[Clifford's Inn]], further to the east (subsequently demolished).{{sfn|Todd|2001|pp=11, 13}} Despite his low material status (Woolf referring to Leonard during their engagement as a "penniless Jew"), the couple shared a close bond. Indeed, in 1937, Woolf wrote in her diary: "Love-making—after 25 years can't bear to be separate ... you see it is enormous pleasure being wanted: a wife. And our marriage so complete."{{sfn|Woolf|1936–1941}} However, Virginia made a suicide attempt in 1913.{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=13}}

In October 1914, Leonard and Virginia Woolf moved away from Bloomsbury and central London to [[Richmond, London|Richmond]], living at 17 The Green, a home discussed by Leonard in his autobiography ''Beginning Again'' (1964).{{sfn|Woolf|1964}} In early March 1915, the couple moved again, to nearby Hogarth House, Paradise Road,{{sfn|Richmond|2015}} after which they named their publishing house.{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=11}} Virginia's first novel, ''The Voyage Out''{{sfn|Woolf|1915}} was published in 1915, followed by another suicide attempt. Despite the introduction of [[conscription]] in 1916, Leonard was exempted on medical grounds.{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=11}}{{sfn|Hughes|2014}}

Between 1924 and 1940, the Woolfs returned to Bloomsbury, taking out a ten-year lease at 52 [[Tavistock Square]],{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=13}} from where they ran the [[Hogarth Press]] from the basement, where Virginia also had her writing room, and is commemorated with a bust of her in the square (see [[#Legacy|illustration]]).{{sfn|Garnett|2011|pp=52–54}} 1925 saw the publication of ''Mrs Dalloway''{{sfn|Woolf|1925}} in May followed by her collapse while at Charleston in August. In 1927, her next novel, ''To the Lighthouse'',{{sfn|Woolf|1927}} was published, and the following year she lectured on ''Women &amp; Fiction'' at Cambridge University and published ''Orlando''{{sfn|Woolf|1928}} in October. Her two Cambridge lectures then became the basis for her major essay ''A Room of One's Own''{{sfn|Woolf|1929}} in 1929.{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=13}} Virginia wrote only one drama, ''[[Freshwater (play)|Freshwater]]'', based on her great-aunt [[Julia Margaret Cameron]], and produced at her sister's studio on [[Fitzroy Street, London|Fitzroy Street]] in 1935.{{sfn|Woolf|1935}} 1936 saw another collapse of her health following the completion of ''[[The Years]]''.{{sfn|Woolf|1936a}}{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=13}}
	
The Woolf's final residence in London was at 37 [[Mecklenburgh Square]] (1939–1940), destroyed during [[the Blitz]] in September 1940; a month later their previous home on Tavistock Square was also destroyed. After that, they made Sussex their permanent home.{{sfn|Brooks|2012a}} For descriptions and illustrations of all Virginia Woolf's London homes, see [[Jean Moorcroft Wilson]]'s book ''Virginia Woolf, Life and London: A Biography of Place'' (pub. Cecil Woolf, 1987).{{sfn|Wilson|1987}}

==== Hogarth Press (1917–1938) ====
{{main|Hogarth Press}}
{{multiple image
| header = The Woolfs' homes in Richmond
| align = center
| direction = horizontal
| total_width = 400
| float = none
| image1 = 17 The Green Richmond, 2017.jpg
| caption1 = 17 The Green
| alt1 = The Woolfs'  home at 17 The Green
| width1 = 401
| image2 = Hogarth Press House, Richmond, Surrey.jpg
| caption2 = Hogarth House
| alt2 = Hogarth House
| width2 = 640
}}
[[File:Shakespeare Plays hand bound by Virginia Woolf.JPG|thumb|Shelf of [[Shakespeare]] plays hand-bound by Virginia Woolf in her bedroom at [[Monk's House]]{{efn|It has been suggested that Woolf bound books to help cope with her depression, as is hinted at in her writing: "A great part of every day is not lived consciously. One walks, eats, sees things, deals with what has to be done; the broken vacuum cleaner; ... cooking dinner; bookbinding."{{sfn|Sim|2016}}}}]]
Virginia had taken up book-binding as a pastime in October 1901, at the age of 19,{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Chronology |p=192}}{{sfn|Heyes|2016}} and the Woolfs had been discussing setting up a publishing house for some time, and at the end of 1916 started making plans. Having discovered that they were not eligible to enroll in the St Bride School of Printing, they started purchasing supplies after seeking advice from the Excelsior Printing Supply Company on [[Farringdon Road]] in March 1917, and soon they had a printing press set up on their dining room table at Hogarth House, and the [[Hogarth Press]] was born.{{sfn|Heyes|2016}}

Their first publication was ''Two Stories'' in July 1917, inscribed ''Publication No. 1'', and consisted of two short stories, "The Mark on the Wall"{{sfn|Woolf|2017a}} by Virginia Woolf and ''Three Jews'' by Leonard Woolf. The work consisted of 32 pages, hand bound and sewn, and illustrated by [[woodcuts]] designed by [[Dora Carrington]]. The illustrations were a success, leading Virginia to remark that the press was "specially good at printing pictures, and we see that we must make a practice of always having pictures" (13 July 1917). The process took two and a half months with a production run of 150 copies.{{sfn|British Library|2018c}} Other short short stories followed, including ''[[Kew Gardens (short story)|Kew Gardens]]'' (1919){{sfn|Woolf|1919b}} with a [[woodblock printing|woodblock]] by Vanessa Bell as [[book frontispiece|frontispiece]].{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=13}} Subsequently, Bell added further illustrations, adorning each page of the text.{{sfn|British Library|2018d}}

The press subsequently published Virginia's novels along with works by [[T.S. Eliot]], [[Laurens van der Post]], and others.{{sfn|Messud|2006}} The Press also commissioned works by contemporary artists, including [[Dora Carrington]] and [[Vanessa Bell]]. Woolf believed that to break free of a patriarchal society women writers needed a "room of their own" to develop and often fantasised about an "Outsider's Society" where women writers would create a [[Safe space|virtual private space for themselves]] via their writings to develop a feminist critique of society.{{sfn|McTaggart|2010}} Though Woolf never created the "Outsider's society", the Hogarth Press was the closest approximation as the Woolfs chose to publish books by writers that took unconventional points of view to form a reading community.{{sfn|McTaggart|2010}} Initially the press concentrated on small experimental publications, of little interest to large commercial publishers. Until 1930, Woolf often helped her husband print the Hogarth books as the money for employees was not there.{{sfn|McTaggart|2010}} Virginia relinquished her interest in 1938, following a third attempted suicide. After it was bombed in September 1940, the press was moved to [[Letchworth]] for the remainder of the war.{{sfn|Eagle|Carnell|1981|p=135}} Both the Woolfs were internationalists and pacifists who believed that promoting understanding between peoples was the best way to avoid another world war and chose quite consciously to publish works by foreign authors of whom the British reading public were unaware.{{sfn|McTaggart|2010}} The first non-British author to be published was the Soviet writer [[Maxim Gorky]], the book ''Reminiscences of Leo Nikolaiovich Tolstoy'' in 1920, dealing with his friendship with Count [[Leo Tolstoy]].{{sfn|Heyes|2016}}

==== Memoir Club (1920–1941) ====
{{main|Memoir Club}}
{{multiple image | header = ''Bloomsberries''| align = center | direction = horizontal | total_width = 600 | float = none
| image1 = Mary ('Molly') MacCarthy1915 (3x4 crop).jpg| caption1 = [[Mary MacCarthy]] and son 1915|alt1=Photo of Mary MacCarthy with her son Michael in 1915. Taken by Lady Ottoline Morrell |width1=
| image2 = EMForster1917.jpg| caption2 = [[E.M. Forster]] 1917| alt2 =Portrait of E M Forster 1917| width2=
| image3 = Duncan Grant with John Maynard Keynes.jpg| caption3 = [[Duncan Grant]] (L)&lt;br /&gt;[[John Maynard Keynes]] 1912| alt3=Photo of Duncan Grant talking to John Maynard Keynes in 1912| width3=
| image4 = Roger Fry (Coburn) 1913 (cropped).jpg| caption4 = [[Roger Fry]] 1913|alt4= Portrait of Roger Fry in 2013| width4=
| image5 = David Garnett.jpg| caption5 = [[David Garnett]] {{circa|1902}}|alt5= Portrait of David Garnett, aged about 20|width5=
}}
1920 saw a postwar reconstitution of the Bloomsbury Group, under the title of the [[Memoir Club]], which as the name suggests focussed on self-writing, in the manner of [[Proust]]'s ''[[A La Recherche]]'', and inspired some of the more influential books of the 20th century. The Group, which had been scattered by the war, was reconvened by [[Molly MacCarthy|Mary ('Molly') MacCarthy]] who called them "Bloomsberries", and operated under rules derived from the [[Cambridge Apostles]], an elite university debating society that a number of them had been members of. These rules emphasised candour and openness. Among the 125 memoirs presented, Virginia contributed three that were published posthumously in 1976, in the autobiographical anthology ''[[Moments of Being]]''.{{sfn|Woolf|1985}} These were ''22 Hyde Park Gate'' (1921), ''Old Bloomsbury'' (1922) and ''Am I a Snob?'' (1936).{{sfn|Rosenbaum|Haule|2014}}

==== Vita Sackville-West (1922–1941) ====
[[File:Vita Sackville-West at Monk's House.jpg|thumb|[[Vita Sackville-West]] at Monk's House {{circa|1934}}|alt=Photo of Vita Sackville-West in armchair at Virginia's home at Monk's House, smoking and with dog on her lap]]
The [[ethos]] of the Bloomsbury group encouraged a liberal approach to sexuality, and on 14 December 1922{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Vol. II |p=235}} Woolf met the writer and gardener [[Vita Sackville-West]],{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=13}} wife of [[Harold Nicolson]], while dining with Clive Bell. Writing in her diary the next day, she referred to meeting "the lovely gifted aristocratic Sackville West".{{sfn|Woolf|1920–1924|p=216}} At the time, Sackville-West was the more successful writer as both poet and novelist,{{sfn|Hussey|2006}} commercially and critically, and it was not until after Woolf's death that she became considered the better writer.{{sfn|Smith|2006}} After a tentative start, they began a sexual relationship, which, according to Sackville-West in a letter to her husband on 17 August 1926, was only twice consummated.{{sfn|Boynton|Malin|2005|p=580}} The relationship reached its peak between 1925 and 1928, evolving into more of a friendship through the 1930s,&lt;ref name=Cramer126/&gt; though Woolf was also inclined to brag of her affairs with other women within her intimate circle, such as [[Sibyl Colefax]] and [[Comtesse de Polignac]].{{sfn|Garnett|2011|p=131}} This period of intimacy was to prove fruitful for both authors, Woolf producing three novels, ''To the Lighthouse'' (1927), ''Orlando'' (1928) and ''The Waves'' (1931) as well as a number of essays, including "[[Mr. Bennett and Mrs. Brown]]" (1924){{sfn|Woolf|1924}} and "[[A Letter to a Young Poet]]" (1932).{{sfn|Woolf|1932}}{{sfn|Hussey|2006}}

Sackville-West worked tirelessly to lift Woolf's self-esteem, encouraging her not to view herself as a quasi-reclusive inclined to sickness who should hide herself away from the world, but rather offered praise for her liveliness and wit, her health, her intelligence and achievements as a writer.{{sfn|DeSalvo|1982}} Sackville-West led Woolf to reappraise herself, developing a more positive self-image, and the feeling that her writings were the products of her strengths rather than her weakness.{{sfn|DeSalvo|1982}} Starting at the age of 15, Woolf had believed the diagnosis by her father and his doctor that reading and writing were deleterious to her nervous condition, requiring a regime of physical labour such as gardening to prevent a total nervous collapse. This led Woolf to spend much time obsessively engaging in such physical labour.{{sfn|DeSalvo|1982}}

Sackville-West was the first to argue to Woolf she had been misdiagnosed, and that it was far better to engage in reading and writing to calm her nerves—advice that was taken.{{sfn|DeSalvo|1982}} Under the influence of Sackville-West, Woolf learned to deal with her nervous ailments by switching between various forms of intellectual activities such as reading, writing and book reviews, instead of spending her time in physical activities that sapped her strength and worsened her nerves.{{sfn|DeSalvo|1982}} Sackville-West chose the financially struggling Hogarth Press as her publisher to assist the Woolfs financially. ''Seducers in Ecuador'', the first of the novels by Sackville-West published by Hogarth, was not a success, selling only 1500 copies in its first year, but the next Sackville-West novel they published, ''The Edwardians'', was a best-seller that sold 30,000 copies in its first six months.{{sfn|DeSalvo|1982}} Sackville-West's novels, though not typical of the Hogarth Press, saved Hogarth, taking them from the red into the black.{{sfn|DeSalvo|1982}} However, Woolf was not always appreciative of the fact that it was Sackville-West's books that kept the Hogarth Press profitable, writing dismissively in 1933 of her "servant girl" novels.{{sfn|DeSalvo|1982}} The financial security allowed by the good sales of Sackville-West's novels in turn allowed Woolf to engage in more experimental work, such as ''[[The Waves]]'', as Woolf had to be cautious when she depended upon Hogarth entirely for her income.{{sfn|DeSalvo|1982}}

In 1928, Woolf presented Sackville-West with ''[[Orlando: A Biography|Orlando]]'',{{sfn|Woolf|1928}} a fantastical biography in which the eponymous hero's life spans three centuries and both sexes. It was published in October, shortly after the two women spent a week travelling together in France, that September.{{citation needed|date=February 2020}} [[Nigel Nicolson]], Vita Sackville-West's son, wrote, "The effect of Vita on Virginia is all contained in ''Orlando'', the longest and most charming love letter in literature, in which she explores Vita, weaves her in and out of the centuries, tosses her from one sex to the other, plays with her, dresses her in furs, lace and emeralds, teases her, flirts with her, drops a veil of mist around her."{{sfn|Blamires|1983|p=307}} After their affair ended, the two women remained friends until Woolf's death in 1941. Virginia Woolf also remained close to her surviving siblings, Adrian and Vanessa; Thoby had died of typhoid fever at the age of 26.{{sfn|Briggs|2006a|p=13}}

=== {{anchor|Sussex}}Sussex (1911–1941) ===
[[File:VStephenKCox.jpg|thumb|upright|Virginia Stephen (L) with [[Katherine Cox]], Asham 1912|alt=Virginia Stephen with Katherine Cox at Asham in 1912]]
Virginia was needing a country retreat to escape to, and on 24 December 1910, she found a house for rent in [[Firle]], Sussex, near [[Lewes]] (see [[#ESmap|Map]]). She obtained a lease and took possession of the house the following month, naming it 'Little Talland House', after their childhood home in Cornwall, although it was actually a new red gabled villa on the main street opposite the village hall.{{efn|Virginia was somewhat disparaging about the exterior of Little Talland House, describing it as an "eyesore" (Letter to Violet Dickinson 29 January 1911) and "inconceivably ugly, done up in patches of post-impressionist colour" (Letters, no. 561, April 1911). However she and Vanessa decorated the interior, "staining the floors the colours of the Atlantic in a storm" (Letters, no. 552, 24 January 1911){{sfn|Wilkinson|2001}}}}{{sfn|Bell|1972|pp=166–167}}{{sfn|Wilkinson|2001}} The lease was a short one, and in October, she and Leonard Woolf found Asham House{{efn|Sometimes spelled "Asheham". Demolished 1994{{sfn|Brooks|2012a}}}} at Asheham a few miles to the west, while walking along the Ouse from Firle.{{sfn|Woolf|1964|p=56}} The house, at the end of a tree-lined road was a strange beautiful Regency-Gothic house in a lonely location.{{sfn|Brooks|2012a}} She described it as "flat, pale, serene, yellow-washed", without electricity or water and allegedly haunted.{{sfn|Eagle|Carnell|1981|p=9}} She took out a five-year lease{{sfn|Woolf|1964|p=56}} jointly with Vanessa in the New Year, and they moved into it in February 1912, holding a house warming party on the 9th.{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Chronology |pp=199–201}}{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=176}}

It was at Asham that the Woolfs spent their wedding night later that year. At Asham, she recorded the events of the weekends and holidays they spent there in her ''Asham Diary'', part of which was later published as ''A Writer's Diary'' in 1953.{{sfn|Woolf|1953}} In terms of creative writing, ''[[The Voyage Out]]'' was completed there, and much of ''[[Night and Day (Woolf novel)|Night and Day]]''.{{sfn|Woolf|1919a}} Asham provided Woolf with well needed relief from the pace of London life and was where she found a happiness that she expressed in her diary of 5 May 1919 "Oh, but how happy we've been at Asheham! It was a most melodious time. Everything went so freely; – but I can't analyse all the sources of my joy".{{sfn|Asham|2018}} Asham was also the inspiration for ''A Haunted House'' (1921–1944),{{sfn|Woolf|1964|p=57}}&lt;ref name=haunted9/&gt;{{sfn|Eagle|Carnell|1981|p=9}} and was painted by members of the Bloomsbury Group, including Vanessa Bell and Roger Fry.{{sfn|Fry|1913}} It was during these times at Asham that Ka Cox (seen here) started to devote herself to Virginia and become very useful.{{sfn|Bell |1972|p=1:183}}

{{multiple image | header = Life in Sussex| align = center | direction = horizontal | total_width =800  | float = none
|image1= Little Talland House.jpg|caption1= Little Talland House, [[Firle]] | alt1=Photo of Little Talland House, Firle, East Sussex. Leased by Virginia Woolf in 1911
|image2=Asheham House, nr Beddingham ca. 1914.jpg| caption2 = Asham House, [[Beddingham]] | alt2= Photo of Asham house in 1914
|image3=The Round House, Lewes, 2017.jpg|caption3=The Round House, Lewes |alt3=The Round House in Lewes
|image4=Monk's House, Rodmell, UK.jpg|caption4=[[Monk's House]], Rodmell |alt4=Monk's House in Rodmell}}
While at Asham Leonard and Virginia found a farmhouse in 1916, that was to let, about four miles away, which they thought would be ideal for her sister. Eventually, Vanessa came down to inspect it, and moved in&lt;!--not a mistake--&gt; in October of that year, taking it as a summer home for her family. The [[Charleston Farmhouse]] was to become the summer gathering place for the literary and artistic circle of the Bloomsbury Group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Crafter|first=Cate|date=2021-06-03|title=Discover the Bloomsbury Group's connection to Sussex|url=https://www.greatbritishlife.co.uk/travel/places-to-visit/the-bloomsbury-group-sussex-connection-8009262|access-date=2021-07-02|website=Great British Life|language=en-UK}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Vol II: 1915–1918}}

After the end of the war, in 1918, the Woolfs were given a year's notice by the landlord, who needed the house. In mid-1919, "in despair", they purchased "a very strange little house" for £300, the Round House in Pipe Passage, Lewes, a converted windmill.{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Chronology |pp=199–201}}{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=176}}{{sfn|Woolf|1964|p=57}} No sooner had they bought the Round House, than [[Monk's House]] in nearby [[Rodmell]], came up for auction, a [[weatherboarded]] house with oak beamed rooms, said to be 15th or 16th century. The Leonards favoured the latter because of its orchard and garden, and sold the Round House, to purchase Monk's House for £700.{{sfn|Maggio|2009}}{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=13}} Monk's House also lacked water and electricity, but came with an acre of garden, and had a view across the Ouse towards the hills of the [[South Downs]]. Leonard Woolf describes this view (and the amenities){{sfn|Woolf|1964|p=60}} as being unchanged since the days of [[Chaucer]].{{sfn|Eagle|Carnell|1981|p=228}} From 1940, it became their permanent home after their London home was bombed, and Virginia continued to live there until her death. Meanwhile, Vanessa made Charleston her permanent home in 1936.{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Vol. II: 1915–1918}} It was at Monk's House that Virginia completed ''[[Between the Acts]]''{{sfn|Woolf|1941}} in early 1941, followed by a further breakdown directly resulting in her suicide on 28 March 1941, the novel being published posthumously later that year.{{sfn|Todd|2001|p=13}}

=== {{anchor|Neo-pagans}}The Neo-pagans (1911–1912) ===
[[File:Neopagans1911 (cropped).jpg|thumb|[[Noël Olivier]]; Maitland Radford; Virginia Stephen; [[Rupert Brooke]] camping on [[Dartmoor]] August 1911|alt=Group of neopagans, Noel Olivier; Maitland Radford; Virginia Woolf; Rupert Brooke, sitting in front of a farm gate on Dartmoor in August 1911]]
During her time in Firle, Virginia became better acquainted with [[Rupert Brooke]] and his group of ''[[Modern Paganism|Neo-Pagans]]'', pursuing socialism, vegetarianism, exercising outdoors and alternative life styles, including [[social nudity]]. They were influenced by the ethos of [[Bedales]], [[Fabianism]] and [[Percy Bysshe Shelley|Shelley]]. The women wore sandals, socks, open neck shirts and head-scarves. Although she had some reservations, Woolf was involved with their activities for a while, fascinated by their bucolic innocence in contrast to the sceptical intellectualism of Bloomsbury, which earned her the nickname "The Goat" from her brother Adrian.{{efn|"Goat" was also a term of ridicule that George Duckworth used towards Virginia, "he always called me 'the poor goat' "(Letter to Vanessa 13 May 1921){{sfn|Woolf|1912–1922}} }} While Woolf liked to make much of a weekend she spent with Brooke at the vicarage in [[Grantchester]], including swimming in the pool there, it appears to have been principally a literary assignation. They also shared a psychiatrist in the name of [[Maurice Craig (psychiatrist)|Maurice Craig]].&lt;ref name=Jones228/&gt; Through the ''Neo-Pagans'', she finally met [[Ka Cox]] on a weekend in Oxford in January 1911, who had been part of the ''Friday Club'' circle and now became her friend and played an important part in dealing with her illnesses. Virginia nicknamed her "Bruin". At the same time, she found herself dragged into a [[Love triangle|triangular]] relationship involving Ka, [[Jacques Raverat]] and [[Gwen Raverat|Gwen Darwin]]. She became resentful of the other couple, Jacques and Gwen, who married later in 1911, not the outcome Virginia had predicted or desired. They would later be referred to in both ''To the Lighthouse'' and ''The Years''. The exclusion she felt evoked memories of both Stella Duckworth's marriage and her triangular involvement with Vanessa and Clive.{{sfn|Lee|1999|pp=293–297}}

The two groups eventually fell out. Brooke pressured Ka into withdrawing from joining Virginia's ''ménage'' on Brunswick Square in late 1911, calling it a "bawdy-house" and by the end of 1912 he had vehemently turned against Bloomsbury. Later, she would write sardonically about Brooke, whose premature death resulted in his idealisation, and express regret about "the Neo-Paganism at that stage of my life". Virginia was deeply disappointed when Ka married [[William Edward Arnold-Forster]] in 1918, and became increasingly critical of her.{{sfn|Lee|1999|pp=293–297}}

=== {{anchor|Mental health}}Mental health ===

Much examination has been made of Woolf's mental health (e.g., see [[#Mental health biblio|Mental health bibliography]]). From the age of 13, following the death of her mother, Woolf suffered periodic mood swings from severe depression to manic excitement, including psychotic episodes, which the family referred to as her "madness".{{sfn|Garnett|2011|p=114}}{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=172}} However, as [[Hermione Lee]] points out, Woolf was not "mad"; she was merely a woman who suffered from and struggled with illness for much of her relatively short life, a woman of "exceptional courage, intelligence and stoicism", who made the best use, and achieved the best understanding she could of that illness.{{efn|Virginia Woolf used the term "mad" to refer to her psychotic episodes, resenting Ka Cox in later years because she made her "self-conscious; remembering how she had seen me mad" as she wrote in her diary on 25 May 1938 on learning of Ka's death{{sfn|Woolf|1936–1941|p=143}}{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=707}}}}{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=175}} 

Psychiatrists today contend that her illness constitutes [[bipolar disorder]] (manic-depressive illness).{{sfn|Dalsimer|2004}} Her mother's death in 1895, "the greatest disaster that could happen",&lt;ref name="Rem40" /&gt;{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=40}} precipitated a crisis of alternating excitability and depression accompanied by irrational fears, for which their family doctor, Dr. Seton, prescribed rest, stopping lessons and writing, and regular walks supervised by Stella.{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=45}} Yet just two years later, Stella too was dead, bringing on her next crisis in 1897, and her first expressed wish for death at the age of fifteen, writing in her diary that October that "death would be shorter &amp; less painful". She then stopped keeping a diary for some time. This was a scenario she would later recreate in "Time Passes" (''To the Lighthouse'', 1927).{{sfn|Woolf|1927}}&lt;ref name="Gordon51" /&gt;

The death of her father in 1904 provoked her most alarming collapse, on 10 May, when she threw herself out of a window and she was briefly institutionalised{{sfn|Meyer|Osborne|1982}} under the care of her father's friend, the eminent psychiatrist [[George Savage (physician)|George Savage]]. Savage blamed her education—frowned on by many at the time as unsuitable for women{{sfn|Burstyn|2016}}—for her illness.{{sfn|Banks|1998}}{{sfn|Adams|2016}} She spent time recovering at the house of Stella's friend Violet Dickinson, and at her aunt [[Caroline Emelia Stephen|Caroline's]] house in Cambridge,{{sfn|Lewis|2000}} and by January 1905, Dr Savage considered her "cured".{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=220}} Violet, seventeen years older than Virginia, became one of her closest friends and one of her more effective nurses. She characterised this as a "romantic friendship" (Letter to Violet 4 May 1903).{{sfn|Woolf|1888–1912}}{{efn|In her correspondence, Woolf would address Violet as "My Beloved Woman", and wrote "this romantic friendship ought to be preserved".&lt;ref name=Lilienfeld40/&gt;}} Her brother Thoby's death in 1906 marked a "decade of deaths” that ended her childhood and adolescence. From then on, her life was punctuated by urgent voices from the grave, that at times seemed more real than her visual reality.{{sfn|Gordon|2004}}

On Dr. Savage's recommendation, Virginia spent three short periods in 1910, 1912, and 1913 at Burley House at 15 Cambridge Park, [[Twickenham]] (see [[#Street tour|image]]), described as "a private nursing home for women with nervous disorder" run by Miss Jean Thomas.{{sfn|Pearce|2007}}{{sfn|Snodgrass|2015}} By the end of February 1910, she was becoming increasingly restless, and Dr. Savage suggested being away from London. Vanessa rented ''Moat House,'' outside Canterbury, in June, but there was no improvement, so Dr. Savage sent her to Burley for a "rest cure". This involved partial isolation, deprivation of literature, and force-feeding, and after six weeks she was able to convalesce in Cornwall and Dorset during the autumn. 

She loathed the experience; writing to her sister on 28 July,{{sfn|Woolf|1910}} she described how she found the phony religious atmosphere stifling and the institution ugly, and informed Vanessa that to escape "I shall soon have to jump out of a window."{{sfn|Gordon|2004}} The threat of being sent back would later lead to her contemplating suicide.&lt;ref name="Harris34" /&gt; Despite her protests, Savage would refer her back in 1912 for insomnia and in 1913 for depression. 

On emerging from ''Burley House'' in September 1913, she sought further opinions from two other physicians on the 13th, Maurice Wright, and [[Henry Head]], who had been [[Henry James]]' physician. Both recommended she return to ''Burley House''. Distraught, she returned home and attempted suicide by taking an overdose of 100 [[grain (unit)|grains]] of [[Barbital|veronal]] (a barbiturate) and nearly dying,&lt;ref name="Gordon52" /&gt; had she not been found by Ka Cox, who summoned help. 

On recovery, she went to ''Dalingridge Hall'', George Duckworth's home in [[East Grinstead]], Sussex, to convalesce on 30 September, accompanied by Ka Cox and a nurse,{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Vol. II |p=17}} returning to ''Asham'' on 18 November with Cox and Janet Case. She remained unstable over the next two years, with another incident involving veronal that she claimed was an "accident", and consulted another psychiatrist in April 1914, [[Maurice Craig (psychiatrist)|Maurice Craig]], who explained that she was not sufficiently psychotic to be certified or committed to an institution. 

The rest of the summer of 1914 went better for her, and they moved to Richmond, but in February 1915, just as ''The Voyage Out'' was due to be published, she relapsed once more, and remained in poor health for most of that year.{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=330}} Then, despite Miss Thomas's gloomy prognosis, she began to recover, following 20 years of ill health.{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Vol. II |p=228}}&lt;ref name="Gordon53" /&gt; Nevertheless, there was a feeling among those around her that she was now permanently changed, and not for the better.{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Vol. II |pp=26–27}}

Over the rest of her life, she suffered recurrent bouts of depression. In 1940, a number of factors appeared to overwhelm her. Her biography of Roger Fry{{sfn|Woolf|1940a}} had been published in July, and she had been disappointed in its reception. The horrors of war depressed her, and their London homes had been destroyed in the Blitz in September and October. Woolf had completed ''Between the Acts'' (published posthumously in 1941){{sfn|Woolf|1941}} in November, and completing a novel was frequently accompanied by exhaustion.{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=224}} Her health became increasingly a matter of concern, culminating in her decision to end her life on 28 March 1941.{{sfn|Snodgrass|2015}}

Though this instability would frequently affect her social life, she was able to continue her literary productivity with few interruptions throughout her life. Woolf herself provides not only a vivid picture of her symptoms in her diaries and letters, but also her response to the demons that haunted her and at times made her long for death:{{sfn|Dalsimer|2004}} "But it is always a question whether I wish to avoid these glooms... These 9 weeks give one a plunge into deep waters... One goes down into the well &amp; nothing protects one from the assault of truth."{{sfn|Woolf|1925–1930|p=112}}

Psychiatry had little to offer Woolf, but she recognised that writing was one of the behaviours that enabled her to cope with her illness:{{sfn|Dalsimer|2004}} "The only way I keep afloat... is by working... Directly I stop working I feel that I am sinking down, down. And as usual, I feel that if I sink further I shall reach the truth."{{sfn|Woolf|1925–1930|p=235}} Sinking under water was Woolf's metaphor for both the effects of depression and psychosis— but also for finding truth, and ultimately was her choice of death.{{sfn|Dalsimer|2004}} 

Throughout her life, Woolf struggled, without success, to find meaning in her illness: on the one hand, an impediment, on the other, something she visualised as an essential part of who she was, and a necessary condition of her art.{{sfn|Dalsimer|2004}} Her experiences informed her work, such as the character of Septimus Warren Smith in ''Mrs Dalloway'' (1925),{{sfn|Woolf|1925}} who, like Woolf, was haunted by the dead, and ultimately takes his own life rather than be admitted to a sanitorium.{{sfn|Gordon|2004}}

Leonard Woolf relates how during the 30 years they were married, they consulted many doctors in the [[Harley Street]] area, and although they were given a diagnosis of [[neurasthenia]], he felt they had little understanding of the causes or nature. The proposed solution was simple—as long as she lived a quiet life without any physical or mental exertion, she was well. On the other hand, any mental, emotional, or physical strain resulted in a reappearance of her symptoms. These began with a headache, followed by insomnia and thoughts that started to race. Her remedy was simple, to retire to bed in a darkened room, eat, and drink plenty of milk, following which the symptoms slowly subsided.{{sfn|Woolf|1964|pp=75–76}}

Modern scholars, including her nephew and biographer, [[Quentin Bell]],{{sfn|Bell|1972|p=44}} have suggested her breakdowns and subsequent recurring depressive periods were influenced by the sexual abuse which she and her sister Vanessa were subjected to by their half-brothers [[George Herbert Duckworth|George]] and [[Gerald Duckworth]] (which Woolf recalls in her autobiographical essays "[[A Sketch of the Past]]" and "22 Hyde Park Gate") (see [[#Sexual abuse|Sexual abuse]]). Biographers point out that when Stella died in 1897, there was no counterbalance to control George's predation, and his nighttime prowling. Virginia describes him as her first lover, "The old ladies of Kensington and Belgravia never knew that George Duckworth was not only father and mother, brother and sister to those poor Stephen girls; he was their lover also."{{sfn|Woolf|1921|p=178}}{{sfn|Gordon|2004}}

It is likely that other factors also played a part. It has been suggested that these include [[genetic predisposition]], for both trauma and family history have been implicated in bipolar disorder.{{sfn|Boeira et al|2016}} Virginia's father, Leslie Stephen, suffered from depression, and her half-sister Laura was institutionalised. Many of Virginia's symptoms, including persistent headache, insomnia, irritability, and anxiety, resembled those of her father.{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=72}} Another factor is the pressure she placed upon herself in her work; for instance, her breakdown of 1913 was at least partly triggered by the need to finish ''The Voyage Out''.{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=326}}

Virginia herself hinted that her illness was related to how she saw the repressed position of women in society, when she wrote in ''A Room of One's Own'' that had Shakespeare had a sister of equal genius, she "would certainly have gone crazed, shot herself, or ended her days in some lonely cottage outside the village, half witch, half wizard, feared and mocked at". These inspirations emerged from what Woolf referred to as her lava of madness, describing her time at Burley{{sfn|Gordon|2004}}&lt;ref name="Montross61" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Hague259" /&gt; in a 1930 letter to [[Ethel Smyth]]:
{{quote|As an experience, madness is terrific I can assure you, and not to be sniffed at; and in its lava I still find most of the things I write about. It shoots out of one everything shaped, final, not in mere driblets, as sanity does. And the six months—not three—that I lay in bed taught me a good deal about what is called oneself.{{sfn|Woolf|1929–1931|loc=2194: 22 June 1930; p. 180}} }}

Thomas Caramagno{{sfn|Caramagno|1992}} and others,{{sfn|Koutsantoni|2012}} in discussing her illness, oppose the "neurotic-genius" way of looking at mental illness, where creativity and mental illness are conceptualised as linked rather than antithetical.{{sfn|Jamison|1996}}{{sfn|Caramagno|1992}} [[Stephen Trombley]] describes Woolf as having a confrontational relationship with her doctors, and possibly being a woman who is a "victim of male medicine", referring to the lack of understanding, particularly at the time, about mental illness.{{sfn|Trombley|1980}}{{sfn|Trombley|1981}}

=== Death ===
[[File:Handwriting-virginia-woolf-10921544-600-870.jpg|thumb|upright|Virginia Woolf's suicide letter to her husband. (Reading by [[Juliet Stevenson]]){{sfn|Stevenson|2015}}]]
After completing the manuscript of her last novel (posthumously published), ''[[Between the Acts]]'' (1941),{{sfn|Woolf|1941}} Woolf fell into a depression similar to that which she had earlier experienced. The onset of World War II, the destruction of her London home during [[the Blitz]], and the cool reception given to [[Roger Fry: A Biography|her biography]]{{sfn|Woolf|1940a}} of her late friend [[Roger Fry]] all worsened her condition until she was unable to work.{{sfn|Lee|1999|}} When Leonard enlisted in the Home Guard, Virginia disapproved. She held fast to her [[pacifism]] and criticised her husband for wearing what she considered to be "the silly uniform of the Home Guard".{{sfn|Gordon|1984|p=269}}

After World War II began, Woolf's diary indicates that she was obsessed with death, which figured more and more as her mood darkened.{{sfn|Gordon|1984|p=279}} On 28 March 1941, Woolf drowned herself by filling her overcoat pockets with stones and walking into the [[River Ouse, Sussex|River Ouse]] near her home.{{sfn|Lee|1999|p=185}} Her body was not found until 18 April.&lt;ref name=Panken262/&gt; Her husband buried her cremated remains beneath an elm tree in the garden of [[Monk's House]], their home in [[Rodmell]], Sussex.{{sfn|Wilson|2016|p=825}}

In her suicide note, addressed to her husband, she wrote:
{{quote|Dearest,
I feel certain that I am going mad again. I feel we can't go through another of those terrible times. And I shan't recover this time. I begin to hear voices, and I can't concentrate. So I am doing what seems the best thing to do. You have given me the greatest possible happiness. You have been in every way all that anyone could be. I don't think two people could have been happier till this terrible disease came. I can't fight it any longer. I know that I am spoiling your life, that without me you could work. And you will I know. You see I can't even write this properly. I can't read. What I want to say is I owe all the happiness of my life to you. You have been entirely patient with me and incredibly good. I want to say that—everybody knows it. If anybody could have saved me it would have been you. Everything has gone from me but the certainty of your goodness. I can't go on spoiling your life any longer. I don't think two people could have been happier than we have been. V.{{sfn|Jones|2013}}{{sfn|Rose|1979|p=243}} }}

==Work==
[[File:Roger Fry - Virginia Woolf.jpg|thumb|upright|A portrait of Woolf by [[Roger Fry]] {{circa|1917}}|alt= Portrait of Woolf in 1917 by Roger Fry]][[File:StracheyWoolf.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Lytton Strachey]] and Woolf at [[Garsington Manor|Garsington]], 1923|alt=Lytton Strachey with Virginia Woolf 1923 ]]
[[File:Virginia Woolf 1927.jpg|thumb|upright|Virginia Woolf 1927|alt=Portrait of Virginia Woolf 1927]]
Woolf is considered to be one of the more important 20th century novelists.{{sfn|Curtis|2006|p=4}} A [[literary modernism|modernist]], she was one of the pioneers of using [[stream of consciousness (narrative mode)|stream of consciousness]] as a [[narrative device]], alongside contemporaries such as [[Marcel Proust]],{{sfn|Leonard|1981}}{{sfn|Taunton|2016}} [[Dorothy Richardson]] and [[James Joyce]].{{sfn|Rahn|2018}}{{sfn|Goldman|2001}}&lt;ref name=Ross10/&gt; Woolf's reputation was at its greatest during the 1930s, but declined considerably following [[World War II]]. The growth of [[Feminist literary criticism|feminist criticism]] in the 1970s helped re-establish her reputation.{{sfn|Beja|1985|pp=1, 3, 53}}{{sfn|Snodgrass|2015}}

Virginia submitted her first article in 1890, to a competition in ''[[Tit-Bits]]''. Although it was rejected, this shipboard romance by the 8-year-old would presage her first novel 25 years later, as would contributions to the ''Hyde Park News'', such as the model letter "to show young people the right way to express what is in their hearts", a subtle commentary on her mother's legendary matchmaking.{{sfn|Licence|2015|p=20}}&lt;ref name=Alexander46/&gt; She transitioned from juvenilia to professional journalism in 1904 at the age of 22. Violet Dickinson introduced her to [[Kathleen Lyttelton|Mrs. Lyttelton]], the editor of the ''Women's Supplement'' of ''[[The Guardian (Anglican newspaper)|The Guardian]]'', a Church of England newspaper. Invited to submit a 1,500-word article, Virginia sent Lyttelton a review of [[W.D. Howells]]' ''The Son of Royal Langbirth'' and an essay about her visit to [[Haworth]] that year, ''Haworth, November 1904''.{{sfn|Woolf|1904}}{{sfn|Gordon|2004}} The review was published anonymously on 4 December, and the essay on the 21st.{{sfn|Bell|1972|loc=Chronology |p=194}}&lt;ref name=Koutsantoni5/&gt; In 1905, Woolf began writing for ''[[The Times Literary Supplement]]''.{{sfn|Liukkonen|2008}}

Woolf would go on to publish novels and essays as a public intellectual to both critical and popular acclaim. Much of her work was self-published through the [[Hogarth Press]]. "Virginia Woolf's peculiarities as a fiction writer have tended to obscure her central strength: she is arguably the major [[lyric poetry|lyrical]] novelist in the English language. Her novels are highly experimental: a narrative, frequently uneventful and commonplace, is refracted—and sometimes almost dissolved—in the characters' receptive consciousness. Intense lyricism and stylistic virtuosity fuse to create a world overabundant with auditory and visual impressions".&lt;ref name=Shukla51/&gt; "The intensity of Virginia Woolf's poetic vision elevates the ordinary, sometimes banal settings"—often wartime environments—"of most of her novels".&lt;ref name=Shukla51/&gt;

=== Fiction and drama ===

==== Novels ====
{{main|The Voyage Out}}
Her first novel, ''The Voyage Out'',{{sfn|Woolf|1915}} was published in 1915 at the age of 33, by her half-brother's imprint, [[Gerald Duckworth and Company Ltd]]. This novel was originally titled ''Melymbrosia'', but Woolf repeatedly changed the draft. An earlier version of ''The Voyage Out'' has been reconstructed by Woolf scholar [[Louise DeSalvo]] and is now available to the public under the intended title. DeSalvo argues that many of the changes Woolf made in the text were in response to changes in her own life.{{sfn|Haule|1982}} The novel is set on a ship bound for South America, and a group of young [[Edwardians]] onboard and their various mismatched yearnings and misunderstandings. In the novel are hints of themes that would emerge in later work, including the gap between preceding thought and the spoken word that follows, and the lack of concordance between expression and underlying intention, together with how these reveal to us aspects of the nature of love.{{sfn|Matar|2014}}

{{main|Mrs Dalloway}}
"''Mrs Dalloway'' (1925){{sfn|Woolf|1925}} centres on the efforts of Clarissa Dalloway, a middle-aged society woman, to organise a party, even as her life is paralleled with that of Septimus Warren Smith, a working-class veteran who has returned from the First World War bearing deep psychological scars".&lt;ref name=Shukla51/&gt;

{{main|To the Lighthouse}}
"''To the Lighthouse'' (1927){{sfn|Woolf|1927}} is set on two days ten years apart. The plot centres on the Ramsay family's anticipation of and reflection upon a visit to a lighthouse and the connected familial tensions. One of the primary themes of the novel is the struggle in the creative process that beset painter Lily Briscoe while she struggles to paint in the midst of the family drama. The novel is also a meditation upon the lives of a nation's inhabitants in the midst of war, and of the people left behind."&lt;ref name=Shukla51/&gt; It also explores the passage of time, and how women are forced by society to allow men to take emotional strength from them.{{sfn|Beja|1985|pp=15–17}}

{{main|Orlando: A Biography}}
''Orlando: A Biography'' (1928){{sfn|Woolf|1928}} is one of Virginia Woolf's lightest novels. A parodic biography of a young nobleman who lives for three centuries without ageing much past thirty (but who does abruptly turn into a woman), the book is in part a portrait of Woolf's lover [[Vita Sackville-West]].{{sfn|Winterson|2018}} It was meant to console Vita for the loss of her ancestral home, [[Knole House]], though it is also a satirical treatment of Vita and her work. In ''Orlando'', the techniques of historical biographers are being ridiculed; the character of a pompous biographer is being assumed for it to be mocked.{{sfn|Lee|1977|pp=15–17}}

{{main|The Waves}}
"''The Waves'' (1931) presents a group of six friends whose reflections, which are closer to recitatives than to interior monologues proper, create a wave-like atmosphere that is more akin to a [[prose poem]] than to a plot-centred novel".&lt;ref name=Shukla51/&gt;

{{main|Flush: A Biography}}
''Flush: A Biography'' (1933){{sfn|Woolf|1933}} is a part-fiction, part-biography of the cocker spaniel owned by Victorian poet [[Elizabeth Barrett Browning]]. The book is written from the dog's point of view. Woolf was inspired to write this book from the success of the [[Rudolf Besier]] play ''[[The Barretts of Wimpole Street]]''. In the play, Flush is on stage for much of the action. The play was produced for the first time in 1932 by the actress [[Katharine Cornell]].

{{main|The Years}}
''The Years'' (1936),{{sfn|Woolf|1937}} traces the history of the genteel Pargiter family from the 1880s to the "present day" of the mid-1930s. The novel had its origin in a lecture Woolf gave to the National Society for Women's Service in 1931, an edited version of which would later be published as "Professions for Women".{{sfn|Woolf|1977|pages=xxvii-xliv}} Woolf first thought of making this lecture the basis of a new book-length essay on women, this time taking a broader view of their economic and social life, rather than focusing on women as artists, as the first book had. She soon jettisoned the theoretical framework of her "novel-essay" and began to rework the book solely as a fictional narrative, but some of the non-fiction material she first intended for this book was later used in ''[[Three Guineas]]'' (1938).

{{main|Between the Acts}}
"Her last work, ''Between the Acts'' (1941),{{sfn|Woolf|1941}} sums up and magnifies Woolf's chief preoccupations: the transformation of life through art, sexual ambivalence, and meditation on the themes of flux of time and life, presented simultaneously as corrosion and rejuvenation—all set in a highly imaginative and symbolic narrative encompassing almost all of English history."&lt;ref name=Shukla51/&gt; This book is the most lyrical of all her works, not only in feeling but in style, being chiefly written in verse.{{sfn|Beja|1985|p=24}} While Woolf's work can be understood as consistently in dialogue with the [[Bloomsbury Group]], particularly its tendency (informed by [[G.E. Moore]], among others) towards doctrinaire rationalism, it is not a simple recapitulation of the coterie's ideals.{{sfn|Himmelfarb|1985}}

==== Themes ====
Woolf's fiction has been studied for its insight into many themes including war, shell shock, witchcraft, and the role of social class in contemporary modern British society.{{sfn|Harrington|2018}} In the postwar ''Mrs Dalloway'' (1925),{{sfn|Woolf|1925}} Woolf addresses the moral dilemma of war and its effects{{sfn|Floyd|2016}}{{sfn|Bradshaw|2016}} and provides an authentic voice for soldiers returning from World War I, suffering from shell shock, in the person of Septimus Smith.{{sfn|Church|2016}} In ''A Room of One's Own'' (1929) Woolf equates historical accusations of witchcraft with creativity and genius among women{{sfn|Brown|2015}} "When, however, one reads of a witch being ducked, of a woman possessed by devils...then I think we are on the track of a lost novelist, a suppressed poet, of some mute and inglorious Jane Austen".&lt;ref name=ROO3/&gt; Throughout her work Woolf tried to evaluate the degree to which her privileged background [[framing (social sciences)|framed]] the lens through which she viewed class.{{sfn|Madden|2006}}{{sfn|Maggio|2009}} She both examined her own position as someone who would be considered an elitist snob, but attacked the class structure of Britain as she found it. In her 1936 essay ''Am I a Snob?'',{{sfn|Woolf|1936}} she examined her values and those of the privileged circle she existed in. She concluded she was, and subsequent critics and supporters have tried to deal with the dilemma of being both elite and a social critic.{{sfn|Hite|2004}}{{sfn|Latham|2003}}{{sfn|Bas|2008}}

The sea is a recurring motif in Woolf's work. Noting Woolf's early memory of listening to waves break in Cornwall, Katharine Smyth writes in ''[[The Paris Review]]'' that ‘the radiance [of] cresting water would be consecrated again and again in her writing, saturating not only essays, diaries, and letters but also ''Jacob’s Room'', ''The Waves'', and ''To the Lighthouse''.’&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url= https://www.theparisreview.org/blog/2019/01/29/where-virginia-woolf-listened-to-the-waves/|work=The Paris Review|title= Where Virginia Woolf Listened to the Waves |date=January 29, 2019|first=Katharine|last=Smyth}}&lt;/ref&gt; Patrizia A. Muscogiuri explains that ‘seascapes, sailing, diving and the sea itself are aspects of nature and of human beings’ relationship with it which frequently inspired Virginia Woolf's writing.’&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last= Muscogiuri|first=Patrizia|url= https://books.google.com/books?id=CvMwDgAAQBAJ |title= Virginia Woolf and the Natural World|publisher= Oxford University Press|year=2011|isbn= 9781942954149|edition=First|location=UK|pages=258}}&lt;/ref&gt; This trope is deeply embedded in her texts’ structure and grammar: James Antoniou notes in [[Sydney Morning Herald]] how ‘Woolf made a virtue of the [[semicolon]], the shape and function of which resembles the wave, her most famous motif.’&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url= https://www.smh.com.au/culture/books/the-punctuation-mark-that-causes-so-much-angst-20190919-p52t17.html|work=The Sydney Morning Herald|title= The punctuation mark that causes so much angst|date=September 27, 2019|first=James|last=Antoniou}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the considerable conceptual difficulties, given Woolf's idiosyncratic use of language,{{sfn|Brassard|2016}} her works have been translated into over 50 languages.{{sfn|Harrington|2018}}{{sfn|Pratt|2017}} Some writers, such as the Belgian [[Marguerite Yourcenar]], had rather tense encounters with her, while others, such as the Argentinian [[Jorge Luis Borges]], produced versions that were highly controversial.{{sfn|Brassard|2016}}{{sfn|Snodgrass|2015}}

==== Drama ====
{{main|Freshwater (play)}}
Virginia Woolf researched the life of her great-aunt, the photographer [[Julia Margaret Cameron]], publishing her findings in an essay titled "Pattledom" (1925),&lt;ref name="WoolfEssay4/280"/&gt; and later in her introduction to her 1926 edition of Cameron's photographs.{{sfn|Cameron|1926}}{{sfn|Swenson|2017}} She had begun work on a play based on an episode in Cameron's life in 1923, but abandoned it. Finally it was performed on 18 January 1935 at the studio of her sister, [[Vanessa Bell]] on Fitzroy Street in 1935.{{sfn|Wilson |Barrett|2003}} Woolf directed it herself, and the cast were mainly members of the [[Bloomsbury Group]], including herself. ''Freshwater'' is a short three act comedy satirising the [[Victorian era]], only performed once in Woolf's lifetime.{{sfn|Woolf|1935}} Beneath the comedic elements, there is an exploration of both generational change and artistic freedom. Both Cameron and Woolf fought against the class and gender dynamics of Victorianism{{sfn|Usui|2007}} and the play shows links to both ''[[To the Lighthouse]]'' and ''[[A Room of One's Own]]'' that would follow.{{sfn|Swenson|2017}}

=== Non-fiction ===
Woolf wrote a body of autobiographical work and more than 500 essays and reviews,{{sfn|Hussey|2006}} some of which, like ''A Room of One's Own'' (1929) were of book length. Not all were published in her lifetime. Shortly after her death, Leonard Woolf produced an edited edition of unpublished essays titled ''The Moment and other Essays'',{{sfn|Woolf|1947}} published by the Hogarth Press in 1947. Many of these were originally lectures that she gave,{{sfn|Trilling|1948}} and several more volumes of essays followed, such as ''The Captain's Death Bed: and other essays'' (1950).{{sfn|Woolf|1950}}

==== ''A Room of One's Own'' ====
{{main|A Room of One's Own}}
Among Woolf's non-fiction works, one of the best known is ''A Room of One's Own'' (1929),{{sfn|Woolf|1929}} a book-length essay. Considered a key work of feminist literary criticism, it was written following two lectures she delivered on "Women and Fiction" at Cambridge University the previous year. In it, she examines the historical disempowerment women have faced in many spheres, including social, educational and financial. One of her more famous dicta is contained within the book "A woman must have money and a room of her own if she is to write fiction". Much of her argument ("to show you how I arrived at this opinion about the room and the money") is developed through the "unsolved problems" of women and fiction writing to arrive at her conclusion, although she claimed that was only "an opinion upon one minor point".{{sfn|British Library|2018a}} In doing so, she states a good deal about the nature of women and fiction, employing a quasi-fictional style as she examines where women writers failed because of lack of resources and opportunities, examining along the way the experiences of the [[Brontë family|Brontës]], [[George Eliot]] and [[George Sand]], as well as the fictional character of [[Shakespeare]]'s sister, equipped with the same genius but not position. She contrasted these women who accepted a deferential status with [[Jane Austen]], who wrote entirely as a woman.{{sfn|Kronenberger|1929}}

=== Influences ===
Michel Lackey argues that a major influence on Woolf, from 1912 onward, was Russian literature and Woolf adopted many of its aesthetic conventions.{{sfn|Lackey|2012}} The style of [[Fyodor Dostoyevsky]] with his depiction of a fluid mind in operation helped to influence Woolf's writings about a "discontinuous writing process", though Woolf objected to Dostoyevsky's obsession with "psychological extremity" and the "tumultuous flux of emotions" in his characters together with his right-wing, monarchist politics as Dostoyevsky was an ardent supporter of the autocracy of the [[Russian Empire]].{{sfn|Lackey|2012}} In contrast to her objections to Dostoyevsky's "exaggerated emotional pitch", Woolf found much to admire in the work of [[Anton Chekhov]] and [[Leo Tolstoy]].{{sfn|Lackey|2012}} Woolf admired Chekhov for his stories of ordinary people living their lives, doing banal things and plots that had no neat endings.{{sfn|Lackey|2012}} From Tolstoy, Woolf drew lessons about how a novelist should depict a character's psychological state and the interior tension within.{{sfn|Lackey|2012}} Lackey notes that, from [[Ivan Turgenev]], Woolf drew the lessons that there are multiple "I's" when writing a novel, and the novelist needed to balance those multiple versions of him- or herself to balance the "mundane facts" of a story vs. the writer's overarching vision, which required a "total passion" for art.{{sfn|Lackey|2012}}

Another influence on Woolf was the American writer [[Henry David Thoreau]], with Woolf writing in a 1917 essay that her aim as a writer was to follow Thoreau by capturing "the moment, to burn always with this hard, gem-like flame" while praising Thoreau for his statement "The millions are awake enough for physical labor, but only one in hundreds of millions is awake enough to a poetic or divine life. To be awake is to be alive".{{sfn|Majumdar|1969}} Woolf praised Thoreau for his "simplicity" in finding "a way for setting free the delicate and complicated machinery of the soul".{{sfn|Majumdar|1969}} Like Thoreau, Woolf believed that it was silence that set the mind free to really contemplate and understand the world.{{sfn|Majumdar|1969}} Both authors believed in a certain transcendental, mystical approach to life and writing, where even banal things could be capable of generating deep emotions if one had enough silence and the presence of mind to appreciate them.{{sfn|Majumdar|1969}} Woolf and Thoreau were both concerned with the difficulty of human relationships in the modern age.{{sfn|Majumdar|1969}} Other notable influences include [[William Shakespeare]], [[George Eliot]], [[Leo Tolstoy]], [[Marcel Proust]], [[Anton Chekhov]], [[Emily Brontë]], [[Daniel Defoe]], [[James Joyce]], and [[E.M. Forster]].{{cn|date=June 2021}}

=== List of selected publications ===
&lt;!-- Should only include cited work: and list is linked to main text. For regular lists see navbox on this page and separate Bibliography below - also Talk    --&gt;
{{main|Bibliography of Virginia Woolf}}
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;see {{harvtxt|Kirkpatrick|Clarke|1997}}, {{harvtxt|VWS|2018}}, {{harvtxt|Carter|2002}}

{{refbegin|30em}}

==== Novels ====
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf| title=The voyage out|date= 2017|orig-year=1915|publisher=FV Éditions |isbn=979-10-299-0459-2|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1915}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oe48DwAAQBAJ}} see also ''[[The Voyage Out]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91v/ Complete text ]
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=Night and Day|year= 2004|orig-year=1919a|publisher=1st World Publishing |isbn=978-1-59540-530-2 |ref={{harvid|Woolf|1919a}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PG8xgLGGurMC}} see also ''[[Night and Day (Woolf novel)|Night and Day]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91n/ Complete text]
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=Jacob's Room|date= 2015|orig-year=1922a|publisher=Mondial |isbn=978-1-59569-114-9|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1922a}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=funFBgAAQBAJ}} see also ''[[Jacob's Room]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91j/ Complete text]
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=Mrs. Dalloway|date= 2012|orig-year=1925|publisher=[[Broadview Press]] |isbn=978-1-55111-723-2|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1925}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RkcJa8oaEosC}} see also ''[[Mrs Dalloway]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91md/ Complete text]
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=To the Lighthouse |year=2004|orig-year=1927|publisher=Collector's Library |isbn=978-1-904633-49-5|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1927}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=S_qN7V5CB6QC}} see also ''[[To the Lighthouse]]'' &amp; Complete text, also [http://www.woolfonline.com/?node=content/text/transcriptions&amp;project=1 Texts at Woolf Online]
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|editor-last=DiBattista|editor-first=Maria |title=Orlando (Annotated): A Biography|date= 2006|orig-year=1928|publisher=[[Houghton Mifflin Harcourt|HMH]] |isbn=978-0-547-54316-1|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1928}} |url=https://archive.org/details/orlandobiography00wool_0|url-access=registration}} see also ''[[Orlando: A Biography]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91o/ Complete text]
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=The Waves|year=2000 |orig-year=1931|publisher=[[Wordsworth Editions]] |isbn=978-1-84022-410-8|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1931}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=G708Q0sSPjwC}} see also ''[[The Waves]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91w/ Complete text]
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=The Years|date=1936 |publisher=[[Hogarth Press]]|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1936a}}}}
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=Between the Acts |date=2014|orig-year=1941|publisher=[[Houghton Mifflin Harcourt]] |isbn=978-0-544-45178-0|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1941}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y0nCBAAAQBAJ}}  see also ''[[Between the Acts]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91b/ Complete text]

==== Short stories ====
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|title=The Short Stories of Virginia Woolf |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XgojDgAAQBAJ|date= 2016a|orig-year=1944|publisher=Read Books Limited |isbn=978-1-4733-6304-5}} see also ''[[A Haunted House and Other Short Stories]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/ Complete text]
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=The Mark on the Wall |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-uQdCgAAQBAJ|date= 2015|orig-year=1917 Hogarth Press |publisher=Booklassic |isbn=978-963-522-263-6|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1917a}}}} see also ''[[The Mark on the Wall]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91m/chapter8.html Complete text]
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=Kew Gardens |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=On8dCgAAQBAJ|date=7 July 2015|orig-year=1919b Hogarth Press |publisher=Booklassic |isbn=978-963-522-264-3|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1919b}}}} see also ''[[Kew Gardens (short story)|Kew Gardens]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91m/chapter7.html Complete text]

==== Cross-genre ====
*  {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|title=Flush|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_KQDxcmF3fgC|year=1998|orig-year=1933|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-283328-0|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1933}}}} see also ''[[Flush: A Biography]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91f/ Complete text]

==== Drama ====
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|title=Freshwater: A Comedy by Virginia Woolf (The 1923 &amp; 1935 Editions)|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=I1JODwAAQBAJ|date= 2017|orig-year=1935|publisher=Musaicum Books|isbn=978-80-272-3556-8|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1935}}}} see also ''[[Freshwater (play)|Freshwater]]''
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|editor-last= Ruotolo|editor-first=Lucio|others=Illustrations: [[Edward Gorey]]|title=Freshwater: a comedy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0JdQAAAAMAAJ|year=1976|publisher=Harcourt Brace Jovanovich|isbn=9780151334872}}

==== Biography ====
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|title=Roger Fry: A Biography|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EU9ODwAAQBAJ|date= 2017|orig-year=1940|publisher=Musaicum Books|isbn=978-80-272-3516-2|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1940a}}}} see also ''[[Roger Fry: A Biography]]'' &amp; [https://archive.org/details/rogerfryabiograp010045mbp Complete text]

==== Essays ====
* {{cite web|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|title=Haworth, November 1904|work=[[The Guardian]]|access-date=8 March 2018|date=14 December 1904 |url=http://digital.library.upenn.edu/women/woolf/VW-Bronte.html}}
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=A Room of One's Own|date=2016|orig-year=1929|publisher=Read Books Limited|isbn=978-1-4733-6305-2|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1929}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GgwjDgAAQBAJ}} see also ''[[A Room of One's Own]] ''&amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91r/ Complete text]
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=Mr. Bennett and Mrs. Brown|date= 2017|orig-year=1924 Hogarth Press |isbn=978-88-260-3291-7|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1924}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6Kg8DgAAQBAJ}} see also ''[[Mr. Bennett and Mrs. Brown]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/mr-bennett-and-mrs-brown/ Complete text]
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=A Letter to a Young Poet|date= 2016|orig-year=1932 Hogarth Press |publisher=Read Books Limited|isbn=978-1-4733-6307-6|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1932}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OgojDgAAQBAJ}} see also ''[[A Letter to a Young Poet]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91d/chapter25.html Complete text]
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=Three Guineas|date= 2016|orig-year=1938|publisher=Read Books Limited|isbn=978-1-4733-6301-4|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1938}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MwgjDgAAQBAJ}} see also ''[[Three Guineas]]'' &amp; [https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91tg/complete.html Complete text]

===== Essay collections =====
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|editor-last1= McNeillie|editor-first1=Andrew|editor-last2= Clarke|editor-first2=Stuart N.|editor-link1=Andrew McNeillie|title=The Essays of Virginia Woolf 6 vols. |date=1986–2011|publisher=[[Random House]]}}
** {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-mask=1|title=The Essays of Virginia Woolf Volume Two 1912–1918|year=1986|publisher=[[Harcourt Brace Jovanovich]]|isbn=978-0-15-629055-5|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1912–1918}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_bInAQAAMAAJ}}
*** {{harvnb|Ackroyd|1988}} (Review)
** {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-mask=1|title=The Essays of Virginia Woolf Volume Four 1925–1928|year=1994|publisher=[[Harcourt Brace Jovanovich]]|isbn=978-0-7012-0666-6|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1925–1928}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6cxkAAAAMAAJ}}
** {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-mask=1|title=The Essays of Virginia Woolf Volume Five 1929–1932|year=2017|publisher=[[Random House]]|isbn=978-1-4481-8194-0|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1929–1932}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Mc0pDwAAQBAJ}}
** {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-mask=1|title=The Essays of Virginia Woolf Volume Six 1933–1941|year=2011|publisher=[[Random House]]|isbn=978-0-7012-0671-0|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1933–1941}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ncwpDwAAQBAJ}}
*** {{harvnb|Patten|2011}} (Review)
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|date=2016b|title=The Collected Essays and Letters of Virginia Woolf – Including a Short Biography of the Author |publisher=Read Books Limited |isbn=978-1-4733-6310-6 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YQsjDgAAQBAJ}}
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|editor-last=Woolf|editor-first=Leonard|editor-link=Leonard Woolf|title= The Moment &amp; Other Essays|date= 2017|orig-year=1947 Hogarth Press |publisher=Musaicum Books|type=posthumous|isbn=978-80-272-3619-0|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1947}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TU9ODwAAQBAJ}} [http://www.gutenberg.net.au/ebooks15/1500221h.html Complete text]
** {{cite book|title=The Leaning Tower|date=1940|pages=100''ff''|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1940b}} |url=http://www.gutenberg.net.au/ebooks15/1500221h.html#ch18}}
*** {{harvnb|Trilling|1948}} (Review)
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|editor-last=Woolf|editor-first=Leonard|editor-link=Leonard Woolf|title=The Captain's death bed: and other essays|year=1950 |publisher=[[Hogarth Press]]|isbn=9780701204563|type=posthumous |url=https://archive.org/details/captainsdeathbed0000unse|url-access=registration}} (excerpts)
** {{cite book|last1=Virginia|first1=Woolf|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=Leslie Stephen |year=1932|pages=67–73|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1932a}}}} (excerpt) &amp; [https://books.google.com/books?id=Mc0pDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT831 also here]
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|editor-last=Bradshaw |editor-first=David|title=Selected Essays|year=2009|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-955606-9 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WxMUDAAAQBAJ}}
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=The Greatest Essays of Virginia Woolf|year=2017|publisher=Musaicum Books|isbn=978-80-272-3514-8 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8VFODwAAQBAJ}}

==== Contributions ====

* {{cite book|last=Cameron|first=Julia Margaret|author-link=Julia Margaret Cameron|editor-last=Powell|editor-first=Tristram|editor-link=Tristram Powell|others=Introductions by Virginia Woolf and [[Roger Fry]]|title=Victorian photographs of famous men &amp; fair women|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZK4lAQAAIAAJ|date= 1973|orig-year=1926 Hogarth Press, edited by [[Leonard Woolf|Leonard]] and Virginia Woolf |edition=Revised |publisher=[[D. R. Godine]] |isbn=978-0-87923-076-0|ref={{harvid|Cameron|1926}}}} (Digital edition)

==== Autobiographical writing ====
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|editor-last=Woolf|editor-first=Leonard|editor-link=Leonard Woolf|title=A Writer's Diary|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KwCVDlaXllsC|date=2003|orig-year=1953|publisher=[[Houghton Mifflin Harcourt|HMH]]|isbn=978-0-547-54691-9|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1953}}}}
** {{harvnb|Auden|1954}} (Review)
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|editor-last= Schulkind |editor-first=Jeanne|title=Moments of being: unpublished autobiographical writings |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=y4lbAAAAMAAJ |year=1985|orig-year=1976|edition=2nd |publisher=Harcourt Brace Jovanovich|isbn=978-0-15-162034-0}} (see ''[[Moments of Being]]'')
&lt;!-- Essays in Moments of Being --&gt;
** {{cite book|last= Schulkind|first=Jeanne|title=Preface to the Second Edition|page=6|ref={{harvid|Schulkind|1985a}}|bibcode=2007ess..bookD..17M|year=2007}}, in {{harvtxt|Woolf|1985}} (excerpts)
** {{cite book|last= Schulkind|first=Jeanne|title=Introduction|pages=11–24|ref={{harvid|Schulkind|1985}}}}, in {{harvtxt|Woolf|1985}}
** {{cite book|title=Reminiscences|date=1908|pages=25–60|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1908}}}}
** {{cite book|title=A Sketch of the Past|date=1940|pages=61–160|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1940}}}}{{efn|Originally published in 1976, the discovery in 1980 of a 77-page typescript acquired by the [[British Library]], containing 27 pages of new material necessitated a new edition in 1985. In particular, 18 pages of new material was inserted between pp. 107–125 of the first edition. Page 107 of that edition resumes as page 125 in the second edition, so that page references to the first edition in the literature, after p. 107 are found 18–19 pages later in the second edition.{{sfn|Schulkind|1985a}} All page references to ''Sketches'' are to the second edition, otherwise to the first edition of ''Moments of Being''. This added 22 new pages, and changed the pagination for the Memoir Club essays that followed by an extra 22 pages. Pagination also varies between printings of the 2nd. edition. Pages here refer to the 1985 Harvest (North American) edition}} (excerpts – 1st ed.)
**;Memoir Club Contributions
*** {{cite book|title=22 Hyde Park Gate|date=1921|pages=162–178|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1921}}}}
*** {{cite book|title=Old Bloomsbury|date=1922|pages=179–202|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1922}}}}
*** {{cite book|title=Am I a Snob?|date=1936|pages=203–220|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1936}}}}

==== Diaries and notebooks ====
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|editor-last=Leaska|editor-first= Mitchell A |title=A passionate apprentice: the early journals, 1897–1909|year=1990 |publisher=[[Hogarth Press]] |isbn=9780701208455 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dbRbAAAAMAAJ}}
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|editor-last=Bradshaw|editor-first= David |title=Carlyle's House and Other Sketches|year=2003|publisher=[[Hesperus Press]]|isbn=978-1-84391-055-8 |url=https://archive.org/details/carlyleshouseoth0000wool|url-access=registration}}
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|editor-last=Bell|editor-first=Anne Oliver|title=The Diary of Virginia Woolf 5 vols.|date=1977–1984|publisher=[[Houghton Mifflin]]}}
** {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-mask=1|title=The Diary of Virginia Woolf Volume One 1915–1919|year=1979|isbn=978-0-544-31037-7|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1915–1919}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=IpC8ngEACAAJ}}
** {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-mask=1|title=The Diary of Virginia Woolf Volume Two 1920–1924|year=1981|isbn=978-0-14-005283-1|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1920–1924}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZCjuAAAAMAAJ}}
** {{cite book|author=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=The Diary of Virginia Woolf Volume Three 1925–1930|year=1978|isbn=9780151255993|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1925–1930}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gijuAAAAMAAJ}}
** {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-mask=1|title=The Diary of Virginia Woolf Volume Five 1936–1941|year=1985|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt|isbn=978-0-15-626040-4|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1936–1941}} |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cbAnAQAAMAAJ}}
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|editor-last=Rosenbaum |editor-first=S. P.|title=The Platform of Time: Memoirs of Family and Friends|year=2008 |publisher=[[Hesperus Press]]|isbn=978-1-84391-711-3 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=X7InAQAAMAAJ}}

==== Letters ====
* {{cite book|last1=Woolf|first1=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|editor-last1=Nicolson|editor-first1=Nigel|editor-last2=Banks|editor-first2=Joanne Trautmann|editor-link1=Nigel Nicolson|title=The Letters of Virginia Woolf 6 vols.|url=https://archive.org/details/lettersofvirgini00nico|url-access=registration|year=1975–1980|publisher=[[Harcourt Brace Jovanovich]]|location=New York|isbn=9780151509263}}
** {{cite book|last1=Woolf|first1=Virginia|author-mask=1|title=The Letters of Virginia Woolf Volume One 1888–1912|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OxXJAQAACAAJ|year=1977|publisher=Harcourt Brace Jovanovich|isbn=978-0-15-650881-0|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1888–1912}}}}
*** {{cite web|title=Shut up in the Dark (Letter 531: Vanessa Bell, July 28, 1910)|url=https://www.theparisreview.org/blog/2017/01/25/107074/|work=[[The Paris Review]]|access-date=10 April 2018|date=25 January 2017|ref={{harvid|Woolf| 1910}}}}
** {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-mask=1|title=The Letters of Virginia Woolf Volume Two 1912–1922|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7_v1MAAACAAJ|year=1982|publisher=Harvest/HBJ Books|isbn=978-0-15-650882-7|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1912–1922}}}}
** {{cite book|last1=Woolf|first1=Virginia|author-mask=1|title=The Letters of Virginia Woolf Volume Three 1923–1928|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9j0JAQAAMAAJ|year=1975|publisher=Harcourt Brace Jovanovich|isbn=978-0-15-150926-3|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1923–1928}}}}
** {{cite book|last1=Woolf|first1=Virginia|author-mask=1|title=The Letters of Virginia Woolf Volume Four 1929–1931|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zifuAAAAMAAJ|date= 1979|publisher=Harcourt Brace Jovanovich|isbn=978-0-15-150927-0|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1929–1931}}}}
*** {{harvnb|Edel|1979}} (Review)
** {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-mask=1|title=The Letters of Virginia Woolf Volume Five 1932–1935 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=u980QwAACAAJ|year=1982|publisher=Harcourt Brace Jovanovich |isbn=978-0-15-650886-5 |ref={{harvid|Woolf|1932–1935}}}}

==== Photograph albums ====
* {{cite web|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|title= Virginia Woolf Monk's House photographs, ca. 1867-1967 (MS Thr 564)|url=http://oasis.lib.harvard.edu/oasis/deliver/deepLink?_collection=oasis&amp;uniqueId=hou02507|year=1983|publisher=Harvard Theatre Collection, [[Houghton Library]], [[Harvard Library]]|access-date=31 December 2017|type=Guide}}
** [https://hollis.harvard.edu/primo-explore/search?query=any,contains,Virginia%20Woolf%20Monk%27s%20House%20Photograph%20Album,AND&amp;pfilter=pfilter,exact,images,AND&amp;tab=everything&amp;search_scope=everything&amp;sortby=rank&amp;vid=HVD2&amp;lang=en_US&amp;mode=advanced&amp;offset=0&amp;fromRedirectFilter=true List of Album Guides]

{{div col}} 
# [https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:19138844$1i Album 1 MS Thr 557 (1863–1938)]
# [https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:17947670$1i Album 2 MS Thr 559 (1909–1922)]
# [https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:17947671$1i Album 3 MS Thr 560 (1890–1933)]
# [https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:17948758$1i Album 4 MS Thr 561 (1890–1947)]
# [https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:17948759$1i Album 5 MS Thr 562 (1892–1938)]
# [https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:18043536$1i Album 6 MS Thr 563 (1850–1900)]
{{div col end}}

==== Collections ====
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|title=Delphi Complete Works of Virginia Woolf (Illustrated)|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=o1AbAgAAQBAJ|date= 2013|publisher=Delphi Classics|isbn=978-1-908909-19-0}}
* {{cite web|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=eBooks@Adelaide|url=https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/|publisher=Library of [[University of Adelaide]]|access-date=14 February 2018|year= 2015}}
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=The Complete Works of Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LWhODwAAQBAJ|date= 2017a|publisher=Musaicum Books|isbn=978-80-272-1784-7}}
* {{cite web|last=Woolf|first=Virginia|author-link=Virginia Woolf|author-mask=1|title=Virginia Woolf|url=http://gutenberg.net.au/pages/woolf.html|publisher=[[Project Gutenberg]] Australia|access-date=27 March 2018|year=2007}}
{{refend}}

== Views ==
In her lifetime, Woolf was outspoken on many topics that were considered controversial, some of which are now considered progressive, others regressive.&lt;ref name=Ellisfront/&gt; She was an ardent [[feminist]] at a time when women's rights were barely recognised, and [[anti-colonialist]], anti-imperialist and a [[pacifist]] when [[chauvinism]] was popular. On the other hand, she has been criticised for views on class and race in her private writings and published works. Like many of her contemporaries, some of her writing is now considered offensive. As a result, she is considered polarising, a revolutionary feminist and socialist hero or a purveyor of [[hate speech]].&lt;ref name=Ellisfront/&gt;{{sfn|Lee|1995}}

Works such as ''A Room of One's Own'' (1929){{sfn|Woolf|1929}} and ''Three Guineas'' (1938){{sfn|Woolf|1938}} are frequently taught as icons of feminist literature in courses that would be very critical of some of her views expressed elsewhere.{{sfn|McManus|2008}} She has also been the recipient of considerable [[homophobic]] and [[misogynist]] criticism.{{sfn|Hussey|2012}}

=== Humanist views ===
Virginia Woolf was born into a non-religious family and is regarded, along with her fellow Bloomsberries [[E.M. Forster]] and [[G.E. Moore]], as a [[humanism|humanist]]. Both her parents were prominent [[agnostic atheism|agnostic atheists]]. Her father, [[Leslie Stephen]], had become famous in polite society for his writings which expressed and publicised reasons to doubt the veracity of religion. Stephen was also President of the [[West London Ethical Society]], an early [[secular humanism|humanist]] organisation, and helped to found the [[Humanists UK|Union of Ethical Societies]] in 1896. Woolf's mother, [[Julia Stephen]], wrote the book ''Agnostic Women'' (1880), which argued that agnosticism (defined here as something more like atheism) could be a highly moral approach to life.

Woolf was a critic of Christianity. In a letter to [[Ethel Smyth]], she gave a scathing denunciation of the religion, seeing it as self-righteous "egotism" and stating "my Jew [Leonard] has more religion in one toenail—more human love, in one hair".{{sfn|Woolf|1932–1935|p=321}} Woolf stated in her private letters that she thought of herself as an atheist.{{sfn|Streufert|1988}}

{{quote|She thought there were no Gods; no one was to blame; and so she evolved this atheist's religion of doing good for the sake of goodness.|Woolf characterises Clarissa Dalloway, the title character of ''[[Mrs Dalloway]]''{{sfn|Woolf|1925|p=76}}}}

=== Controversies ===
[[Hermione Lee]] cites a number of extracts from Woolf's writings that many, including Lee, would consider offensive, and these criticisms can be traced back as far as those of [[Wyndham Lewis]] and [[Q.D. Leavis]] in the 1920s and 1930s.{{sfn|Lee|1995}} Other authors provide more nuanced contextual interpretations, and stress the complexity of her character and the apparent inherent contradictions in analysing her apparent flaws.{{sfn|McManus|2008}} She could certainly be off-hand, rude and even cruel in her dealings with other authors, translators and biographers, such as her treatment of [[Ruth Gruber]]. Some authors{{who|date=December 2019}}, particularly [[postcolonial]] feminists dismiss her (and modernist authors in general) as privileged, elitist, [[classist]], racist, and [[antisemitic]].

Woolf's tendentious expressions, including prejudicial feelings against disabled people, have often been the topic of academic criticism:{{sfn|Lee|1995}}
&lt;blockquote&gt; The first quotation is from a diary entry of September 1920 and runs: "The fact is the lower classes are detestable." The remainder follow the first in reproducing stereotypes standard to upper-class and upper-middle class life in the early 20th century: "imbeciles should certainly be killed"; "Jews" are greasy; a "crowd" is both an ontological "mass" and is, again, "detestable"; "Germans" are akin to vermin; some "baboon faced intellectuals" mix with "sad green dressed negroes and negresses, looking like chimpanzees" at a peace conference; Kensington High St. revolts one's stomach with its innumerable "women of incredible mediocrity, drab as dishwater".{{sfn|McManus|2008}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Antisemitism===
Though accused of [[antisemitism]],{{sfn|Edel|1979}} the treatment of [[Judaism]] and [[Jews]] by Woolf is far from straightforward.{{sfn|Schröder|2003}} She was happily married to a Jewish man ([[Leonard Woolf]]) but often wrote about Jewish characters using stereotypes and generalisations. For instance, she described some of the Jewish characters in her work in terms that suggested they were physically repulsive or dirty. On the other hand, she could criticise her own views: "How I hated marrying a Jew — how I hated their nasal voices and their oriental jewellery, and their noses and their wattles — what a snob I was: for they have immense vitality, and I think I like that quality best of all" (Letter to Ethel Smyth 1930).{{sfn|Woolf|1929–1931|loc=2215: 2 Aug.}}{{sfn|Snodgrass|2015}}{{sfn|Gross|2006}} These attitudes have been construed to reflect, not so much antisemitism, but [[tribalism]]; she married outside her social grouping, and Leonard Woolf, too, expressed misgivings about marrying a [[gentile]]. Leonard, "a penniless Jew from Putney", lacked the material status of the Stephens and their circle.{{sfn|Edel|1979}}

While travelling on a cruise to Portugal, she protested at finding "a great many [[Spanish and Portuguese Jews|Portuguese Jews]] on board, and other repulsive objects, but we keep clear of them".&lt;ref name=Forrester49/&gt; Furthermore, she wrote in her diary: "I do not like the Jewish voice; I do not like the Jewish laugh." Her 1938 short story ''[[The Duchess and the Jeweller]]'' (originally titled ''The Duchess and the Jew'') has been considered antisemitic.{{sfn|Rodríguez|2001–2002}}

Yet Woolf and her husband Leonard came to despise and fear the 1930s [[fascism]] and antisemitism. Her 1938 book ''[[Three Guineas]]''{{sfn|Woolf|1938}} was an indictment of fascism and what Woolf described as a recurring propensity among [[patriarchy|patriarchal]] societies to enforce repressive societal mores by violence.{{sfn|Young|2002}}

== Modern scholarship and interpretations ==
Though at least one biography of Virginia Woolf appeared in her lifetime, the first authoritative study of her life was published in 1972 by her nephew Quentin Bell. [[Hermione Lee]]'s 1996 biography ''Virginia Woolf''{{sfn|Lee|1999}} provides a thorough and authoritative examination of Woolf's life and work, which she discussed in an interview in 1997.{{sfn|Lee|1997}} In 2001, [[Louise DeSalvo]] and Mitchell A. Leaska edited ''The Letters of Vita Sackville-West and Virginia Woolf''. Julia Briggs's ''Virginia Woolf: An Inner Life'' (2005) focuses on Woolf's writing, including her novels and her commentary on the creative process, to illuminate her life. The sociologist Pierre Bourdieu also uses Woolf's literature to understand and analyse gender domination. Woolf biographer [[Gillian Gill]] notes that Woolf's traumatic experience of sexual abuse by her half-brothers during her childhood influenced her advocacy of protection of vulnerable children from similar experiences.{{sfn|Haynes|2019}}

=== Virginia Woolf and her mother ===
The intense scrutiny of Virginia Woolf's literary output (see [[#VWB|Bibliography]]) has led to speculation as to her mother's influence, including psychoanalytic studies of mother and daughter.&lt;ref name=MP67/&gt;{{sfn|Rosenman|1986}}&lt;ref name=MH91/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hirsch108/&gt; Woolf states that, "my first memory, and in fact it is the most important of all my memories"{{sfn|Woolf|1940|p=64}} is of her mother. Her memories of her mother are memories of an obsession,&lt;ref name=Birrento69/&gt;{{sfn|Woolf|1940|pp=81–84}} starting with her first major breakdown on her mother's death in 1895, the loss having a profound lifelong effect.&lt;ref name=Simpson12/&gt; In many ways, her mother's profound influence on Virginia Woolf is conveyed in the latter's recollections, "there she is; beautiful, emphatic ... closer than any of the living are, lighting our random lives as with a burning torch, infinitely noble and delightful to her children".{{sfn|Woolf|1908|p=40}}

Woolf described her mother as an "invisible presence" in her life, and Ellen Rosenman argues that the mother-daughter relationship is a constant in Woolf's writing.{{sfn|Rosenman|1986|loc=cited in {{harvtxt|Caramagno|1989}}}} She describes how Woolf's [[modernism]] needs to be viewed in relationship to her ambivalence towards her Victorian mother, the centre of the former's female identity, and her voyage to her own sense of autonomy. To Woolf, "Saint Julia" was both a martyr whose perfectionism was intimidating and a source of deprivation, by her absences real and virtual and premature death.{{sfn|Caramagno|1989}} Julia's influence and memory pervades Woolf's life and work. "She has haunted me", she wrote.{{sfn|Woolf|1923–1928|p=374}}

=== Historical feminism ===
According to the 2007 book ''Feminism: From Mary Wollstonecraft to Betty Friedan'' by Bhaskar A. Shukla, "Recently, studies of Virginia Woolf have focused on feminist and lesbian themes in her work, such as in the 1997 collection of critical essays, ''Virginia Woolf: Lesbian Readings'', edited by Eileen Barrett and Patricia Cramer."&lt;ref name=Shukla51/&gt; In 1928, Woolf took a grassroots approach to informing and inspiring feminism. She addressed undergraduate women at the ODTAA Society at Girton College, Cambridge and the Arts Society at Newnham College with two papers that eventually became ''[[A Room of One's Own]]'' (1929).{{sfn|Woolf|1929}} 

Woolf's best-known nonfiction works, ''[[A Room of One's Own]]'' (1929){{sfn|Woolf|1929}} and ''[[Three Guineas]]'' (1938),{{sfn|Woolf|1938}} examine the difficulties that female writers and intellectuals faced because men held disproportionate legal and economic power, as well as the future of women in education and society, as the societal effects of industrialisation and birth control had not yet fully been realised.{{citation needed|date=November 2016}} In ''[[The Second Sex]]'' (1949), [[Simone de Beauvoir]] counts, of all women who ever lived, only three female writers—[[Emily Brontë]], Woolf and "sometimes" [[Katherine Mansfield]]— have explored "the given".&lt;ref name=Beauvoir53/&gt;

== In popular culture ==
[[File:Stamps of Romania, 2007-013.jpg|thumb|Virginia Woolf on Romanian stamp 2007|alt=Virginia Woolf portrayed on Romanian stamp 2007]]
* ''[[Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf?]]'' is a 1962 play by [[Edward Albee]]. It examines the structure of the marriage of an American middle-aged academic couple, Martha and George. [[Mike Nichols]] directed a [[Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf? (film)|film version]] in 1966, starring [[Elizabeth Taylor]] and [[Richard Burton]]. Taylor won the 1966 [[Academy Award]] for Best Actress for the role.
*''[[Me! I'm Afraid of Virginia Woolf]]'', a 1978 TV play, references the title of the Edward Albee play and features an English literature teacher who has a poster of her. It was written by [[Alan Bennett]] and directed by [[Stephen Frears]].
* The artwork ''[[The Dinner Party]]'' (1979) features a place setting for Woolf.{{sfn|Chicago|1974–1979}}
* The 1996 album ''[[Poetic Justice (Steve Harley album)|Poetic Justice]]'', by British musician [[Steve Harley]], contains a tribute to Woolf, specifically her most adventurous novel, in its closing track: "Riding the Waves (for Virginia Woolf)".{{citation needed|date=January 2019}}
* Michael Cunningham's 1998 [[Pulitzer Prize]]-winning novel ''[[The Hours (novel)|The Hours]]'' focused on three generations of women affected by Woolf's novel ''[[Mrs Dalloway]]''. In 2002, a [[The Hours (film)|film version]] of the novel was released, starring [[Nicole Kidman]] as Woolf. Kidman won the 2003 [[Academy Award]] for her portrayal.
* Susan Sellers's novel ''Vanessa and Virginia'' (2008) explores the close sibling relationship between Woolf and her sister, Vanessa Bell. It was adapted for the stage by Elizabeth Wright in 2010 and first performed by Moving Stories Theatre Company.
* Priya Parmar's 2014 novel ''Vanessa and Her Sister'' also examined the Stephen sisters' relationship during the early years of their association with what became known as the Bloomsbury Group.{{sfn|Parmar|2015}}
* An exhibition on Virginia Woolf was held at the [[National Portrait Gallery, London|National Portrait Gallery]] from July to October 2014.{{sfn|Brown|2014}}
* In the 2014 novel ''The House at the End of Hope Street'',{{sfn|van Praag|2014}} Woolf is featured as one of the women who has lived in the titular house.
* Virginia is portrayed by both [[Lydia Leonard]] and [[Catherine McCormack]] in the BBC's three-part drama series ''[[Life in Squares]]'' (2015).{{sfn|Coe|2015}}
* On 25 January 2018, Google showed a Google doodle celebrating her 136th birthday.{{sfn|TOI|2018}}
*In many [[Barnes &amp; Noble]] stores, Woolf is featured in Gary Kelly's ''Author Mural Panels,'' an imprint of the Barnes &amp; Noble Author brand that also features other notable authors like [[Zora Neale Hurston|Hurston]], [[Rabindranath Tagore|Tagore]], and [[Franz Kafka|Kafka]].
*The 2018 film ''[[Vita and Virginia]]'' depicts the relationship between [[Vita Sackville-West]] and Woolf, portrayed by [[Gemma Arterton]] and [[Elizabeth Debicki]] respectively.

=== Adaptations ===
A number of Virginia Woolf's works have been adapted for the screen, and her play ''Freshwater'' (1935){{sfn|Woolf|1935}} is the basis for a 1994 [[chamber opera]], ''[[Freshwater (opera)|Freshwater]]'', by [[Andy Vores]]. The final segment of the 2018 ''[[London Unplugged]]'' is adapted from her short story ''[[Kew Gardens (short story)|Kew Gardens]]''. ''Septimus and Clarissa'', a stage adaptation of ''Mrs. Dalloway'' was created and produced by the New York-based ensemble Ripe Time in 2011 at the Baruch Performing Arts Center. It was adapted by [[Ellen McLaughlin]], and directed and devised by Rachel Dickstein. It was nominated for a 2012 Drama League award for Outstanding Production, a Drama Desk nomination for Outstanding Score (Gina Leishman) and a Joe A. Calloway Award nomination for outstanding direction (Rachel Dickstein.)

== {{anchor|Legacy}}Legacy ==
{{multiple image
| header = Memorials
| align = right
| direction = horizontal
| total_width = 400
| float = none
| image1 = Virginia Woolf mural.jpg
| caption1 = Plaque honouring Virginia Woolf on the building bearing her name, [[King's College, London]], [[Kingsway, London|Kingsway]]
| alt1 = Plaque describing Virginia's time at King's College, on the Virginia Woolf Building there
| image2 = Virginia Woolf, Tavistock Square, London.JPG
| caption2 = Woolf's [[bust (sculpture)|bust]] in [[Tavistock Square]], London, by [[Stephen Tomlin]], 1931. Erected by the Virginia Woolf Society of Great Britain, 2004.
| alt2 = Bronze cast of Stephen Tomlin's bust of Virginia Woolf (1931) in Tavistock Square
}}
Virginia Woolf is known for her contributions to 20th-century literature and her essays, as well as the influence she has had on literary, particularly feminist criticism. A number of authors have stated that their work was influenced by her, including [[Margaret Atwood]], [[Michael Cunningham]],{{efn|"Like my hero Virginia Woolf, I do lack confidence. I always find that the novel I'm finishing, even if it's turned out fairly well, is not the novel I had in my mind."{{sfn|Brockes|2011}}}} [[Gabriel García Márquez]],{{efn|"after having read Ulysses in English as well as a very good French translation, I can see that the original Spanish translation was very bad. But I did learn something that was to be very useful to me in my future writing—the technique of the interior monologue. I later found this in Virginia Woolf, and I like the way she uses it better than Joyce."{{sfn|Stone|1981}}}} and [[Toni Morrison]].{{efn|"I wrote on Woolf and Faulkner. I read a lot of Faulkner then. You might not know this, but in the '50s, American literature was new. It was renegade. English literature was English. So there were these avant-garde professors making American literature a big deal. That tickles me now."{{sfn|Bollen|2012}}}} Her iconic image{{sfn|Silver|1999}} is instantly recognisable from the Beresford portrait of her at twenty (at the top of this page) to the Beck and Macgregor portrait in her mother's dress in ''Vogue'' at 44 (see [[#VWMD|image]]) or [[Man Ray]]'s cover of ''Time'' magazine (see [[#MRVW|image]]) at 55.&lt;ref name=License8/&gt; More postcards of Woolf are sold by the [[National Portrait Gallery, London|National Portrait Gallery]], London than any other person.{{sfn|Stimpson|1999}} Her image is ubiquitous, and can be found on products ranging from tea towels to T-shirts.&lt;ref name=License8/&gt;

Virginia Woolf is studied around the world, with organisations such as the Virginia Woolf Society,{{sfn|VWS|2017}} and The Virginia Woolf Society of Japan. In addition, trusts—such as the Asham Trust—encourage writers in her honour.{{sfn|Asham|2018}} Although she had no descendants, a number of her extended family are notable.{{sfn|Brooks|2015}}

=== Monuments and memorials ===
In 2013, Woolf was honoured by her alma mater of King's College London with the opening of the Virginia Woolf Building on [[Kingsway, London|Kingsway]], with a plaque commemorating her time there and her contributions (see image),{{sfn|King's College, London|2013}}{{sfn|King's College, London|2018}} together with [[:file:Auto-icon of Virginia Woolf at King's College London.jpg|this exhibit]] depicting her accompanied by a quotation "London itself perpetually attracts, stimulates, gives me a play &amp; a story &amp; a poem" from her 1926 diary.&lt;ref name=Squier204/&gt; Busts of Virginia Woolf have been erected at her home in [[Rodmell]], Sussex and at Tavistock Square, London where she lived between 1924 and 1939.

In 2014, she was one of the inaugural honorees in the [[Rainbow Honor Walk]], a [[List of halls and walks of fame|walk of fame]] in [[San Francisco]]'s [[Castro District, San Francisco|Castro neighbourhood]] noting [[LGBTQ]] people who have "made significant contributions in their fields".{{sfn|Barmann|2014}}

Woolf Works, a women's co-working space in Singapore, opened in 2014 and was named after her in tribute to the essay ''[[A Room of One's Own]]'';{{sfn|Mohapatra|Venugopal|2017|pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=gJkqDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT76 76–]}} it also has many other things named after it (see the essay's article).

A campaign was launched in 2018 by Aurora Metro Arts and Media to erect a statue of Woolf in Richmond, where she lived for 10 years. The proposed statue shows her reclining on a bench overlooking the river Thames.{{sfn|Statue Fundraiser}}

== Family trees ==
&lt;small&gt;&amp;nbsp;see {{harvnb|Lee|1999|pp=xviii–xvix}}, {{harvnb|Bell|1972|pp=[https://books.google.com/books?id=9hYqDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PP9 x–xi]}}, {{harvnb|Bicknell|1996a|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=f2WwCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PR20 xx]}}, {{harvnb|Venn|1904}}&lt;/small&gt;

{{anchor|Pattle}}{{chart top|'''&lt;big&gt;Pattle-de l'Etang Family Tree&lt;/big&gt;'''&lt;ref name=ForresterTree/&gt;{{sfn|Wood|2017}}|collapsed=yes}}&lt;!-- set to yes on page after edit --&gt;
{{chart/start|align=center}}
{{chart| | | |||||||||||||||JP |-|v|-| AA |JP=James Peter Pattle 1775–1845|AA=m. 1811&lt;br /&gt;Adeline Marie de l'Etang 1793–1845}}&lt;!-- 1st generation: James Pattle --&gt;
{{chart| ,| -|- | -| -|v | -|-|-|v|-|-| -|-|-|-|-|-|-|v|-|^|-|-|-|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|.}}&lt;!-- connection to 2nd generation --&gt;
{{chart| Ad||El | | JM||HP|-|v|- |Sa||JJ|-|v|-|Ma||Lo|||||||TS|v|Va||So
|Ad=Adeline Pattle&lt;br /&gt;1812–1836|El=Eliza Pattle&lt;br /&gt;1814–1818|JM=[[Julia Margaret Cameron|Julia Margaret Pattle]]&lt;br /&gt;1815–1879|HP= m. 1835&lt;br /&gt;[[Henry Thoby Prinsep|Henry Prinsep]]&lt;br /&gt;1792–1878 |Sa=Sara Monckton Pattle&lt;br /&gt;1816–1887|JJ= m. 1837&lt;br /&gt;Dr John Jackson&lt;br /&gt;1804–1887|Ma=Maria Theodosia Pattle&lt;br /&gt;1818–1892|Lo=Louisa Colebrooke Pattle&lt;br /&gt;1821–1873|TS=m. 1850&lt;br /&gt;[[Third Earl Somers|Earl Somers]]&lt;br /&gt;1819–1883|Va=Virginia Pattle&lt;br /&gt;1827–1910|So=Sophia Ricketts Pattle&lt;br /&gt;1829–1911}}&lt;!-- 2nd generation: Adeline Pattle --&gt;
{{chart|||||||||||||||||!|||||||||,|^|-|-|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|.||||`|-|-|-|-|v|-|.}}&lt;!-- connection to 3rd generation --&gt;
{{chart||||||||||||||||VCP||HHV|-|AMJ||HF|-|ML||HD|v|JP|v|LS||IC||AM|VCP=[[Valentine Cameron Prinsep|Valentine]]&lt;br /&gt;1838–1904|HHV=m.1856&lt;br /&gt;[[Halford Vaughan]]&lt;br /&gt;1811–1885|AMJ=Adeline Maria Jackson&lt;br /&gt;1837–1881|HF=m.1862&lt;br /&gt;[[Herbert William Fisher|Herbert Fisher]]&lt;br /&gt;1826–1903|ML=Mary Louisa Jackson&lt;br /&gt;1840–1916{{efn|Mary Louisa and Herbert Fisher's children included 1. [[Florence Henrietta Fisher]] (1864–1920) who married [[Frederic William Maitland]] (1850–1906) in 1886, who wrote the biography of Leslie Stephen{{sfn|Maitland|1906}} and 2. [[H. A. L. Fisher]] (1865–1940), whose daughter [[Mary Bennett]] (1913–2005), wrote the biography of the Jackson family{{sfn|Bennett|2002}}{{sfn|Vogeler|2014}}}}|HD=m. (1)1867&lt;br /&gt;[[Herbert Duckworth]]&lt;br /&gt;1833–1870|JP=[[Julia Stephen|Julia Prinsep Jackson]]&lt;br /&gt;1846–1895|LS=m. (2) 1878&lt;br /&gt;[[Leslie Stephen]]{{efn|Leslie Stephen had one daughter, Laura Makepeace Stephen (1870–1945), by his first wife, Minny Thackeray}}&lt;br /&gt;1832–1904|IC=[[Lady Isabella Caroline Somers-Cocks|Isabella Caroline Somers-Cocks]]&lt;br /&gt;1851–1921|AM=[[Adeline Marie Russell, Duchess of Bedford|Adeline Marie Somers-Cocks]]&lt;br /&gt;1852–1920 |boxstyle_JP=}}&lt;!-- 3rd (index) generation: Valentine --&gt;
{{chart|||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||,|-|-|-|'||||!||!|||||||||||||}}&lt;!-- connections down to 4th generation  --&gt;
{{chart|||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||!||||||||!|LS||||||||||LS=Laura&lt;br /&gt;1870–1945}}&lt;!-- Laura &amp; 2nd line of connectors--&gt;
{{chart|||||||||||||||||||||||||||,|-|-|-|-|v|-|-|^|.|||||||`|v|-|-|-|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|.}}&lt;!-- 3rd line of connections joining 4th gen--&gt;
{{chart|||||||||||||||||||||||||||!|||||!||||!||||||||!|||||||!|||||!||||||||!}}&lt;!-- 4th line of connections (up from boxes)--&gt;
{{chart|||||||||||||||||||||||||||Geo||Ste||Ger||DG|r2|Van|v|CB||Tho||Vir|-|Leo||Adr|Geo=[[George Herbert Duckworth]]&lt;br /&gt;1868–1934|Ste=Stella&lt;br /&gt;1869–1897|Ger=[[Gerald Duckworth|Gerald de l'Etang Duckworth]]&lt;br /&gt;1870–1937|DG=[[Duncan Grant]]&lt;br /&gt;1885–1978|Van=[[Vanessa Bell]]&lt;br /&gt;1879–1961|CB=m.1907&lt;br /&gt;[[Clive Bell]]&lt;br /&gt;1881–1964|Tho=[[Thoby Stephen]]&lt;br /&gt;1880–1906|Vir='''Virginia'''&lt;br /&gt;1882–1941|Leo=m. 1912&lt;br /&gt;[[Leonard Woolf]]&lt;br /&gt;1880–1969|Adr=[[Adrian Stephen]] &lt;br /&gt;1883–1948|boxstyle_Vir=background-color: #fcc;}}&lt;!-- 4th generation: George Duckworth --&gt;
{{chart||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||!|||,|^|-|.}}&lt;!-- connections --&gt;
{{chart||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||||AG||JB||QB|AG=[[Angelica Garnett|Angelica Vanessa Bell]]&lt;br /&gt;1918–2012|JB=[[Julian Bell]]&lt;br /&gt;1908 –1937|QB=[[Quentin Bell]]&lt;br /&gt;1910–1996}}&lt;!-- 5th generation: Angelica --&gt;
{{chart/end}}
{{chart bottom}}

{{anchor|Stephen}}{{chart top|'''&lt;big&gt;Stephen Family Tree&lt;/big&gt;'''&lt;ref name=Belltree/&gt;{{sfn|Venn|1904}}|collapsed=yes}}
{{chart/start|align=left}}
{{chart|||||||||RW|v|EB|RW=Robert Wilberforce&lt;br /&gt;1728–1768|EB=Elizabeth Bird&lt;br /&gt;1730–1798}}
{{chart||||||||||,|-|^|-|.}}
{{chart|AS|v|JS1|-|SW||WW||JV|v|CK|AS=m.(1) 1783&lt;br /&gt;Anna Stent&lt;br /&gt;1758–1790|JS1=[[James Stephen (British politician)|James Stephen]]&lt;br /&gt;1758–1832|SW=m.(2) 1800&lt;br /&gt;Sarah Wilberforce&lt;br /&gt;1757–1816|WW=[[William Wilberforce]]&lt;br /&gt;1759–1833|JV=[[John Venn (priest)|John Venn]]&lt;br /&gt;1759–1813|CK=m. 1789&lt;br /&gt;Katherine King&lt;br /&gt;1760–1803
}}
{{chart||||`|-|-|-|-|.|||||v|-|-|-|-|-|^}}
{{chart|WMT|v|IGS||JS|v|JCV|||WMT=[[William Makepeace Thackeray]]&lt;br /&gt;1811–1863|IGS=m. 1836&lt;br /&gt;Isabella Gethin Shawe&lt;br /&gt;1816–1893|JS=[[James Stephen (civil servant)|James]]&lt;br /&gt;1789–1859|JCV=1814&lt;br /&gt;Jane Catherine&lt;br /&gt;1793–1875}}&lt;!-- Index-1  --&gt;
{{chart|||| `|-|v|-|-|-|.||`|v|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|.}}&lt;!-- connector --&gt;
{{chart|RR|-|AT||MT|v|LS|v|JJ||JF||Car|RR=m. 1877&lt;br /&gt;[[Richmond Ritchie]]|AT=[[Anne Thackeray|Annie]]&lt;br /&gt;1837–1919|MT=m.(1)&lt;br /&gt;Minnie Thackeray&lt;br /&gt;1840–1875|LS=[[Leslie Stephen|Leslie]]&lt;br /&gt;1832–1904|JJ=m.(2) 1878&lt;br /&gt;[[Julia Stephen|Julia Duckworth]]&lt;br /&gt;1846–1895|JF= [[James Fitzjames Stephen|James Fitzjames]]&lt;br /&gt;1829–1894|Car=[[Caroline Stephen|Caroline]]&lt;br /&gt;1834–1909|boxstyle_LS=}}&lt;!-- IndexGen --&gt;
{{chart||||||||||||!||||!}}
{{chart|||||||||||LS||4JS|LS=Laura&lt;br /&gt;1870–1945|4JS='''Virginia'''+3 other&lt;br /&gt;see [[Julia Stephen]]|boxstyle_4JS=background-color: #fcc;}}&lt;!-- Children --&gt;
|{{chart/end}}
{{chart bottom}}

== Notes ==
{{notelist|30em}}

==References==
&lt;!-- Citations with URLs go here to avoid cluttering wikitext --&gt;
&lt;!-- Alphabetical --&gt;
{{Reflist|24em|refs=

&lt;ref name=Alexander46&gt;{{harvnb|Alexander|2005|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=odBIxjAhjbsC&amp;pg=PA46 46]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Stella&gt;{{harvnb|Androom|2017|loc=[https://androom.home.xs4all.nl/biography/p015040.htm Hills, Stella]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Beauvoir53&gt;{{harvnb|Beauvoir|1949|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=KuMtBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT53 53]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Bell: Virginia Woolf  --&gt;
&lt;ref name=Belltree&gt;{{harvnb|Bell|1972|loc=[https://books.google.com/books?id=9hYqDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PP9 Family Tree pp. x–xi]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Bicknell: Selected letters --&gt;
&lt;!-- ref name=BicknellTree&gt;{{harvnb|Bicknell|1996a|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=f2WwCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PR20 xx]}}&lt;/ref --&gt;
&lt;ref name=BicknellIntro6&gt;{{harvnb|Bicknell|1996a|loc=[https://books.google.com/books?id=f2WwCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA6 Introduction p. 6]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Birrento69&gt;{{harvnb|Birrento|2007|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=l_j4ln5cEI8C&amp;pg=PA69 69]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Blair70&gt;{{harvnb|Blair|2012|loc=[https://books.google.com/books?id=19lz01yFmpcC&amp;pg=PA70 Spanning Convention and Intellect p. 70]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Bond23&gt;{{harvnb|Bond|2000|loc=[https://books.google.com/books?id=5L1CFtyLcG0C&amp;pg=PA23 Julia Stephen p. 23]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Briggs37&gt;{{harvnb|Briggs|2006a|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=_Fn2kILpMkoC&amp;pg=PA37 37]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- ref name=CWn4&gt;{{harvnb|Caws|Wright|1999|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=U8MeZDksY1wC&amp;pg=PA387 387, Note 4]}}&lt;/ref --&gt;

&lt;ref name=Cramer126&gt;{{harvnb|Cramer|1997|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=sH8UCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA126 126]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Curtis: Virginia's women --&gt;
&lt;ref name=Curtis17&gt;{{harvnb|Curtis|2002b|loc=[https://books.google.com/books?id=lWSzSTjldFkC&amp;pg=PA17 Introduction p. 17]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Curtis58&gt;{{harvnb|Curtis|2002b|loc=[https://books.google.com/books?id=lWSzSTjldFkC&amp;pg=PA58 Introduction p. 58]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Dunn: Conspiracy  --&gt;
&lt;ref name=Dunn33&gt;{{harvnb|Dunn|1990|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=-xs1AgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT33 33]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Dunn76&gt;{{harvnb|Dunn|1990|p=[https://books.google.ca/books?id=gJP02k_T1ZYC&amp;pg=PT76 76]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Ellisfront&gt;{{harvnb|Ellis|2007|loc=[http://assets.cambridge.org/97805218/82897/frontmatter/9780521882897_frontmatter.pdf Front Matter]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Ender218&gt;{{harvnb|Ender|2005|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=bMRuB2f-EYMC&amp;pg=PA218 218]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Flint54&gt;{{harvnb|Flint|2017|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=e9TwDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA54 54]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Forrester: Portrait --&gt;
&lt;ref name=ForresterTree&gt;{{harvnb|Forrester|2015|loc=[https://books.google.com/books?id=AXipBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PP9 Family Tree]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Forrester49&gt;{{harvnb|Forrester|2015|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=AXipBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA47 47]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Froula19&gt;{{harvnb|Froula|2005|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=GN7UgbL4kKoC&amp;pg=PA19 19]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Gordon: Writer's life --&gt;
&lt;ref name=Gordon51&gt;{{harvnb|Gordon|1984|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=NLDSAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT51 51]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Gordon52&gt;{{harvnb|Gordon|1984|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=NLDSAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT52 52]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Gordon53&gt;{{harvnb|Gordon|1984|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=NLDSAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT52 53]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Hague259&gt;{{harvnb|Hague|2003|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=95_C3LCSrCEC&amp;pg=PA259 259]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Hale62&gt;{{harvnb|Hale|1998|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=U-8tjg6aliEC&amp;pg=PA62 62 n. 1]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Harris34&gt;{{harvnb|Harris|2011|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=GgA7CwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT34 34]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Hirsch108&gt;{{harvnb|Hirsch|1989|pp=[https://books.google.com/books?id=HSVMW_cN8Q8C&amp;pg=PA108 108''ff''.]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Jones228&gt;{{harvnb|Jones|2014|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=LjcQBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT228 228]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Koutsantoni5&gt;{{harvnb|Koutsantoni|2013|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=wt3ivsDLyPQC&amp;pg=PA5 5]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Kukil 2011: Leslie Stephen's Photo Album --&gt;
&lt;ref name=Kukil36f&gt;{{harvnb|Kukil|2011|loc=[https://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/rarebook/exhibitions/stephen/36f.htm Julia Stephen with Virginia, 1884]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Kukil37c&gt;{{harvnb|Kukil|2011|loc=[https://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/rarebook/exhibitions/stephen/37c.htm Talland House, c.1882-1894]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Kukil38a&gt;{{harvnb|Kukil|2011|loc=[https://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/rarebook/exhibitions/stephen/38a.htm Julia Stephen with Stephen children at lessons, c.1894]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Kukil38g&gt;{{harvnb|Kukil|2011|loc=[https://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/rarebook/exhibitions/stephen/38g.htm Julia Stephen reading a book at Talland House, 1892]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Kukil38l&gt;{{harvnb|Kukil|2011|loc=[https://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/rarebook/exhibitions/stephen/38l.htm Adrian Stephen, Julia Stephen, and Henry James at Talland House, 1894]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Licence: Living in squares --&gt;
&lt;ref name=License8&gt;{{harvnb|Licence|2015|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=sWfGCQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT8 8]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=License12&gt;{{harvnb|Licence|2015|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=sWfGCQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT12 12]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=License19&gt;{{harvnb|Licence|2015|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=sWfGCQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT19 19]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Lilienfeld40&gt;{{harvnb|Lilienfeld|1997|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=sH8UCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA40 40]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Snaith: Palgrave   --&gt;
&lt;ref name=MH91&gt;{{harvnb|Hussey|2007|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=h7uJDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA91 91]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=MP67&gt;{{harvnb|Minow-Pinkney|2007|pp=[https://books.google.com/books?id=h7uJDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA67 67, 75]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=MP230&gt;{{harvnb|Minow-Pinkney|2006|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=vJgkDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA230&amp; 230]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Moggridge217&gt;{{harvnb|Moggridge|1992|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=DFsctHxvFhoC&amp;pg=PA217 217]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Montross61&gt;{{harvnb|Montross|2014|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=lw2aAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT61 61]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=OliverPref&gt;{{harvnb|Oliver|2013|loc=[https://books.google.com/books?id=cZMdDMyr3RcC&amp;pg=PA1989 Preface]}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;!-- Panken: Lust of creation --&gt;
&lt;ref name=Panken19&gt;{{harvnb|Panken|1987|loc=[https://books.google.com/books?id=nV5EmZA6obcC&amp;pg=PA19 The "Broken Cchrysalis" p. 19]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Panken43&gt;{{harvnb|Panken|1987|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=de4UyeBbCIwC&amp;pg=PA43 43]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Panken262&gt;{{harvnb|Panken|1987|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=de4UyeBbCIwC&amp;pg=PA262 262]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Parkes250&gt;{{harvnb|Parkes|2011|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=KE6oYs6v79UC&amp;pg=PA250 250 Note 5]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Prins39&gt;{{harvnb|Prins|2017|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=gLsIDgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA39 39]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Read10&gt;{{harvnb|Read|2015|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=tdkVBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT10 10]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Ross10&gt;{{harvnb|Richardson|2014|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=AQ9bBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA10 10]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Rose5&gt;{{harvnb|Rose|1983|p=[https://books.google.ca/books?id=EbRDDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA5 5]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Rosenbaum1/130"&gt;{{harvnb|Rosenbaum|1987|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=ZtS-DAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA130 130]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Rosner: Cambridge companion  --&gt;
&lt;ref name="Rosner2014/3"&gt;{{harvnb|Rosner|2014|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=k66BAwAAQBAJ&amp;PA3 3]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Rosner: Modernism and architecture  --&gt;
&lt;ref name="Rosner2008/69"&gt;{{harvnb|Rosner|2008|loc=[https://books.google.ca/books?id=hs4zCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA69 Walls p. 69]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=SoLHPG&gt;{{harvnb|Sheppard|1975|loc=[http://www.british-history.ac.uk/survey-london/vol38/pp26-38 Hyde Park Gate pp. 26–38]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Shukla51&gt;{{harvnb|Shukla|2007|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=EgfmJBJjfIcC&amp;pg=PA51 51]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Simpson12&gt;{{harvnb|Simpson|2016|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=lPE8CwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT12 12]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Spalding: Gwen Raverat --&gt;
&lt;ref name="Spalding2010/163"&gt;{{harvnb|Spalding|2010|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=WPwcNbrneJkC&amp;pg=PA163 163]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Squier: Virginia Woolf and London --&gt;
&lt;ref name=talland&gt;{{harvnb|Squier|1985|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=JYU6DwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT28 28]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Squier204&gt;{{harvnb|Squier|1985|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=JYU6DwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT204 204]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=chronology&gt;{{harvnb|Stephen|1987|loc=[https://books.google.com/books?id=VwquiPrOd9EC&amp;pg=PR17 Chronology pp. xvii–xxii]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Tolley106&gt;{{harvnb|Tolley|1997|p=[https://books.google.ca/books?id=ygrK5ygfLwQC&amp;pg=PA106 106]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Nikki Vine's Family Tree --&gt;
&lt;!-- ref name=VineJacksonFam&gt;{{harvnb|Vine|2018|loc=[http://www.nikoko.co.uk/Diaries/Jackson.htm Jackson Family]}}&lt;/ref --&gt;
&lt;ref name=VineJacksonDiary&gt;{{harvnb|Vine|2018|loc=[http://www.nikoko.co.uk/Diaries/mrsjackson.htm Jackson Diary]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=VineDuckworth&gt;{{harvnb|Vine|2018|loc=[http://www.nikoko.co.uk/Champneys/GedHTree/ghtout/gp95.htm#head4 Duckworth]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Wilson: VW's London --&gt;
&lt;ref name=Wilson21&gt;{{harvnb|Wilson|1987|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=_CRcyUYWzrIC&amp;pg=PA21 21]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Wilson181&gt;{{harvnb|Wilson|1987|pp=[https://books.google.com/books?id=_CRcyUYWzrIC&amp;pg=PA181 181–182]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Zimring160&gt;{{harvnb|Zimring|2016|p=[https://books.google.ca/books?id=bByoDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT160 160]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Works by WOOLF  --&gt;
&lt;!-- Short stories --&gt;
&lt;ref name=hauntedintro&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|2016a|loc=[https://books.google.com/books?id=XgojDgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT5 Introduction pp. 5–6]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=haunted9&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|2016a|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=XgojDgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT36 36]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=mothers&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|1929|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=GgwjDgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT61 61]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Essays --&gt;
&lt;!-- Reminiscences --&gt;
&lt;ref name=Rem14&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|1908|p=[https://books.google.ca/books?id=I09ODwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT14 14]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Rem40&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|1908|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=I09ODwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT18 40]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Sketch --&gt;
&lt;ref name=SOP102&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|2017|loc=[https://books.google.com/books?id=8VFODwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT1130 ''Sketch'' p. 102]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=SOP136&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|2017|loc=[https://books.google.ca/books?id=LWhODwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT3979 ''Sketch'' p. 136]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=SOP135&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|2017a|loc=[https://books.google.ca/books?id=LWhODwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT3999 ''Sketch'' p. 135]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="WoolfEssay4/280"&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|1925–1928|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=8VFODwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT2918 280]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;ref name="WoolfEssay6/261"&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|1933–1941|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=ncwpDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT261 261]}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;!-- Novels --&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;ref name=between150&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|1941|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=Y0nCBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT154 150]}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;!-- Lighthouse --&gt;
&lt;ref name=lighthouse44&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|1927|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=KFxLCAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT28 44]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=lighthouse1109&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|1927|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=o1AbAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT1109 1109]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Room --&gt;
&lt;ref name=ROO3&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|1929|loc=[https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91r/chapter3.html Chapter 3]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Writer's Diary --&gt;
&lt;ref name=writer346&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|1953|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=KwCVDlaXllsC&amp;pg=PT358 346]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Woolf online --&gt;
&lt;ref name=WOLTalland&gt;{{harvnb|Deegan|Shillingsburg|2018|loc=[http://www.woolfonline.com/?node=content/contextual/transcriptions&amp;project=1&amp;parent=2&amp;taxa=45&amp;content=5845&amp;pos=1 Dell. Talland House]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

== Bibliography ==
&lt;!-- Curated bibliography --&gt;
{{refbegin|30em}}

=== Books and theses ===
* {{cite book|editor-last=Batchelor|editor-first=John|title=The Art of Literary Biography|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YEvQ1_1YPCQC|year=1995|publisher=[[Clarendon Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-818289-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Beauvoir|first=Simone de|author-link=Simone de Beauvoir|title=The Second Sex|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KuMtBQAAQBAJ|date= 2015|orig-year=1949|publisher=[[Random House]]|isbn=978-1-4735-2191-9|ref={{harvid|Beauvoir|1949}}|edition=Vintage Feminism Short}} see also ''[[The Second Sex]]''
* {{cite book|editor-last=Benstock|editor-first=Shari|title=The Private Self: Theory and Practice of Women's Autobiographical Writings|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZgRRqohTH5kC|year=1988|publisher=[[UNC Press]] Books|isbn=978-0-8078-4218-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Brooker|first=Peter|title=Bohemia in London: The Social Scene of Early Modernism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7TEWDAAAQBAJ|date= 2004|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]]|isbn=978-0-230-28809-6}}
* {{cite book|last=Burstyn|first=Joan N.|title=Victorian Education and the Ideal of Womanhood|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6RSHDQAAQBAJ|date= 2016|orig-year=1980|publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]]|isbn=978-1-315-44430-7}}
* {{cite book|editor-last1=Eagle|editor-first1=Dorothy S.|editor-last2=Carnell|editor-first2=Hilary|title=The Oxford Illustrated Literary Guide to Great Britain and Ireland|url=https://archive.org/details/oxfordillustrate0000eagl|url-access=registration|year=1981|orig-year=1977|edition=2nd|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-869125-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Ender|first=Evelyne|title=Architexts of Memory: Literature, Science, and Autobiography|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bMRuB2f-EYMC|year=2005|publisher=[[University of Michigan Press]]|isbn=0-472-03104-X}}
* {{cite book|last=Hirsch|first=Marianne|author-link=Marianne Hirsch|title=The Mother / Daughter Plot: Narrative, Psychoanalysis, Feminism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HSVMW_cN8Q8C|date=1989|publisher=[[Indiana University Press]]|isbn=0-253-11575-2}}
* {{cite book|last= Jaillant|first=Lise|title=Cheap Modernism: Expanding Markets, Publishers' Series and the Avant-Garde|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MAz1MAAACAAJ|date=17 April 2017|publisher=[[Edinburgh University Press]]|isbn=978-1-4744-1724-2}}
** {{cite book|title='Classics behind Plate Glass': the Hogarth Press and the Uniform Edition of the Works of Virginia Woolf|pages=120–139}}
* {{cite book|editor-last1=Mandler|editor-first1=Peter|editor-last2=Pedersen|editor-first2=Susan|editor-link1=Peter Mandler|editor-link2=Susan Pedersen (historian)|title=After the Victorians: Private Conscience and Public Duty in Modern Britain|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9ECIAgAAQBAJ|date=16 August 2005|publisher=[[Routledge]]|isbn=978-1-134-91178-3}}
* {{cite book|last1=Mohapatra|first1=Sushmita |last2=Venugopal|first2=Savitha|date=15 June 2017 |title=Dear Ms Expat: Inspiring Tales from Women Who Built New Lives in a New Land |publisher=Marshall Cavendish International Asia |isbn=978-981-4779-44-9 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gJkqDwAAQBAJ}}
* {{cite book|last=Oliver|first=Vanessa|title=Healing Home: Health and Homelessness in the Life Stories of Young Women|url=https://archive.org/details/healinghomehealt0000oliv|url-access=registration|date= 2013|publisher=[[University of Toronto Press]]|isbn=978-1-4426-6236-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Olson|first=Liesl|title=Modernism and the Ordinary|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=QtiK0QgbFd0C|date= 2009|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-970972-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Parkes|first=Adam|title=A Sense of Shock: The Impact of Impressionism on Modern British and Irish Writing|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KE6oYs6v79UC|date=2011|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]], USA|isbn=978-0-19-538381-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Parmar|first=Priya|title=Vanessa and Her Sister|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tfQYBAAAQBAJ|date= 2015|publisher=[[Doubleday Canada]]|isbn=978-0-385-68134-6}}
* {{cite book|last=Prince|first=Tracy J.|title=Culture Wars in British Literature: Multiculturalism and National Identity|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9UgkaK8d_zoC|date= 2012|publisher=[[McFarland &amp; Company|McFarland]]|isbn=978-0-7864-6294-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Prins|first=Yopie|author-link=Yopie Prins|title=Ladies' Greek: Victorian Translations of Tragedy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gLsIDgAAQBAJ|date= 2017|publisher=[[Princeton University Press]]|isbn=978-1-4008-8574-9}}
* {{cite book|last1=Ramazanoglu|first1=Caroline|last2=Holland|first2=Janet|title=Feminist Methodology: Challenges and Choices|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PZKQCwG-GSoC|date= 2002|publisher=[[SAGE Publications]]|isbn=978-0-7619-5123-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Richardson|first=Dorothy|author-link=Dorothy Richardson|editor-last1=Ross|editor-first1=Stephen|editor-last2=Thomson|editor-first2=Tara|title=Pointed Roofs|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AQ9bBAAAQBAJ|date= 2014|orig-year=1915|publisher=[[Broadview Press]]|isbn=978-1-77048-538-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Rosner|first=Victoria|title=Modernism and the Architecture of Private Life|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hs4zCgAAQBAJ|date= 2008|publisher=[[Columbia University Press]]|isbn=978-0-231-13305-0}}
* {{cite book|last1=Sellers|first1=Susan|author-link1=Susan Sellers|title=Vanessa &amp; Virginia: A Novel|url=https://archive.org/details/vanessavirginia00sell|url-access=registration|date= 2010|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt|location=Boston|isbn=978-0-547-39388-9}}
* {{cite book|editor1-last=Sheppard|editor1-first=FHW|title=Survey of London. Vol. 38. South Kensington Museums Area|url=http://www.british-history.ac.uk/survey-london/vol38|date=1975|publisher=[[Institute of Historical Research]] ([[British History Online]])|location=London|isbn=978-0-485-48238-6}} see also ''[[Survey of London]]''
* {{cite book|last=Shukla|first=Bhaskar A.|title=Feminism:From Mary Wollstonecraft To Betty Friedan|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EgfmJBJjfIcC|year=2007|publisher=Sarup &amp; Sons|isbn=978-81-7625-754-1}}
* {{cite book|editor-last=Snodgrass|editor-first=Mary Ellen|editor-link=Mary Ellen Snodgrass|title=Encyclopedia of Feminist Literature|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=b5xbAgAAQBAJ|date= 2013|edition=2nd|publisher=Infobase Learning|isbn=978-1-4381-4064-3}}
* {{cite book|last=Stephen|first=Julia D.|author-link=Julia Stephen|editor1-last=Steele|editor1-first=Elizabeth |editor2-last=Gillespie|editor2-first=Dianne F|title=Julia Duckworth Stephen: Stories for Children, Essays for Adults|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VwquiPrOd9EC|year=1987|publisher=[[Syracuse University Press]]|isbn=978-0-8156-2592-6}}
** {{harvnb|Broughton|1989}} (Review)
* {{cite book|editor-last1=Stuart|editor-first1=Christopher|editor-last2=Todd|editor-first2=Stephanie|title=New Essays on Life Writing and the Body|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qO0YBwAAQBAJ|date= 2009|publisher=Cambridge Scholars Publishing|isbn=978-1-4438-0803-3}}
* {{Cite book|last=van Praag|first=Menna|year=2014|title=The house at the end of Hope Street: a novel |location=New York |publisher=Penguin Books |isbn=978-0143124948 |oclc=852829959}}
* {{cite book|last=Wilson|first=Scott|title=Resting Places: The Burial Sites of More Than 14,000 Famous Persons|edition=3rd|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FOHgDAAAQBAJ|date= 2016|publisher=[[McFarland &amp; Company]]|isbn=978-1-4766-2599-7}}
* {{cite book|last1=Woolf|first1=Virginia|editor1-last=Leaska|editor1-first=Mitchell A.|year=1977 |title=The Pargiters: The Novel-Essay Portion of The Years|location=New York|publisher=Harcourt Brace Jovanovich|isbn=0-15-671380-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Zimring|first=Rishona|title=Social Dance and the Modernist Imagination in Interwar Britain|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bByoDQAAQBAJ|date= 2016|publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]]|isbn=978-1-351-89959-8}}

==== {{anchor|VWB}}Biography: Virginia Woolf ====
* {{cite book|editor-last=Acheson|editor-first=James|title=Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=e9TwDQAAQBAJ|date= 2017|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]]|isbn=978-1-137-43083-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Bell|first=Quentin|author-link=Quentin Bell|title=Virginia Woolf: A Biography|url=https://archive.org/details/virginiawoolfbi000bell|year=1972|publisher=[[Harcourt Brace Jovanovich]]|isbn=978-0-15-693580-7}}
** Vol. I: Virginia Stephen 1882 to 1912.''  London: Hogarth Press. 1972.
** Vol. II:  Virginia Woolf 1912 to 1941.''  London: Hogarth Press. 1972.
* {{cite book|last=Bishop|first=Edward|title=A Virginia Woolf Chronology|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GN2uCwAAQBAJ|date= 1988|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]] UK|isbn=978-1-349-07881-3}}
* {{cite book|last=Bond|first=Alma Halbert|title=Who Killed Virginia Woolf?: A Psychobiography|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5L1CFtyLcG0C|year=2000|publisher=Insight Books Human Sciences|isbn=978-0-595-00205-4}}
** {{harvnb|Poole|1991}} (Review)
* {{cite book|editor-last1=Boynton|editor-first1=Victoria|editor-last2=Malin|editor-first2=Jo|title=Encyclopedia of Women's Autobiography: Volume 2 K-Z|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XlmmBOGvo6EC|year=2005|publisher=[[Greenwood Press]]|isbn=978-0-313-32739-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Brackenbury|first=Rosalind|title=Miss Stephen's Apprenticeship: How Virginia Stephen Became Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mZ1NDwAAQBAJ|date= 2018|publisher=[[University of Iowa Press]]|isbn=978-1-60938-551-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Briggs|first=Julia|title=Virginia Woolf: An Inner Life|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_Fn2kILpMkoC|year=2006a|publisher=[[Harcourt (publisher)|Harcourt]]|isbn=978-0-15-603229-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Curtis|first=Vanessa|title=Virginia Woolf's Women|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lWSzSTjldFkC|year=2002b|publisher=[[University of Wisconsin Press]]|isbn=978-0-299-18340-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Curtis|first=Anthony|title=Virginia Woolf: Bloomsbury &amp; Beyond|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KJJlAAAAMAAJ|year=2006|publisher=[[Haus Publishing]]|isbn=978-1-904950-23-3}}
* {{cite book|editor-last1=Czarnecki|editor-first1=Kristin|editor-last2=Rohman|editor-first2=Carrie|title=Virginia Woolf and the Natural World|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=efMwDgAAQBAJ|date= 2011|publisher=[[Liverpool University Press]]|isbn=978-1-942954-14-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Dalsimer|first=Katherine|title=Virginia Woolf: Becoming a Writer|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hEpFyKtNdscC|date= 2008|orig-year=2001|publisher=[[Yale University Press]]|isbn=978-0-300-13376-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Dally|first=Peter John|title=Virginia Woolf: The Marriage of Heaven and Hell|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CYVoAAAAMAAJ|date= 1999|publisher=[[Robson Books]]|isbn=978-1-86105-219-3}}
* {{cite book|last=DeSalvo|first=Louise A.|author-link=Louise DeSalvo|title=Virginia Woolf: The Impact of Childhood Sexual Abuse on Her Life and Work|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dtarQgAACAAJ|year=1989|publisher=[[Women's Press]]|isbn=978-0-7043-5042-7}}
** {{harvnb|Beattie|1989}} (Review)
** {{harvnb|Poole|1991}} (Review)
* {{cite book|last=Dunn|first=Jane|title=A Very Close Conspiracy: Vanessa Bell and Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gJP02k_T1ZYC|date= 1990|publisher=[[Random House]]|isbn=978-1-4464-3465-9}} (additional excerpts)
* {{cite book|last=Forrester|first=Viviane|author-link=Viviane Forrester|title=Virginia Woolf: A Portrait|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AXipBgAAQBAJ|date= 2015|publisher=[[Columbia University Press]]|isbn=978-0-231-53512-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Froula|first=Christine|title=Virginia Woolf and the Bloomsbury Avant-Garde: War, Civilization, Modernity|url=https://archive.org/details/virginiawoolfblo0000frou|url-access=registration|date= 2005|publisher=[[Columbia University Press]]|isbn=978-0-231-50878-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Goldman|first=Jane|title=The Cambridge Introduction to Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=74oONFoebsAC|date= 2006|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|isbn=978-1-139-45788-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Gordon|first=Lyndall|author-link=Lyndall Gordon|title=Virginia Woolf: A Writer's Life|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qp1bAAAAMAAJ|year=1984|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-811723-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Hall|first=Sarah M.|title=Before Leonard: The Early Suitors of Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=j5JlAAAAMAAJ|year=2006|publisher=[[peter Owen Publishers|Peter Owen]]|isbn=978-0-7206-1222-6}}
* {{cite book|last=Hall|first=Sarah M.|author-mask=1|title=The Bedside, Bathtub &amp; Armchair Companion to Virginia Woolf and Bloomsbury|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1bSWNgAACAAJ|date= 2007|publisher=Bloomsbury Academic|isbn=978-0-8264-8675-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Harris|first=Alexandra|author-link=Alexandra Harris|title=Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GgA7CwAAQBAJ|date= 2011|publisher=[[Thames &amp; Hudson]]|isbn=978-0-500-77097-9}}
** {{harvnb|Hadley|2011}} (Review)
* {{cite book|last1=Holtby|first1=Winifred|author-link=Winifred Holtby|title=Virginia Woolf: a critical memoir|date=2007|orig-year=1932|publisher=[[Bloomsbury Publishing|Bloomsbury]]|location=London|isbn=9780826494436|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=j0UeAQAAIAAJ}}
* {{cite book|last=Humm|first=Maggie|title=Snapshots of Bloomsbury: The Private Lives of Virginia Woolf and Vanessa Bell|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=stgZzIQAYyEC|year=2006|publisher=[[Rutgers University Press]]|isbn=978-0-8135-3706-1}}
* {{cite book|last=King|first=James|title=Virginia Woolf|url=https://archive.org/details/virginiawoolf00king|url-access=registration|year=1995|publisher=[[W. W. Norton &amp; Company|Norton]]|location=New York|isbn=978-0-393-03748-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Leaska|first=Mitchell A.|title=Granite and Rainbow: The Hidden Life of Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=avNcBknV9xEC|year=2000|publisher=Cooper Square Publishing, LLC|isbn=978-0-8154-1047-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Lee|first=Hermione|author-link=Hermione Lee|title=Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZW4KVeQM6CoC|year=1999|orig-year=1996|publisher=[[Vintage Books]]|isbn=978-0-375-70136-8}} (excerpt - Chapter 1)
** {{harvnb|Merkin|1997}} (Review)
*  {{cite book|last=Levenback|first=Karen L.|title=Virginia Woolf and the Great War|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Ujiurjch9TQC|year=1999|publisher=[[Syracuse University Press]]|isbn=978-0-8156-0546-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Licence|first=Amy|title=Living in Squares, Loving in Triangles: The Lives and Loves of Virginia Woolf and the Bloomsbury Group|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sWfGCQAAQBAJ|date= 2015|publisher=Amberley Publishing Limited|isbn=978-1-4456-4579-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Nadel|first=Ira|author-link=Ira Nadel|title=Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jjNmDQAAQBAJ|date= 2016|publisher=[[Reaktion Books]]|isbn=978-1-78023-712-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Nicolson|first=Nigel|author-link=Nigel Nicolson|title=Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=q6yg73mtjjUC|date= 2000|publisher=[[Penguin Publishing Group]]|isbn=978-1-4406-7921-6}}
** {{harvnb|Sweeney|2000}} (Review)
* {{cite book|last=Pearce|first=Brian Louis|title=Virginia Woolf and the Bloomsbury Group in Twickenham|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=g2zeoAEACAAJ|year=2007|publisher=Borough of Twickenham Local History Society|isbn=978-0-903341-80-6|page=7}}
* {{cite book|last=Poole|first=Roger|title=The Unknown Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KDk4AAAAIAAJ|year=1995|orig-year=1978|publisher=[[CUP Archive]]|isbn=978-0-521-48402-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Reid|first=Panthea|title=Art and Affection: A Life of Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wyFHB82sYOUC|year=1996|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-510195-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Rose|first=Phyllis|author-link=Phyllis Rose|title=Woman of Letters: A Life of Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LFPdky63WGkC|date=1979|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-502621-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Rosenman|first=Ellen Bayuk|title=The Invisible Presence: Virginia Woolf and the Mother-daughter Relationship|url=https://archive.org/details/invisiblepresenc0000rose|url-access=registration|year=1986|publisher=[[Louisiana State University Press]]|isbn=978-0-8071-1290-8}}
** {{harvnb|Caramagno|1989}} (Review)
* {{cite book|last=Silver|first=Brenda R.|title=Virginia Woolf Icon|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NR4CF9x1o0gC|year=1999|publisher=[[University of Chicago Press]]|isbn=978-0-226-75746-9}}
* {{cite book|editor-last=Snaith|editor-first=Anna|title=Palgrave Advances in Virginia Woolf Studies|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=h7uJDAAAQBAJ|date= 2007|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]] UK|isbn=978-0-230-20604-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Spalding|first=Frances|title=Virginia Woolf: Art, Life and Vision|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gc7poAEACAAJ|year=2014|publisher=[[National Portrait Gallery, London|National Portrait Gallery]], London|type=[https://www.npg.org.uk/whatson/virginiawoolf/home Exhibition catalogue]|isbn=978-1-85514-481-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Squier|first=Susan Merrill|title=Virginia Woolf and London: The Sexual Politics of the City|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JYU6DwAAQBAJ|date= 1985|publisher=[[University of North Carolina Press]]|isbn=978-1-4696-3991-8}}
* {{cite thesis |last=Streufert |first=Mary J. |date=8 June 1988 |title=Measures of reality: the religious life of Virginia Woolf |type=[[Master of Arts|MA]] thesis|url=http://ir.library.oregonstate.edu/concern/graduate_thesis_or_dissertations/7d278z05s |publisher=[[Oregon State University]]}}
* {{cite book|last=Wilson|first=Jean Moorcroft|title=Virginia Woolf Life and London. A Biography of Place|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_CRcyUYWzrIC|year=1987|publisher=Cecil Woolf|isbn=9781860646447}} (''Illustrations of Woolf's London homes are excerpted at {{harvtxt|UAH|2018}}.'')

===== {{anchor|Mental health biblio}}Mental health =====
* {{cite book|last=Bennett|first=Maxwell|title=Virginia Woolf and Neuropsychiatry|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xZdEAAAAQBAJ|date= 2013|publisher=[[Springer Science &amp; Business Media]]|isbn=978-94-007-5748-6}} [https://www.springer.com/gp/book/9789400757479 additional excerpts]
* {{cite book|last=Caramagno|first=Thomas C.|title=The Flight of the Mind: Virginia Woolf's Art and Manic-Depressive Illness|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dvTdFfPOYdAC|date= 1992|publisher=[[University of California Press]]|isbn=978-0-520-93512-9}} (summary)
* {{cite thesis|last=Drummer|first=Carlee Rader|title=The Broken Chrysalis: Virginia Woolf's Grieved Grief|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2FwhywAACAAJ|year=1989|publisher=[[Stony Brook University]]|type=PhD thesis}}
* {{cite book|last=Jamison|first=Kay Redfield|author-link=Kay Redfield Jamison|title=Touched With Fire|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8VMM61KHiVIC|date= 1996|publisher=[[Simon and Schuster]]|isbn=978-1-4391-0663-1}} see also ''[[Touched with Fire]]''
* {{cite book|last1=Meyer|first1=Robert G.|last2=Osborne|first2=Yvonne Hardaway|title=Case Studies in Abnormal Behavior|url=https://archive.org/details/casestudiesinabn00meye|url-access=registration|year=1982|publisher=Allyn and Bacon|isbn=978-0-205-07744-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Montross|first=Christine|author-link=Christine Montross|title=Falling into the Fire|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lw2aAgAAQBAJ|date= 2014|publisher=[[Oneworld Publications]]|isbn=978-1-78074-367-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Panken|first=Shirley|title=Virginia Woolf and the "Lust of Creation": A Psychoanalytic Exploration|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=de4UyeBbCIwC|year=1987|publisher=[[SUNY Press]]|isbn=978-0-88706-200-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Szasz|first=Thomas|author-link=Thomas Stephen Szasz|title=My Madness Saved Me: The Madness and Marriage of Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7qsxWjJtCKkC|date= 2011|publisher=[[Transaction Publishers]]|isbn=978-1-4128-0945-0}}
* {{cite thesis|last1=Trombley|first1=Stephen|author-link=Stephen Trombley|title=Virginia Woolf and her doctors|date=October 1980|publisher=[[University of Nottingham]]|url=http://eprints.nottingham.ac.uk/30895/1/290837.pdf|type=PhD thesis}}
* {{cite book|last=Trombley|first=Stephen|author-link=Stephen Trombley|title=All that Summer She was Mad: Virginia Woolf and Her Doctors|url=https://archive.org/details/allthatsummershe0000trom|url-access=registration|year=1981|publisher=Junction Books|location=London|isbn=978-0-86245-039-7}}
* {{cite book|last1=Webb|first1=Ruth|title=Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fJcgAQAAIAAJ|year=2000|publisher=[[British Library]]|isbn=9780712346160}}

==== Biography: Other ====
* {{cite book|last1=Bell|first1=Vanessa|editor-last=Marler|editor-first=Regina|author-link=Vanessa Bell|title=The Selected Letters of Vanessa Bell|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=burVAAAAMAAJ|year=1993|publisher=[[Pantheon Books]] |isbn=978-0-679-41939-6}}
** {{harvc|last1=Marler|first1=Regina|c=Biographical introduction|pp=xvii–xviii|in=Bell|year=1993}}
* {{cite book|last=Bennett|first=Mary|author-link=Mary Bennett|title=Who was Dr Jackson?: Two Calcutta Families, 1830–1855|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vtcMPQAACAAJ|year=2002|publisher=[[BACSA]]|isbn=978-0-907799-78-8}}
** {{harvnb|Vogeler|2014}} (Review)
* {{cite book|editor1-last=Bicknell|editor1-first=John W|title=Selected Letters of Leslie Stephen: Volume 1. 1864-1882|date=1996a|publisher=[[Macmillan Publishers|Macmillan]]|isbn=978-1-3492-4887-2 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=f2WwCwAAQBAJ}}
* {{cite book|editor1-last=Bicknell|editor1-first=John W|title=Selected Letters of Leslie Stephen: Volume 2. 1882-1904|date=1996b|publisher=[[Ohio State University Press]]|isbn=978-0-8142-0691-1 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lFZbAAAAMAAJ}}
* {{cite book|editor1-last=Bloom|editor1-first=Abigail Burnham|editor2-last=Maynard|editor2-first=John |title=Anne Thackeray Ritchie: Journals and letters|date=1994|publisher=Ohio State Univ. Press |location=Columbus |isbn=9780814206386|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SHnxiQMZKhwC}}
* {{cite book|last1=Brooke|first1=Rupert|last2=Strachey|first2=James|author-link1=Rupert Brooke|author-link2=James Strachey|editor-last=Hale|editor-first=Keith|title=Friends and Apostles: The Correspondence of Rupert Brooke and James Strachey, 1905–1914|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=U-8tjg6aliEC |year=1998|publisher=[[Yale University Press]]|isbn=978-0-300-07004-0|ref={{harvid|Hale|1998}}}}
* {{cite book|last=Curtis|first=Anthony|title=Before Bloomsbury: the 1890s diaries of three Kensington ladies : Margaret Lushington, Stella Duckworth and Mildred Massingberd|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7GAgAQAAIAAJ |year=2002a|publisher=The Eighteen Nineties Society|isbn=978-0-905744-28-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Delany|first=Paul|title=Fatal Glamour: The Life of Rupert Brooke |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YUbkBgAAQBAJ|date=2015|publisher=[[MQUP]]|isbn=978-0-7735-8278-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Garnett|first=Angelica|author-link=Angelica Garnett|title=Deceived With Kindness |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cOh2CsS6MlsC|date= 2011|orig-year=1985|publisher=[[Random House]] |isbn=978-1-4464-7525-6}}
* {{cite book| last=Garnett| first=Henrietta| title=Anny: A Life of Anny Thackeray Ritchie| url=https://books.google.com/books?id=t6cca0xnAKMC| year=2004a| publisher=[[Chatto &amp; Windus]]| location=London| isbn=0-7011-7129-4}}
** {{harvnb|Lee|2004}} (Review)
* {{cite book|last=Glendinning|first=Victoria|author-link=Victoria Glendinning|title=Leonard Woolf: A Biography |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=naqXH90lyvUC|date=2006|publisher=[[Simon and Schuster]] |isbn=978-0-7432-4653-8}}
** {{harvnb|Messud|2006}} (Review)
* {{cite book|last=Jones|first=Nigel|title=Rupert Brooke: Life, Death and Myth|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LjcQBQAAQBAJ|date= 2014|orig-year=1999 Metro Books|publisher=Head of Zeus|isbn=978-1-78185-715-1}}
** {{harvnb|Parker|1999}} (Review)
* {{cite book|last=Knights|first=Sarah|title=Bloomsbury's Outsider: A Life of David Garnett |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_010CAAAQBAJ|date= 2015|publisher=[[Bloomsbury Publishing]] |isbn=978-1-4482-1544-7}}
** {{harvnb|Taylor|2015}} (Review)
** {{harvnb|Wade|2015}} (Review)
* {{cite book|last=Llewellyn-Jones|first=Rosie|author-link=Rosie Llewellyn-Jones|title=The Louisa Parlby Album: Watercolours from Murshidabad 1795–1803|date=2017|publisher=Francesca Galloway|location=London |url=http://www.francescagalloway.com/usr/documents/exhibitions/list_of_works_url/31/the-louisa-parlby-album.pdf |type=Exhibition catalogue: 23 October – 1 December 2017|isbn=978-0-956-914-767}}
* {{cite book|last1=Maitland|first1=Frederic William|author-link=Frederic Maitland|title=The life and letters of Leslie Stephen|date=1906|publisher=[[Duckworth &amp; Co.]]|location=London |url=https://archive.org/details/lifelettersofles00maituoft|access-date=2 January 2018}}
* {{cite book|last=Moggridge|first=Donald Edward|title=Maynard Keynes: An Economist's Biography|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DFsctHxvFhoC|year=1992|publisher=[[Psychology Press]]|isbn=978-0-415-05141-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Olsen|first=Victoria|title=From Life: Julia Margaret Cameron &amp; Victorian Photography|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8kF-QgAACAAJ|year=2003|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]]|isbn=978-1-4039-6019-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Read|first=Mike|author-link=Mike Read|title=Forever England: The Life of Rupert Brooke|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tdkVBgAAQBAJ|date= 2015|publisher=[[Biteback Publishing]]|isbn=978-1-84954-866-3}}
* {{cite book|last=Rose|first=Phyllis|author-link=Phyllis Rose|title=Parallel Lives: Five Victorian Marriages|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EbRDDwAAQBAJ|year=1983|publisher=[[Vintage Books]]|isbn=978-0-394-72580-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Spalding|first=Frances|author-link=Frances Spalding|title=Gwen Raverat: Friends, Family and Affections|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WPwcNbrneJkC|date= 2010|publisher=[[Random House]]|isbn=978-1-4090-2941-0}}
* {{cite book|last1=Stephen|first1=Virginia|last2=Stephen|first2=Vanessa|last3=Stephen|first3=Thoby|author-link1=Virginia Woolf|author-link2=Vanessa Bell|author-link3=Thoby Stephen|title=Hyde Park Gate News: The Stephen Family Newspaper |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eJBlAAAAMAAJ|year=2005|publisher=[[Hesperus Press]]|isbn=978-1-84391-701-4|ref={{harvid|Stephens|2005}}}}
** {{cite web|title='Hyde Park Gate News', a magazine by Virginia Woolf and Vanessa Bell |url=https://www.bl.uk/collection-items/hyde-park-gate-news-a-magazine-by-virginia-woolf-and-vanessa-bell |website=Collection items|publisher=[[British Library]]|access-date=9 January 2018|type=Manuscript|ref={{harvid|BL|2018}}}}
* {{cite book|last=Tolley|first=Christopher|title=Domestic Biography: The Legacy of Evangelicalism in Four Nineteenth-century Families|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ygrK5ygfLwQC|year=1997|publisher=[[Clarendon Press]] |isbn=978-0-19-820651-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Venn|first=John|author-link=John Venn|title=Annals of a Clerical Family: Being Some Account of the Family and Descendants of William Venn, Vicar of Otterton, Devon, 1600-1621 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rRcFkXb_-OoC|date=2012|orig-year=1904 Macmillan, London|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|isbn=978-1-108-04492-9|ref={{harvid|Venn|1904}}}} ''also Internet archive''
* {{cite book|editor-last1=Wolf|editor-first1=Sylvia|title=Julia Margaret Cameron's Women|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7Ygst7kkrlsC|year=1998|publisher=[[Art Institute of Chicago]]|isbn=978-0-300-07781-0}} ''also available through [[MOMA]]'' ''here''
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Leonard|author-link=Leonard Woolf|title=Growing: an autobiography of the years 1904 to 1911|url=https://archive.org/details/growingautobiogr00wool|url-access=registration|date= 1989|orig-year=1962 |publisher=[[Harcourt Brace Jovanovich]]|isbn=978-0-15-637215-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Woolf|first=Leonard|author-link=Leonard Woolf|author-mask=1|title=Beginning Again: An Autobiography of the Years 1911 to 1918|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UNsPAQAAMAAJ|year=1975|orig-year=1964|publisher=[[Harcourt Brace Jovanovich]]|isbn=978-0-15-611680-0|ref={{harvid|Woolf|1964}}}}

==== Literary commentary ====
* {{cite book|editor-last1=Alexander|editor-first1=Christine|editor-last2=McMaster|editor-first2=Juliet|title=The Child Writer from Austen to Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=odBIxjAhjbsC|date= 2005|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=978-0-521-81293-1}}
* {{cite book|editor-last1=Barrett|editor-first1=Eileen|editor-last2=Cramer|editor-first2=Patricia|title=Virginia Woolf: Lesbian Readings|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JNQyMMwYVCwC|date= 1997|publisher=[[NYU Press]] |isbn=978-0-8147-1263-4}}
** {{harvc|last=Cramer|first=Patricia|c=Part 2: Lesbian readings of Woolf's novels – Introduction |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sH8UCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA117|pp=117–127|in1=Barrett|in2=Cramer|year=1997}}
* {{cite book|editor-last=Bloom|editor-first=Harold|editor-link=Harold Bloom|title=Virginia Woolf |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=n5bhcVB2YS0C|year=2009|publisher=[[Infobase Publishing]] |isbn=978-1-4381-1548-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Beja|first=Morris|title=Critical essays on Virginia Woolf |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-6snAQAAMAAJ|year=1985|publisher=[[G. K. Hall &amp; Co.|G. K. Hall]] |isbn=978-0-8161-8753-9}}
* {{cite book|editor-last=Berman|editor-first=Jessica|title=A Companion to Virginia Woolf |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wERcCwAAQBAJ|date= 2016|publisher=[[John Wiley &amp; Sons|Wiley]] |isbn=978-1-118-45790-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Blair|first=Emily|title=Virginia Woolf and the Nineteenth-Century Domestic Novel |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=19lz01yFmpcC|date= 2012|publisher=[[SUNY Press]] |isbn=978-0-7914-7992-6}}
* {{cite book|last=Blamires|first=Harry|author-link=Harry Blamires|title=A Guide to Twentieth Century Literature in English|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hzUOAAAAQAAJ|date=1983 |publisher=[[Methuen Publishing|Methuen]] |isbn=978-0-416-36450-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Booth|first=Alison|title=Greatness Engendered: George Eliot and Virginia Woolf |url=https://archive.org/details/greatnessengende00boot|url-access=registration|year=1992 |publisher=[[Cornell University Press]] |isbn=0-8014-9930-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Briggs|first=Julia|title=Reading Virginia Woolf |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=udGqBgAAQBAJ |date=2006b|publisher=[[Edinburgh University Press]]|isbn=978-0-7486-2695-3}}
* {{cite thesis|last1=Bunyan|first1=David|title=Virginia Woolf's views of consciousness in relation to art and life|year=1970|publisher=Department of English Studies, [[Durham University]] |type=[[MLitt]] thesis}}
* {{cite book|last=Dalgarno|first=Emily|title=Virginia Woolf and the Visible World |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4HkNDsdlddcC|date= 2007|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=978-0-521-03360-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Ellis|first=Steve|title=Virginia Woolf and the Victorians |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=L2XHm0iR8-QC|date= 2007|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=978-1-139-46896-1}} (additional excerpts)
* {{cite book|last=Goldman|first=Jane|title=The Feminist Aesthetics of Virginia Woolf: Modernism, Post-Impressionism, and the Politics of the Visual|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AlfnMhfkmPYC |date=2001|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=978-0-521-79458-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Gruber|first=Ruth|author-link=Ruth Gruber|title=Virginia Woolf: The Will to Create as a Woman |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lkZhelIfs8UC|date= 2012|orig-year=2005|publisher=[[Open Road Media]] |isbn=978-1-4532-4864-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Hague|first=Angela|title=Fiction, Intuition, &amp; Creativity: Studies in Brontë, James, Woolf, and Lessing|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=95_C3LCSrCEC|year=2003|publisher=[[CUA Press]] |isbn=978-0-8132-1314-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Hill-Miller|first=Katherine|title=From the Lighthouse to Monk's House: A Guide to Virginia Woolf's Literary Landscapes|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6oFbAAAAMAAJ|date=2001 |publisher=[[Duckworth Overlook|Duckworth]] |isbn=978-0-7156-2995-6}}
* {{cite book|editor-last=Humm|editor-first= Maggie|title=Edinburgh Companion to Virginia Woolf and the Arts |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vJgkDQAAQBAJ|year=2010|publisher=[[Edinburgh University Press]] |isbn=978-0-7486-3553-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Hussey|first=Mark|title=Virginia Woolf and war: fiction, reality, and myth |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=j35bAAAAMAAJ|date=1991|publisher=[[Syracuse University Press]] |isbn=978-0-8156-2537-7}}
* {{cite book|last1=Kirkpatrick|first1=Brownlee Jean|last2=Clarke|first2=Stuart N.|title=A Bibliography of Virginia Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ds1kAAAAMAAJ|year=1997|publisher=[[Clarendon Press]] |isbn=978-0-19-818383-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Koutsantoni|first=Dr Katerina|title=Virginia Woolf's Common Reader |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wt3ivsDLyPQC|date=2013|publisher=[[Ashgate Publishing]], Ltd. |isbn=978-1-4094-7526-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Latham|first=Sean|title="Am I a Snob?": Modernism and the Novel |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LOIkfPVVYNIC|year=2003|publisher=[[Cornell University Press]] |isbn=0-8014-8841-9}}
** {{harvnb|Hite|2004}} (Review)
* {{cite book|last=Lee|first=Hermione|author-link=Hermione Lee|title=The novels of Virginia Woolf |url=https://archive.org/details/novelsofvirginia0000leeh|url-access=registration|date=1977 |publisher=Holmes &amp; Meier|isbn=9780841903142}}
* {{cite thesis|last1=Madden|first1=Mary C|title=Virginia Woolf and the persistent question of class: The protean nature of class and self|date=31 March 2006|publisher=Department of English, [[University of South Florida]] |url=http://scholarcommons.usf.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3611&amp;context=etd|type=PhD thesis}}
* {{cite book|last1=Majumdar|first1=Robin|last2=McLaurin|first2=Allen|title=Virginia Woolf: The critical heritage |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=IznJAwAAQBAJ|date=2003|orig-year=1975|publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=978-1-134-72404-8}}
* {{cite book|editor-last1=Martin|editor-first1=Ann|editor-last2=Holland|editor-first2=Kathryn |title=Interdisciplinary / Multidisciplinary Woolf: Selected Papers from the Twenty-Second Annual International Conference on Virginia Woolf |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uhoaDgAAQBAJ|date=June 2013|publisher=[[Liverpool University Press]]|isbn=978-0-9890826-2-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Miller|first=C. Ruth|title=Virginia Woolf: The Frames of Art and Life |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tkOvCwAAQBAJ|date=24 November 1988|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]] UK |isbn=978-1-349-19595-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Paul|first=Janis M.|title=The Victorian heritage of Virginia Woolf: the external world in her novels|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=93xbAAAAMAAJ|year=1987|publisher=Pilgrim Books|isbn=978-0-937664-73-5}}
* {{cite book|editor-last1=Randall|editor-first1=Bryony|editor-last2=Goldman|editor-first2=Jane |title=Virginia Woolf in Context|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9iNred5Ctn4C|date= 2012|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=978-1-107-00361-3}}
* {{cite thesis|last1=Rhydderch|first1=Francesca|title=Cultural translations: A comparative critical study of Kate Roberts and Virginia Woolf|year=2000|type=[[PhD thesis]]|publisher=[[University of Wales, Aberystwyth]] |url=https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/1921915.pdf}}
* {{cite book|editor-last1=Ryan|editor-first1=Derek|editor-last2=Bolaki|editor-first2=Stella |title=Contradictory Woolf|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5fIwDgAAQBAJ|date= 2012|publisher=[[Liverpool University Press]]|isbn=978-1-942954-11-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Sellers|first=Susan|author-link=Susan Sellers|title=The Cambridge Companion to Virginia Woolf |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZpQ4GG-Ng2gC|date= 2010|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=978-0-521-89694-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Sim|first=Lorraine|title=Virginia Woolf: The Patterns of Ordinary Experience |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4QeOCwAAQBAJ|date=2016|publisher=[[Routledge]]|isbn=978-1-317-00160-7 |chapter=Introduction |pages=1–26 |chapter-url=http://docshare01.docshare.tips/files/8192/81926159.pdf}}
* {{cite book|last=Simpson|first=Kathryn|title=Woolf: A Guide for the Perplexed |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lPE8CwAAQBAJ|date= 2016|publisher=[[Bloomsbury Publishing]]|isbn=978-1-4725-9068-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Transue|first=Pamela J.|title=Virginia Woolf and the Politics of Style |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7h57SNNzy3kC|year=1986|publisher=[[SUNY Press]]|location=Albany, NY |isbn=978-1-4384-2228-2}}
* {{cite book|editor-last1=Zamith|editor-first1=Maria Cândida|editor-last2=Flora|editor-first2=Luísa |title=Virginia Woolf: Three Centenary Celebrations|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=l_j4ln5cEI8C |year=2007|publisher=[[Universidade do Porto]] |isbn=978-972-8932-23-7}} [http://dspace.uevora.pt/rdpc/bitstream/10174/21533/1/Moments%20of%20Being.pdf additional excerpt]
* {{cite book|last=Zink|first=Suzana|title=Virginia Woolf's Rooms and the Spaces of Modernity |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3kFKDwAAQBAJ|date= 2018|publisher=[[Springer Nature]] |isbn=978-3-319-71909-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Zwerdling|first=Alex|title=Virginia Woolf and the Real World |url=https://archive.org/details/virginiawoolfrea0000zwer|url-access=registration|year=1986|publisher=[[University of California Press]]|isbn=978-0-520-06184-2}}
** {{harvnb|Caramagno|1989}} (Review)
** {{harvnb|Middleton|1987}} (Review)
** {{harvnb|Pearce|1987}} (Review)

==== Bloomsbury ====
* {{cite book|last1=Caws|first1=Mary Ann|last2=Wright|first2=Sarah Bird|title=Bloomsbury and France: Art and Friends|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=U8MeZDksY1wC|date=1999|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-802781-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Rosenbaum|first=S.P.|title=Victorian Bloomsbury: Volume 1: The Early Literary History of the Bloomsbury Group|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZtS-DAAAQBAJ|date= 2016|orig-year=1987|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]]|isbn=978-1-349-13368-0|ref={{harvid|Rosenbaum|1987}}}} (additional excerpts)
* {{cite book|last=Rosenbaum|first=S.|author-mask=1|title=Edwardian Bloomsbury: The Early Literary History of the Bloomsbury Group|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XAK_DAAAQBAJ|date= 2016|orig-year=1994|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]]|isbn=978-1-349-23237-6}}
* {{cite book|last=Rosenbaum|first=S.|author-mask=1|title=Georgian Bloomsbury: Volume 3: The Early Literary History of the Bloomsbury Group, 1910–1914|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Pyl9DAAAQBAJ|date= 2003|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]] UK|isbn=978-0-230-50512-4}}
* {{cite book|last1=Rosenbaum|first1=S.|author-mask=1|last2=Haule|first2=J.|title=The Bloomsbury Group Memoir Club|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kv3MCwAAQBAJ|date= 2014|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]] UK|isbn=978-1-137-36036-6}}
** {{harvnb|Hughes|2014}} (Review)
* {{cite book|editor-last=Rosner|editor-first=Victoria|title=The Cambridge Companion to the Bloomsbury Group|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=k66BAwAAQBAJ|date=2014|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|isbn=978-1-107-01824-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Todd|first=Pamela|title=Bloomsbury at Home|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DZxMAAAAYAAJ|year=2001|publisher=[[Pavilion Books|Pavilion]]|isbn=978-1-86205-428-8}}
* {{cite book|last1=Woolf|first1=Virginia|last2=Raverat|first2=Gwen|last3=Raverat|first3=Jacques|author-link1=Virginia Woolf|author-link2=Gwen Raverat|author-link3=Jacques Raverat|editor-last=Pryor|editor-first=William |title=Virginia Woolf &amp; the Raverats: A Different Sort of Friendship|publisher=Clear Books |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UiB3bpUQb6AC|year=2003|isbn=978-1-904555-02-5 |ref={{harvid|Pryor|2003}}}}

==== Chapters and contributions ====
* {{cite book|last1=Alexander|first1=Christine|title=Play and apprenticeship: the culture of family magazines|date=2005|pages=31–50}}, in {{harvtxt|Alexander|McMaster|2005}}
* {{cite book|last1=Birrento|first1=Ana Clara|title=Virginia Woolf: Moments of Being|pages=61–72|url=http://dspace.uevora.pt/rdpc/bitstream/10174/21533/1/Moments%20of%20Being.pdf|ref={{harvid|Birrento|2007}}}}, in {{harvtxt|Zamith|Flora|2007}}
* {{cite book|last1=Brassard|first1=Geneviève|title=Woolf in translation|date=2016|pages=441–452|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wERcCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA44|isbn=9781118457900}}, in {{harvtxt|Berman|2016}}
* {{cite book|last1=Dunlap|first1=Sarah|title="One Must Be Scientific": Natural History and Ecology in Mrs. Dalloway|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uhoaDgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA127|date=2013|pages=127–131|isbn=9780989082624}}, in {{harvtxt|Martin|Holland|2013}}
* {{cite book|last1=Flint|first1=Kate|title=Victorian Roots: The sense of the past in Mrs Dalloway and To the Lighthouse|pages=46–59|ref={{harvid|Flint|2017}}}}, in {{harvtxt|Acheson|2017}}
* {{cite book|last1=Gerzina|first1=Gretchen Holbrook|author-link=Gretchen Gerzina|title=Virginia Woolf, Performing Race|date=2010|pages=74–87|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vJgkDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA75|isbn=9780748635535}}, in {{harvtxt|Humm|2010}}
* {{cite book|last1=Gillespie|first1=Diane F|title=The elusive Julia Stephen|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VwquiPrOd9EC&amp;pg=PA1|pages=1–28|ref={{harvid|Gillespie|1987}}|isbn=9780815625926|date=April 1993}}, in {{harvtxt|Stephen|1987}}
* {{cite book|last1=Hussey|first1=Mark|title=Preface|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=waY3ksumjxUC&amp;pg=PT9|date=2006|pages=ix–xviii|isbn=9780547543161}}, in {{harvtxt|Woolf|1928}}
* {{cite book|last1=Hussey|first1=Mark|title=Biographical approaches|date=2007|pages=83–97}}, in {{harvtxt|Snaith|2007}}
* {{cite book|last1=Hussey|first1=Mark|title=Woolf: After Lives|date=2012|pages=13–27|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9iNred5Ctn4C&amp;pg=PA13|isbn=9781107003613}}, in {{harvtxt|Randall|Goldman|2012}}
* {{cite book|last1=Lee|first1=Hermione|author-link=Hermione Lee|title=Virginia Woolf and Offence|date=1995 |url=http://www.oxfordscholarship.com/view/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780198182894.001.0001/acprof-9780198182894-chapter-10 |pages=129–150|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=9780191673917}}, in {{harvtxt|Batchelor|1995}}
* {{cite book|last=Lilienfeld|first=Jane|title='The Gift of a China Inkpot': Violet Dickinson, Virginia Woolf, Elizabeth Gaskell, Charlotte Brontë and the Love of Women in Writing |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sH8UCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA117 |date=1997|pages=35–56|isbn=9780814712641}}, in {{harvtxt|Barrett|Cramer|1997}}
* {{cite book|last1=Minow-Pinkney|first1=Makiko|title=Psychonalytic approaches |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=h7uJDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA60e|date=2007|pages=60–82|isbn=9780230206045}}, in {{harvtxt|Snaith|2007}}
* {{cite book|last1=Minow-Pinkney|first1=Makiko|title=Domestic Arts: Virginia Woolf and entertaining |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vJgkDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA230|pages=227–244|date=2006|isbn=9780748635535}}, in {{harvtxt|Humm|2006}}
* {{cite book|last1=Ross|first1=Stephen|title=Introduction|date=2014|pages=9–46}}, in {{harvtxt|Richardson|2014}}
* {{cite book|last1=Stimpson|first1=Catherine R|title=Foreword|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NR4CF9x1o0gC&amp;pg=PR11|pages=xi–xiv|date=1999|isbn=9780226757469}}, in {{harvtxt|Silver|1999}}

=== Articles ===
'''Journals'''

* {{cite journal|last1=Banks|first1=Joanne Trautmann|title=Mrs Woolf in Harley Street|journal=[[The Lancet]]|date=April 1998|volume=351|issue=9109|pages=1124–1126|doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(98)02502-1|pmid=9660599|s2cid=206010710}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Barzilai|first1=Shuli|title=Virginia Woolf's Pursuit of Truth: "Monday or Tuesday", "Moments of Being" and "The Lady in the Looking-Glass"|journal=The Journal of Narrative Technique|year=1988|volume=18|issue=3|pages=199–210|jstor=30225221}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Bell|first1=Quentin|author-link=Quentin Bell|title=The Mausoleum Book|journal=A Review of English Literature|year=1965|volume=6|issue=1|pages=9–18}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Boeira|first1=Manuela V.|last2=Berni|first2=Gabriela de Á.|last3=Passos|first3=Ives C.|last4=Kauer-Sant'Anna|first4=Márcia|last5=Kapczinski|first5=Flávio|title=Virginia Woolf, neuroprogression, and bipolar disorder|journal=Revista Brasileira de Psiquiatria|date=14 June 2016|volume=39|issue=1|pages=69–71|doi=10.1590/1516-4446-2016-1962|pmid=27304258|pmc=7112729|ref={{harvid|Boeira et al|2016}}|doi-access=free}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Bond|first1=Alma Halbert|title=Virginia Woolf and Leslie Stephen: a father's contribution to psychosis and genius.|journal=The Journal of the American Academy of Psychoanalysis |date=October 1986 |volume=14 |issue=4 |pages=507–524 |pmid=3771329|doi=10.1521/jaap.1.1986.14.4.507}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Caramagno|first1=Thomas C.|title=Review of Virginia Woolf and the Real World; The Invisible Presence: Virginia Woolf and the Mother-Daughter Relationship|journal=[[Modern Philology]] |year=1989 |volume=86 |issue=3 |pages=324–328|jstor=438044|type=Review|doi=10.1086/391719}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Church|first1=Johanna|title=Literary Representations of Shell Shock as a Result of World War I in the Works of Virginia Woolf and Ernest Hemingway|journal=[[Peace &amp; Change]]|date=January 2016 |volume=41 |issue=1 |pages=52–63|doi=10.1111/pech.12172}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Dalsimer|first1=Katherine|title=Virginia Woolf (1882–1941)|journal=[[American Journal of Psychiatry]]|date=May 2004|volume=161|issue=5|pages=809|doi=10.1176/appi.ajp.161.5.809|pmid=15121644}}
* {{cite journal|last1=DeSalvo|first1=Louise A.|author-link=Louise DeSalvo|title=Lighting the Cave: The Relationship between Vita Sackville-West and Virginia Woolf|jstor=3173896|journal=[[Signs (journal)|Signs]]|volume=8|issue=2|date = Winter 1982|pages=195–214|doi=10.1086/493959|s2cid=144131048}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Floyd|first1=Riley H.|title="Must Tell the Whole World": Septimus Smith as Virginia Woolf's Legal Messenge|journal=[[Indiana Law Journal]]|date=Summer 2016|volume=91|issue=4 (9) |pages=14721492 |url=http://www.repository.law.indiana.edu/ilj/vol91/iss4/9}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Haule|first1=James|title= Virginia Woolf's First Voyage: A Novel in the Making by Louise A. DeSalvo; Melymbrosia: An Early Version of "The Voyage out" by Virginia Woolf and Louise A. DeSalvo|journal=[[Contemporary Literature (journal)|Contemporary Literature]]|date=Winter 1982|volume=23|issue=1|pages=100–104|doi=10.2307/1208147|jstor=1208147 |type=Review}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Hite|first1=Molly|title=Am I a Snob? Modernism and the Novel|journal=[[Modernism/modernity]]|date=11 March 2004|volume=11|issue=1|pages=190–192|doi=10.1353/mod.2004.0011|s2cid=143644837|issn=1080-6601 |type=Review}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Jones|first1= Christine Kenyon |last2=Snaith|first2= Anna |title="Tilting at Universities": Woolf at King's College London|url=https://www.questia.com/library/journal/1G1-281175673/tilting-at-universities-woolf-at-king-s-college|journal=Woolf Studies Annual|volume=16|year=2010a|pages=1–44}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Jones|first1= Christine Kenyon |last2=Snaith|first2= Anna |title= A castle of one's own|url=https://issuu.com/kingscollegelondon/docs/report_2009/28|date=31 January 2010b|journal=Kings College Report |volume=17 |pages=26–31}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Lackey|first1=Michael|title=Virginia Woolf and British Russophilia|journal=[[Journal of Modern Literature]] |year=2012 |volume=36 |issue=1 |pages=150 |doi=10.2979/jmodelite.36.1.150 |s2cid=161783820 |url=https://digitalcommons.morris.umn.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1024&amp;context=eng_facpubs}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Leonard|first1=Diane R.|title=Proust and Virginia Woolf, Ruskin and Roger Fry: Modernist Visual Dynamics|journal=[[Comparative Literature Studies]]|year=1981|volume=18|issue=3|pages=333–343|jstor=40246272}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Koutsantoni|first1=Katerina|title=Manic depression in literature: the case of Virginia Woolf|journal=[[Medical Humanities]]|date=June 2012|volume=38|issue=1|pages=7–14|doi=10.1136/medhum-2011-010075 |pmid=22389442 |s2cid=32059883}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Koutsantoni|last2=Oakley|first2=Madeleine|title=Hypothesis of Autism and Psychosis in the Case of Laura Makepeace Stephen|journal=Disability Studies|date=2 April 2014 |volume=4 |issue=3 |doi=10.2139/ssrn.2418709 |ssrn=2418709}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Lewis|first1=Alison M|title=Caroline Emelia Stephen (1834-1909) and Virginia Woolf (1882-1941): A Quaker Influence on Modern English Literature|journal=Quaker Theology|date=Autumn 2000|issue=3|url=http://quakertheology.org/issue3-3.html|access-date=12 February 2018}}
* {{cite journal|last1=McManus|first1= Patricia |title=The "Offensiveness" of Virginia Woolf: From a Moral to a Political Reading|url=https://www.questia.com/library/journal/1G1-219520177/the-offensiveness-of-virginia-woolf-from-a-moral|journal=Woolf Studies Annual|volume=14|year=2008|pages=92–138}}
* {{cite journal|last1=McNicol|first1=Jean|title=Something Rather Scandalous|journal=[[London Review of Books]]|date=20 October 2016|volume=38|issue=20|pages=19–22|url=https://www.lrb.co.uk/v38/n20/jean-mcnicol/something-rather-scandalous|issn=0260-9592}}
* {{cite journal|last1=McTaggart|first1=Ursula|title="Opening the Door": The Hogarth Press as Virginia Woolf's Outsiders' Society|journal=[[Tulsa Studies in Women's Literature]]|volume=29|issue=1|pages=63–81 |year=2010 |jstor=41337032}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Majumdar|first1=Raja|title=Virginia Woolf and Thoreau|journal=The Thoreau Society Bulletin|date=Fall 1969|issue=109|pages=4–5|url=https://archive.org/details/thoreausociety1969109unse}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Metzgar|first1=Lisa|title="All This One Could Never Share;" Virginia Woolf and the Conflict between Community and Independence|journal=Matrix|date=Spring 1998 |volume=1 |issue=1 |url=https://writing.colostate.edu/gallery/matrix/metzgar.cfm|publisher=[[Colorado State University]]}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Middleton|first1=Victoria|title=Alex Zwerdling: Virginia Woolf and the Real World |journal=Rocky Mountain Review of Language and Literature|year=1987|volume=41|issue=4|pages=277–278 |doi=10.2307/1347313 |jstor=1347313|type=Review}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Pearce|first1=Richard|title=Review: Virginia Woolf's Reality|journal=[[Novel: A Forum on Fiction]]|date=Autumn 1987|volume=21|issue=1|pages=93–96|doi=10.2307/1345993|jstor=1345993|type=Review}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Poole|first1=Roger|title=Virginia Woolf: The Impact of Childhood Sexual Abuse on Her Life and Work, and: Who Killed Virginia Woolf?: A Psychobiography, and: Virginia Woolf: A Study of the Short Fiction, and: Virginia Woolf: Strategist of Language|type= Review|journal=MFS Modern Fiction Studies|year=1991|volume=37|issue=2|pages=300–305|doi=10.1353/mfs.0.0773|s2cid=162382065}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Rodríguez|first1=Laura María Lojo|title=Contradiction and ambivalence: Virginia Woolf and the aesthetic experience in "The Duchess and the Jeweller"|journal=Journal of English Studies|date=2001–2002 |volume=3 |pages=115–129|doi=10.18172/jes.73|doi-access=free |url=https://publicaciones.unirioja.es/ojs/index.php/jes/article/viewFile/73/53}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Schröder|first1=Leena Kore|title=Tales of Abjection and Miscegenation: Virginia Woolf's and Leonard Woolf's "Jewish" Stories|journal=Twentieth Century Literature|volume=49|issue=3 |pages=298–327|date=Autumn 2003 |doi=10.2307/3175983|jstor=3175983}} (''text also available here'')
* {{cite journal|last1=Smith|first1=Victoria L.|title=Ransacking the Language": Finding the Missing Goods in Virginia Woolf's "Orlando|journal=[[Journal of Modern Literature]]|year=2006|volume=29|issue=4 |pages=57–75 |jstor=3831880}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Swenson|first1=Kristine|title=Hothouse Victorians: Art and Agency in Freshwater|journal=Open Cultural Studies|date=26 October 2017|volume=1|issue=1|pages=183–193|doi=10.1515/culture-2017-0017|doi-access=free}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Terr|author-link=Lenore Terr|first1=LC|title=Who's afraid in Virginia Woolf? Clues to early sexual abuse in literature.|journal=The Psychoanalytic Study of the Child|year=1990|volume=45 |pages=533–546 |pmid=2251325|doi=10.1080/00797308.1990.11823533 |url=https://digital.lib.utk.edu/collections/islandora/object/playbills%3A7706/datastream/PDF/view}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Usui|first1=Masami|title=Julia Margaret Cameron as a Feminist Precursor of Virginia Woolf|journal=Doshisha Studies in English|year=2007|volume=80|issue=3|pages=59–83 |url=https://doors.doshisha.ac.jp/duar/repository/ir/13075/020000800003.pdf |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160413032023/https://doors.doshisha.ac.jp/duar/repository/ir/13075/020000800003.pdf |archive-date=2016-04-13}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Vogeler|first1=Martha S.|title=Bennett, Mary. Who Was Dr. Jackson? Two Calcutta Families: 1830–1855. London: British Association for Cemeteries in South Asia. 2002. Pp. xv, 116. £12. {{Text|ISBN}} 0-90779-9-78-71 |journal=[[Albion (journal)|Albion]] |date=11 July 2014 |volume=36 |issue=2 |pages=388–389 |doi=10.2307/4054289 |jstor=4054289 |type=Review}}

'''Dictionaries and encyclopaedias'''

* {{Cite ODNB|last=Bell|first= Alan |id=36271|title=Stephen, Sir Leslie (1832–1904)|date=24 May 2012}}
* {{cite encyclopedia|editor1-last=Byers|editor1-first=Paula|title=Virginia Stephen Woolf|year=2004 |encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of World Biography |url=https://www.encyclopedia.com/people/literature-and-arts/english-literature-20th-cent-present-biographies/virginia-stephen-woolf |publisher=[[Gale Group]]}}
* {{Cite ODNB|last=Garnett|first=Jane |id=46943|title=Stephen [née Jackson], Julia Prinsep (1846–1895) |date=23 September 2004b}}
* {{Cite ODNB|last=Gordon|first=Lyndall|author-link=Lyndall Gordon|title=Woolf [née Stephen], (Adeline) Virginia|id=37018|year=2004|freearticle=y (or omit)}} {{free access}} 
* {{cite encyclopedia|last1=Luebering|first1=J. E.|title=Sir Leslie Stephen|date=21 December 2006 |encyclopedia=[[Encyclopædia Britannica]] |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Leslie-Stephen |access-date=2 January 2018}}
* {{cite encyclopedia|last1=Reid|first1=Panthea|title=Virginia Woolf|encyclopedia=[[Encyclopaedia Britannica]] |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Virginia-Woolf}}

'''Newspapers and magazines'''

* {{cite news|last1=Ackroyd|first1=Peter|author-link=Peter Ackroyd|title=The knots and loops of literature|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1988/03/27/books/the-knots-and-loops-of-literature.html|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=27 March 1988|type=Review}}
* {{cite news| last=Anonymous|title=Google celebrates 136th birthday of Virginia Woolf with a doodle|url=https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/business/india-business/google-doodle-celebrates-136th-birthday-of-virginia-woolf/articleshow/62641566.cms| work=[[The Times of India]]| date=25 January 2018| access-date=25 January 2018|ref={{harvid|TOI|2018}}}}
* {{cite news| last=Anonymous|title=1 May (1912): Virginia Stephen Woolf to Leonard Woolf |url=http://theamericanreader.com/01-may-1912-virginia-stephen-woolf-to-leonard-woolf/|access-date=22 March 2018|work=The American Reader |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150602001839/http://theamericanreader.com/01-may-1912-virginia-stephen-woolf-to-leonard-woolf/ |archive-date=2015-06-02 |url-status=unfit |ref={{harvid|The American Reader}}}}
* {{cite news|last1=Auden|first1=W. H.|author-link=W. H. Auden|title=Virginia Woolf: A Consciousness of Reality |url=https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/1954/03/06/a-consciousness-of-reality |work=[[The New Yorker]] |date=27 February 1954 |type=Review}}
* {{cite news|last1=Bas|first1=Marcel|title=Virginia Woolf's Class Consciousness: Snubbing or uplifting the masses?|url=http://roepstem.net/woolf.html|work=Die Roepstem|date=23 January 2008}}
* {{cite news|last1=Beattie|first1=L. Elisabeth|title=In short|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=23 July 1989|url=https://www.nytimes.com/books/00/12/17/specials/woolf-desalvo.html|type=Review}}
* {{cite news|last1=Bollen|first1=Christopher|author-link=Christopher Bollen|title=Toni Morrison |url=https://www.interviewmagazine.com/culture/toni-morrison#_ |access-date=23 February 2018|work=[[Interview (magazine)|Interview]] |date=1 May 2012}}
* {{cite news|last1=Brockes|first1=Emma|author-link=Emma Brockes|title=Michael Cunningham: A life in writing|url=https://www.theguardian.com/culture/2011/feb/07/michael-cunningham-life-writing|access-date=23 February 2018|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=7 February 2011}}
* {{cite magazine|last1=Broughton|first1=Panthea Reid|title=Julia Stephen's Prose: An Unintentional Self-Portrait|magazine=English Literature in Transition, 1880-1920|year=1989|volume=22|issue=1|pages=125–128 |url=https://muse.jhu.edu/article/373158/pdf|type=Review}}
* {{cite news|last=Brown|first=Mark|title=Virginia Woolf celebrated in gallery she spurned as it was 'filled with men'|date=9 July 2014|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2014/jul/09/virginia-woolf-gallery-national-portrait |work=[[The Guardian]]}}
* {{cite news|last1=Edel|first1=Leon|author-link=Leon Edel|title=Triumphs and Symptoms |url=https://archive.nytimes.com/www.nytimes.com/books/00/12/17/specials/woolf-letters4.html |access-date=13 April 2018|work=[[The New York Times]] |date=25 March 1979|type=Review}}
* {{cite news|last1=Fallon|first1=Claire|title=Virginia Woolf's Guide To Grieving |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.ca/entry/virginia-woolfs-guide-to-grieving_us_56a5854be4b0404eb8f20a3b |access-date=9 February 2018|work=[[HuffPost]] |date=25 January 2016}}{{free access}} 
* {{cite magazine|last=Gross|first=John|author-link=John Gross|title=Mr. Virginia Woolf|magazine=[[Commentary (magazine)|Commentary]]|url=https://www.commentarymagazine.com/articles/mr-virginia-woolf/ |date=1 December 2006}} [https://web.archive.org/web/20070228055659/http://www.commentarymagazine.com/cm/main/viewArticle.aip?id=10801&amp;page=2 ''archived version'']
* {{cite news|last1=Hadley|first1=Tessa|author-link=Tessa Hadley|title=Virginia Woolf by Alexandra Harris |url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2011/oct/21/virginia-woolf-alexandra-harris-review|work=The Guardian|date=21 October 2011 |type=Review}}
* {{cite web |last=Haynes |first=Suyin |date=December 17, 2019 |title='It Had a Lifelong Effect on Her.' A New Virginia Woolf Biography Deals With the Author's Experience of Childhood Sexual Abuse |work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |url=https://time.com/5750614/virginia-woolf-biography/ |access-date=26 February 2020}}
* {{cite magazine|last1=Himmelfarb|first1=Gertrude|author-link=Gertrude Himmelfarb|title=From Clapham to Bloomsbury: a genealogy of morals|magazine=[[Commentary (magazine)|Commentary]]|date=1 February 1985 |url=https://www.commentarymagazine.com/articles/from-clapham-to-bloomsbury-a-genealogy-of-morals/}} [https://web.archive.org/web/20070607130045/http://www.facingthechallenge.org/himmelfarb.php ''archived version'']
* {{cite news|last1=Hughes|first1=Kathryn|author-link=Kathryn Hughes|title=The Bloomsbury Group Memoir Club by SP Rosenbaum and James M Haule – review. How a writing group – and some shocking recollections – influenced classic novels |url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2014/jan/23/bloomsbury-group-memoir-club-review|access-date=21 March 2018|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=23 January 2014|type=Review}}
* {{cite news|last1=Humm|first1=Maggie|title=The Stephen sisters as young photographers|work=Canvas|year=2006|issue=15|url=https://www.charleston.org.uk/the-stephen-sisters-as-young-photographers/|publisher=Charleston Trust |location=Firle, East Sussex|ref={{harvid|Humm|2006a}}}}
* {{cite news|last1=Kronenberger|first1=Louis|author-link=Louis Kronenberger|title=Virginia Woolf Discusses Women and fiction|url=https://archive.nytimes.com/www.nytimes.com/books/00/12/17/specials/woolf-room.html|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=10 November 1929|type=Review}}
* {{cite magazine|last1=Matar|first1=Hisham|title=The Unsaid: The Silence of Virginia Woolf|magazine=[[The New Yorker]]|date=10 November 2014|url=https://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/unsaid-silence-virginia-woolf}}
* {{cite news|last1=Lee|first1=Hermione|author-link=Hermione Lee|title=A perfect match |url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2004/jan/10/highereducation.biography|work=[[The Guardian]] |date=10 January 2004|type=Review}}
* {{cite news|last1=Merkin|first1=Daphne|author-link=Daphne Merkin|title=This Loose, Drifting Material of Life|url=https://www.nytimes.com/books/97/06/08/reviews/970608.08merkint.html|access-date=12 March 2018|work=[[The New York Times]] |date=8 June 1997|type=Review}}
* {{cite news|last1=Messud|first1=Claire|author-link=Claire Messud|title=The Husband |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/10/books/review/Messud.t.html|access-date=14 February 2018|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=10 December 2006 |type=Review}}
* {{cite news|last1=Monks|first1=Aoife|title=Virginia Woolf's play exposes the silly side of the Bloomsbury group |url=https://www.theguardian.com/stage/theatreblog/2012/may/23/virginia-woolf-play-bloomsbury-group |work=The Guardian |date=23 May 2012}}
* {{cite news|last1=Parker|first1=Peter|title=Rupert Brooke: a bundle of prejudice and insanity? |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/books/biographyandmemoirreviews/11557238/Rupert-Brooke-a-bundle-of-prejudice-and-insanity.html |access-date=10 April 2018|work=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|date=23 October 1999 |type=Review}}
* {{cite news|last1=Patten|first1=Eve|title=Virginia Woolf's battle with her tea table training |url=https://www.irishtimes.com/culture/books/virginia-woolf-s-battle-with-her-tea-table-training-1.561944 |work=[[The Irish Times]] |date=2 April 2011|type=Review}}
* {{cite magazine|last1=Stone|first1=Peter H.|author-link=Peter Hess Stone|title=Gabriel García Márquez, The Art of Fiction No. 69|url=https://www.theparisreview.org/interviews/3196/gabriel-garcia-marquez-the-art-of-fiction-no-69-gabriel-garcia-marquez|access-date=23 February 2018|magazine=[[The Paris Review]]|issue=82 |date=Winter 1981}}
* {{cite news|last1=Sweeney|first1=Aoibheann|author-link=Aoibheann Sweeney|title=Back to Bloomsbury |url=https://www.nytimes.com/books/00/12/17/reviews/001217.17sweenet.html|work=[[The New York Times]] |date=17 December 2000 |type=Review}} with excerpt 
*{{cite news|last1=Taylor|first1=D. J.|author-link=D J Taylor|title=Bloomsbury's Outsider: A Life of David Garnett by Sarah Knights|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2015/jul/23/bloomsburys-outsider-a-life-of-david-garnett-sarah-knights-review-biography|work=[[The Guardian]]|type=Review|date=23 July 2015}}
* {{cite news|last1=Trilling|first1=Diana|author-link=Diana Trilling|title=Virginia Woolf's Special Realm |url=https://archive.nytimes.com/www.nytimes.com/books/00/12/17/specials/woolf-moment.html |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=21 March 1948|type=Review}}
* {{cite news|last1=Wade|first1=Francesca|title=Dangerous liaisons among the Bloomsbury set |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/books/bookreviews/11698239/Dangerous-liaisons-among-the-Bloomsbury-set.html |work=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|date=26 June 2015|type=Review}}
* {{cite news|last1=Wills|first1=Mathew|title=When Virginia Woolf Wore Blackface |url=https://daily.jstor.org/when-virginia-woolf-wore-blackface/|work=[[JSTOR Daily]]|date=13 May 2017}}
* {{cite news|last=Winterson|first=Jeanette|date=3 September 2018|title='Different sex. Same person': how Woolf's Orlando became a trans triumph|work=The Guardian |url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2018/sep/03/different-sex-same-person-how-woolfs-orlando-became-a-trans-triumph|access-date=2 November 2018}}
* {{cite news|last1=Young|first1=Kevin|author-link=Kevin Young (poet)|title=The Time Virginia Woolf Wore Blackface|url=https://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/the-time-virginia-woolf-wore-blackface|work=[[The New Yorker]] |date=27 October 2017}}

=== Websites and documents ===
* {{cite web|last1=Adams|first1=Terry|date=29 September 2016|title=The death of George Savage |website=Virginia Woolf in Time and Space |publisher=[[James Madison University]] |url=http://sites.jmu.edu/woolfintimeandspace/death-george-savage/ |access-date=17 February 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180218090320/http://sites.jmu.edu/woolfintimeandspace/death-george-savage/ |archive-date=2018-02-18 |url-status=dead}}
* {{Cite web |last=Barmann |first=Jay |title=Castro's Rainbow Honor Walk Dedicated Today |date=2 September 2014 |website=SFiST |url=https://sfist.com/2014/09/02/castros_rainbow_honor_walk_dedicate/}}
* {{cite web | last= Brown|first=Kimmy Sophia| title=Virginia Woolf— On the Track of the Lost Novelist|url=http://significatojournal.com/bliss/a-parliament-of-quotes/virginia-woolf-on-the-track-of-the-lost-novelist/ | website=Significato | date=8 April 2015 | access-date=17 February 2018 }}
* {{cite web|last1=Carter|first1=Jason|title=Virginia Woolf Seminar|url=https://www.uah.edu/woolf/|date= 14 September 2010|publisher=Women's Studies, [[University of Alabama, Huntsville]]}}
* {{cite web|editor-last1= Deegan|editor-first1=Marilyn|editor-last2= Shillingsburg |editor-first2=Peter|editor-link1=Marilyn Deegan|title=Woolf Online: A digital archive of Virginia Woolf's To the Lighthouse (1927) |url=http://www.woolfonline.com/|publisher=[[Society of Authors]]|access-date=7 January 2018|year=2018}}
* {{cite web|last=Jones|first=Josh|title=Virginia Woolf's Handwritten Suicide Note: A Painful and Poignant Farewell (1941)|url=http://www.openculture.com/2013/08/virginia-woolfs-handwritten-suicide-note.html|website=Open Culture |date=26 August 2013|access-date=18 February 2018}}
* {{cite web|last1=Maggio|first1=Paula|title=Gorey illustrations of Woolf in Freshwater |url=https://bloggingwoolf.wordpress.com/2010/08/13/gorey-illustrations-of-woolf-in-freshwater/ |access-date=28 March 2018|date=13 August 2010}}
* {{cite web|last1=Olsen|first1=Victoria|date=1 February 2012|title=Looking for Laura |website=[[Open Letters Monthly]] |url=https://www.openlettersmonthly.com/looking-for-laura/ |access-date=20 January 2018}}
* {{cite web|last1=Saryazdi|first1=Melissa|date=27 September 2017|title=Writers in Cornwall: Virginia Woolf |website=FalWriting: English &amp; Creative Writing at Falmouth |url=https://falwriting.com/new-blog/2017/9/27/writers-in-cornwall-virginia-woolf |access-date=28 February 2018}}
* {{cite web|editor-last1=Wilson |editor-first1=J.J.|editor-last2=Barrett|editor-first2=Eileen|title=Lucio Ruotolo 1927–2003 |url=https://virginiawoolfmiscellany.files.wordpress.com/2013/09/vwm63summer2003.pdf |website=Virginia Woolf Miscellany|publisher=Southern Connecticut State University|access-date=24 March 2018 |date=Summer 2003}} (includes invitation to first performance in 1935 and Lucio Ruotolo's introduction to the 1976 Hogarth Press edition&lt;ref group=Bibliography&gt;{{harvnb|Woolf|1976}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
* {{cite web|title= Virginia Woolf |url=https://alumni.kcl.ac.uk/news-features/notable-alumni/virginia-woolf |website=Notable alumni|publisher=King's College London |access-date=2 February 2018|ref={{harvid|King's College, London|2017}}}}
* {{cite web|title=Virginia and Leonard Woolf marry|url=http://www.history.com/this-day-in-history/virginia-and-leonard-woolf-marry|website=This day in history|publisher=[[A&amp;E (TV channel)|A &amp; E Television]]|access-date=14 February 2018|year=2018|ref={{harvid|History|2018}}}}
* {{cite web|title=Androom Archives|url=https://androom.home.xs4all.nl/index.htm?welcome.htm|year=2017 |access-date=19 December 2017|ref={{harvid|Androom|2017}}}}
* {{cite dictionary|title=Woolf|work=Collins English Dictionary|publisher= Harper Collins Publishers |url=https://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/woolf|access-date=2 February 2018|ref={{harvid|Collins|2018}}}}
* {{cite web|title=Woolf, Creativity and Madness: From Freud to FMRI|website=Smith College Libraries: Online exhibits |publisher=[[Smith College]] Libraries|location=Northampton MA |url=https://www.smith.edu/woolf/index.php|access-date=15 December 2017|ref={{harvid|Smith College|2017}}}}
* {{cite web|title=Virginia Woolf Building (22 Kingsway)|publisher=King's College London |url=https://www.kcl.ac.uk/aboutkings/orgstructure/ps/estates/Real-Estate/completed/VWB.aspx#ad-image-0 |access-date=12 February 2018 |year=2018|ref={{harvid|King's College, London|2018}}}}
* {{cite web|title=Virginia Woolf honoured by new Strand Campus building |url=http://www.kcl.ac.uk/study/international/yourcountry/usa/News/Woolf-building.aspx |website=News|publisher=King's College London |access-date=15 February 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150713190253/http://www.kcl.ac.uk/study/international/yourcountry/usa/News/Woolf-building.aspx |archive-date=13 July 2015|date=2 May 2013|ref={{harvid|King's College, London|2013}}}}
* {{cite web|last1=Chicago|first1=Judy|author-link=Judy Chicago|title=The Dinner Party: Place Settings |url=https://www.brooklynmuseum.org/eascfa/dinner_party/place_settings|publisher=[[Elizabeth A. Sackler Center for Feminist Art]], [[Brooklyn Museum]]|access-date=23 February 2018|date=1974–1979}}
* {{cite web|title=Virginia Woolf Society of Great Britain |url=http://www.virginiawoolfsociety.co.uk/index.html |access-date=26 December 2017|ref={{harvid|VWS|2017}} |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171218033823/http://www.virginiawoolfsociety.co.uk/index.html# |archive-date=18 December 2017|url-status=dead}}
* {{cite web|title=Virginia Woolf: Art, Life and Vision|date=10 July – 20 October 2014 |url=https://www.npg.org.uk/whatson/virginiawoolf/home |publisher=[[National Portrait Gallery, London|National Portrait Gallery]] |type=Museum exhibition}}
* {{cite web|title=Find a will. Index to wills and administrations (1858–1995) |website=[[Calendars of the Grants of Probate and Letters of Administration]]|publisher=[[The National Archives]] |url=https://probatesearch.service.gov.uk/#calendar |access-date=2 March 2018 |ref={{harvid|Archives|2018}}}}
* {{cite web|title=Currency converter|url=http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/currency/ |publisher=National Archives|access-date=2 March 2018|ref={{harvid|Archives|2018a}}}}
* {{cite web|last=NPG|author-link=National Portrait Gallery, London|title=Maurice Beck and Helen Macgregor (1886–1960) |url=https://www.npg.org.uk/collections/search/person/mp65250/maurice-beck-and-helen-macgregor |publisher=[[National Portrait Gallery, London|National Portrait Gallery]], London |access-date=10 March 2018|ref={{harvid|NPG|2018}}}}
* {{cite web|title=Virginia Woolf Around The World |website=Exhibitions|publisher=[[E. J. Pratt Library]], [[Victoria University, Toronto]]. 2018. |date=January 2017 |url=http://library.vicu.utoronto.ca/collections/exhibitions/virginia_woolf_around_the_world|access-date=14 March 2018 |ref={{harvid|Pratt|2017}}}}
* {{cite web|title=Virginia Woolf – First Editions |url=https://www.harringtonbooks.co.uk/pages/author/306/virginia-woolf/ |publisher=[[Adrian Harrington]] Rare Books|access-date=14 March 2018|ref={{harvid|Harrington|2018}}}}
* {{cite web|title=Cox, Katherine Laird 'Ka'|url=http://www.kings.cam.ac.uk/archive-centre/introduction-archives/biographies.html#c |website=Introduction to archives: Rupert Brooke (Biographies)|publisher=King's College, Cambridge|access-date=2 April 2018|ref={{harvid|King's College, Cambridge|2018}}|date=19 March 2015}}
* {{cite web |title=Virginia Woolf Statue Fundraiser |url=https://uk.virginmoneygiving.com/charity-web/charity/finalCharityHomepage.action?charityId=1017238&amp;pageId=1040913 |website=uk.virginmoneygiving.com |publisher=Aurora Metro Arts And Media Ltd |access-date=24 June 2020 |ref={{harvid|Statue Fundraiser}}}}

'''Blogs'''

* {{cite web|last1=Brooks|first1=Rebecca Beatrice|date=8 April 2015|title=Virginia Woolf's Family |website=The Virginia Woolf Blog |url=http://virginiawoolfblog.com/virginia-woolfs-living-family-members/ |access-date=19 January 2018}}
* {{cite web|last1=Eve|first1=Kimberly|title=Victorian Musings|url=http://kimberlyevemusings.blogspot.ca/|access-date=26 December 2017|date=19 November 2017}}
* {{cite web|last1=Roe|first1=Dinah|title=Virginia Woolf and Holman Hunt go to the Lighthouse|url=http://www.dinahroe.com/blog/virginia_woolf_and_holman_hunt_go_to_the_lighthouse|website=Pre-Raphaelites in the city|access-date=25 December 2017|year=2011}}

'''British Library'''

* {{cite web|last1=Gordon|first1=Lyndall|author-link=Lyndall Gordon|title=Too much suicide?|url=https://www.bl.uk/20th-century-literature/articles/too-much-suicide|website=Discovering Literature: 20th century|publisher=[[British Library]]|access-date=9 February 2018|location=London|date=25 May 2016}}
* {{cite web|last1=Heyes|first1=Duncan|title=The Hogarth Press|url=https://www.bl.uk/20th-century-literature/articles/the-hogarth-press|website=Discovering Literature: 20th century|publisher=[[British Library]]|access-date=7 March 2018|date=25 May 2016}}
* {{cite web|last = British Library|author-link=British Library|title=Grace Higgens's diary for 1924|url=https://www.bl.uk/collection-items/grace-higgens-diary-for-1924-with-accounts-of-virginia-woolf|website=20th century collection|date=2018e|access-date=20 March 2018}}

==== Literary commentary ====
* {{cite web|last1=Nagy|first1=Kim|title=Meeting Virginia Woolf at the Strand|url=https://www.wildriverreview.com/columns/triple-goddess-trials/meeting-virginia-woolf-at-the-strand/|website=[[Wild River Review]]|access-date=28 March 2018|ref={{harvid|Nagy|2018}}|date=29 October 2015}}
* {{cite web|last=Rahn|first=Josh|title=Modernism|url=http://www.online-literature.com/periods/modernism.php|website=The Literature Network|publisher=Jalic|year=2018|access-date=21 February 2018}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Rosenbaum|first1=S. P.|title=Virginia Woolf among the Apostles|url=http://letourcritique.u-paris10.fr/index.php/letourcritique/article/view/27/html|journal=Le Tour Critique|access-date=13 April 2018|year=2013|issue=2|pages=131–146}}
* {{cite web|last1=Snodgrass|first1=Chris|title=Introduction: Virginia Woolf (1882‒1941)|url=http://users.clas.ufl.edu/snod/WoolfIntroductionNB.103115.pdf|publisher=Department of English, [[University of Florida]]|type=Course materials|year=2015|access-date=15 March 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180316024434/http://users.clas.ufl.edu/snod/WoolfIntroductionNB.103115.pdf |archive-date=2018-03-16 |url-status=dead}}

;British Library

* {{cite web|last1=Bradshaw|first1=David|title=Mrs Dalloway and the First World War|url=https://www.bl.uk/20th-century-literature/articles/mrs-dalloway-and-the-first-world-war|website=Discovering Literature: 20th century|publisher=[[British Library]]|access-date=14 March 2018|date=25 May 2016}}
* {{cite web|last1=Taunton|first1=Matthew|title=Modernism, time and consciousness: the influence of Henri Bergson and Marcel Proust|url=https://www.bl.uk/20th-century-literature/articles/modernism-time-and-consciousness-the-influence-of-henri-bergson-and-marcel-proust|website=Discovering Literature: 20th century|publisher=[[British Library]]|date=25 May 2016 |access-date=15 March 2018}}
* {{cite web|last = British Library|author-link=British Library|title=A Room of One's Own by Virginia Woolf|url=https://www.bl.uk/collection-items/a-room-of-ones-own-by-virginia-woolf|website=20th century collection|date=2018a|access-date=5 March 2018}}
* {{cite web|last = British Library|author-link=British Library|author-mask=1|title=Kew Gardens by Virginia Woolf, 1927|url=https://www.bl.uk/collection-items/kew-gardens-by-virginia-woolf-1927|website=20th century collection|date=2018d|access-date=20 March 2018}}
* {{cite web|last = British Library|author-link=British Library|author-mask=1|title='Mr. Bennett and Mrs. Brown' by Virginia Woolf|url=https://www.bl.uk/collection-items/mr-bennett-and-mrs-brown-by-virginia-woolf|access-date=3 April 2018|website=20th century collection|date=2019e}}
* {{cite web|last = British Library|author-link=British Library|author-mask=1|title=To the Lighthouse|url=https://www.bl.uk/works/to-the-lighthouse|website=20th century works|id=37018|year=2018|access-date=9 February 2018}}
* {{cite web|last = British Library|author-link=British Library|author-mask=1|title=Two Stories, written and printed by Virginia and Leonard Woolf|url=https://www.bl.uk/collection-items/two-stories-written-and-printed-by-virginia-and-leonard-woolf|website=20th century collection|date=2018c|access-date=20 March 2018}}
* {{cite web|last = British Library|author-link=British Library|author-mask=1|title=Virginia Woolf|url=https://www.bl.uk/people/virginia-woolf|website=20th century people|publisher=[[British Library]]|date=2018b|access-date=11 March 2018}}

==== Virginia Woolf's homes and venues ====
* {{cite web|last1=Brooks|first1=Rebecca Beatrice|date=21 March 2012a|title=Virginia Woolf's Homes Destroyed in the London Blitz |website=The Virginia Woolf Blog |url=http://virginiawoolfblog.com/virginia-woolfs-london-homes-destroyed-by-german-bombs/ |access-date=28 February 2018}}
* {{cite web|last1=Brooks|first1=Rebecca Beatrice|date=10 July 2012b|title=Did Virginia Woolf Live in a Haunted House? |website=The Virginia Woolf Blog |url=http://virginiawoolfblog.com/did-virginia-woolf-live-in-a-haunted-house/ |access-date=28 February 2018}}
* {{cite web|last1=Grant|first1=Duncan|author-link=Duncan Grant|title=Shutter design for 38 Brunswick Square 1912|url= http://www.artandarchitecture.org.uk/images/gallery/9fc9eb12.html |website=Art &amp; Architecture: Gallery collections |publisher=[[Courtauld Institute of Art]]|access-date=4 March 2018|year=1978|ref={{harvid|Grant|1912}}}}
* {{cite web|last1=Halstead|first1=Hannah|title=52 Tavistock Square|url=https://blogs.shu.edu/british-modernism-undergraduate/2017/11/24/52-tavistock-square/|website=Sites of British Modernism: Mapping Key Locations of British Modernism |publisher=[[Seton Hall University]]|access-date=5 March 2018|date=24 November 2017}}
* {{cite web|last=Maggio|first=Paula|title=Virginia's Round House in Lewes up for sale |url=https://bloggingwoolf.wordpress.com/2009/05/03/virginias-round-house-in-lewes-up-for-sale/ |date=4 May 2009 |website=Blogging Woolf}}
* {{cite web|last1=Richardson|first1=Phyllis|title=Tales from Talland House|url=https://unbound.com/books/the-house-of-fiction/updates/tales-from-talland-house|website=Unbound|access-date=1 January 2018|date=24 March 2015}}
* {{cite web|last1=Wilkinson|first1=Sheila M|title=Firle Village, Sussex |year=2001 |url=http://www.virginiawoolfsociety.co.uk/vw_res.firle.htm|access-date=4 March 2018}}, in {{harvtxt|VWS|2017}}
* {{cite web|title=The Woolfs at Asham House|url=http://www.ashamaward.com/pages/content/index.asp?PageID=71 |website=The Asham Award|publisher=The Asham Trust|access-date=5 March 2018|ref={{harvid|Asham|2018}} |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180306023300/http://www.ashamaward.com/pages/content/index.asp?PageID=71 |archive-date=6 March 2018|url-status=dead}}
* {{cite web|title=Literary history celebrated in Brunswick Square |url=https://bloomsburysquares.wordpress.com/2015/12/01/literary-history-celebrated-in-brunswick-bquare/ |website=Bloomsbury Squares &amp; Gardens |publisher=Association of Bloomsbury Squares and Gardens |access-date=4 March 2018|date=1 December 2015|ref={{harvid|Bloomsbury Squares|2015}}}} 
* {{cite web|title=Virginia Woolf (1882–1941) and Hogarth House |url=http://www.richmond.gov.uk/virginia_woolf_and_hogarth_house |publisher=[[London Borough of Richmond upon Thames]]|access-date=15 February 2018 |date=9 January 2015 |ref={{harvid|Richmond|2015}}}}
* {{cite web|title=Bloomsbury Walk|url=https://www.uah.edu/woolf/bloomsbury%20walk.doc|type=Word document |year=2018|access-date=5 March 2018|ref={{harvid|UAH|2018}}}}, in {{harvtxt|Carter|2010}}
* {{cite web|title=Monk's House: Leonard and Virginia Woolf's 17th-century country retreat|year=2018 |url=https://www.nationaltrust.org.uk/monks-house|publisher=[[National Trust]]|access-date=11 March 2018}}
* {{anchor|Street tour}}{{cite web|title=Take a Tour of Virginia Woolf's Life in London |website=Google Arts &amp; Culture |url=https://artsandculture.google.com/theme/-QLS7wTicoXOLA |access-date=31 March 2018|ref={{harvid|Google|2018}}}}

==== Virginia Woolf biography ====
* {{cite web|last=Liukkonen |first=Petri |title=Virginia Woolf (1882–1941)| url=http://www.kirjasto.sci.fi/vwoolf.htm |website=Books and Writers   |publisher=[[Kuusankoski]] Public Library |location=Finland |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150128025206/http://www.kirjasto.sci.fi/vwoolf.htm |year=2008|archive-date=28 January 2015 |access-date=8 February 2016 |url-status=dead }}
* {{cite web|last1=Svendsen|first1=Jessica|last2=Lewis|first2=Pericles|author-link2=Pericles Lewis|title=Virginia Woolf|url=https://modernism.coursepress.yale.edu/virginia-woolf/|website=Modernism Lab|publisher=[[Yale University]]|access-date=11 March 2018|ref={{harvid|Svendsen|Lewis|2018}}}}

==== Timelines ====
* {{cite web|title=Timeline of Virginia Woolf's Life|date=9 February 2012 |website=The Virginia Woolf Blog |url=http://virginiawoolfblog.com/timeline-of-virginia-woolfs-life-2/ |access-date=19 January 2018}}
* {{cite web|last1=Clarke|first1=S. N.|title=Where Virginia Woolf Lived in London |url=http://www.virginiawoolfsociety.co.uk/vw_res.london.htm |access-date=1 March 2018 |year=2000 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180115195125/http://www.virginiawoolfsociety.co.uk/vw_res.london.htm |archive-date=15 January 2018|url-status=dead}}, in {{harvtxt|VWS|2017}}
* {{cite web|title=Chronological List of Works By Virginia Woolf|url=https://www.uah.edu/woolf/chrono.html|access-date=1 March 2018|date=4 December 2002|ref={{harvid|Carter|2002}}}}, in {{harvtxt|Carter|2010}}
* {{cite web|title=The Principal Works of Virginia Woolf (1882–1941) |ref={{harvid|VWS|2018}} |url=http://www.virginiawoolfsociety.co.uk/vw_res.principal.htm |access-date=29 March 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170825075434/http://www.virginiawoolfsociety.co.uk/vw_res.principal.htm |archive-date=25 August 2017 |url-status=dead}}, in {{harvtxt|VWS|2017}}}
* {{cite web|title=Chronology of Virginia Woolf's Life |url=https://www.uah.edu/woolf/woolfchr.html|access-date=1 March 2018|date=7 July 1997}}, in {{harvtxt|Carter|2010}}
* {{cite web|title=Virginia Woolf: The Highs and Lows of Her Creative Genius|url=https://www.biography.com/news/virginia-woolf-biography-facts|website=Biography|publisher=[[A&amp;E Television Networks]]|access-date=30 March 2018|date=25 January 2017}}

==== Genealogy ====
* {{cite web|last1=Vine|first1=Nikki|title=Nikki's Family History and Wells Local History Pages|url=http://www.nikoko.co.uk/index.htm|access-date=6 January 2018|ref={{harvid|Vine|2018}}}}
* {{cite web|last1=Wood|first1=Dudley|title=Family Histories of Wood of Kent, Bone of Hampshire, Lloyd of Cheshire, Thompson of West Yorkshire|url=https://woodlloydfamilyhistory.com/|access-date=30 December 2017|date=3 November 2017}}
* {{cite web|title=Geni|url=https://www.geni.com/family-tree/start|access-date=2 January 2018|year=2018|ref={{harvid|Geni|2018}}}}
* {{cite web|title=Relatives of Virginia Woolf|publisher=Smith College|date=22 March 2011 |url=https://www.smith.edu/woolf/genogram_current/index.html|access-date=15 December 2017|ref={{harvid|Smith College|2011}}}}, in {{harvtxt|Smith College|2017}}
* {{acad|id=DKWT851H|name=Duckworth, Herbert|access-date=14 February 2018}}
* {{acad|id=DKWT886GH|name=Duckworth, George Herbert|access-date=14 February 2018}}
* {{acad|id=DKWT889GD|name=Duckworth, Gerald de l'Étang|access-date=14 February 2018}}
* {{acad|id=STFN899JT|name=Stephen, Julian Thoby|access-date=14 February 2018}}
* {{acad|id=STFN850L|name=Stephen, Leslie|access-date=14 February 2018}}

=== Images ===
* {{anchor|VWMD}}{{cite web|last1=Beck|first1=Maurice|last2= Macgregor|first2=Helen|title=Virginia Woolf tries on her mother's Victorian dress, May 1926|type=Photograph |work=[[Vogue (magazine)|Vogue]] |url=https://i.pinimg.com/originals/0d/83/2a/0d832ac86c0fd0e52022ada3ad8375ce.jpg |access-date=9 January 2018 |date=May 1926}}{{efn|Maurice Beck and Helen Macgregor, who ran a studio in Marylebone, were chief photographers for [[British Vogue|British ''Vogue'']].&lt;ref group=Bibliography&gt;{{harvnb|NPG|2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
* {{cite web|last1=Colman|first1=Dan|title=Vintage Photos of a Young Virginia Woolf Playing Cricket (Ages 5 &amp; 12)|url=http://www.openculture.com/2014/01/young-virginia-woolf-playing-cricket.html|publisher=Open Culture|access-date=11 March 2018|date=14 January 2014}}
* {{cite web|last1=Fry|first1=Roger|author-link=Roger Fry|title=Landscape at Asheham House, near Lewes, Sussex|url=https://artuk.org/discover/artworks/landscape-at-asheham-house-near-lewes-sussex-220642|website=[[Art UK]] |publisher=[[Arts Council England]]|access-date=10 March 2018|format=Painting|year=1913}}
* {{cite web|last1=Kukil|first1=Karen V.|title=Julia Prinsep Jackson, c.1856|website=Leslie Stephen's Photograph Album|url=https://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/rarebook/exhibitions/stephen/31a.htm|publisher=[[Smith College]] |location=Northampton MA|year=2011|type=Exhibition catalogue: photograph album|access-date=19 December 2017}}
* {{anchor|MRVW}}{{cite web|last1=Ray|first1=Man|author-link=Man Ray|title=Virginia Woolf|date=12 April 1937 |url=http://content.time.com/time/covers/0,16641,19370412,00.html |work=Time |access-date=10 March 2018}}
* {{anchor|38BS}}{{cite web|title=Literary history celebrated in Brunswick Square|date=1 December 2015 |type=Photograph |url=https://bloomsburysquares.files.wordpress.com/2015/11/dscn1843.jpg?w=640&amp;h=481|access-date=4 March 2018}}, in {{harvtxt|Bloomsbury Squares|2015}}
* {{anchor|DG12}}{{cite web|title=Shutter design|year=1912|type=Painting |url=http://www.artandarchitecture.org.uk/assets/aa_image/320/9/f/c/9/9fc9eb12f22ff93b317e8ed399cd5abfa52836c6.jpg |access-date=4 March 2018}}, in {{harvtxt|Grant|1912}}
* {{anchor|Asham}}{{cite web|title=Asham|year=2012 |type=Photograph |website=The Virginia Woolf Blog |url=http://virginiawoolfblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/Asheham_House.jpg}}, in {{harvtxt|Brooks|2012b}}
* {{anchor|22HPGext}}{{cite book|title=22 Hyde Park Gate showing red brick extension |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=odBIxjAhjbsC&amp;pg=PA43|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |access-date=20 March 2018|year=2005|isbn= 9780521812931}}

=== Maps ===
* {{anchor|22HPGmap}}{{cite web|title=Map of location of 22 Hyde Park Gate |url=https://tools.wmflabs.org/wiwosm/osm-on-ol/commons-on-osm.php?zoom=16&amp;lat=051.499784&amp;lon=-000.181490|website=[[Google Earth]]|access-date=23 January 2018 |type=Map}}
* {{anchor|22HPGplan}}{{cite web|title=Street plan of Hyde Park Gate|url=http://www.british-history.ac.uk/sites/default/files/publications/pubid-364/images/fig10.gif|year=1975|type=Plan}}, in {{harvtxt|Sheppard|1975}}
* {{anchor|Bloomsmap}}{{cite web|title=Map of Bloomsbury with Gordon, Brunswick, Mecklenburg and Tavistock Squares |url=https://tools.wmflabs.org/wiwosm/osm-on-ol/commons-on-osm.php?zoom=17&amp;lat=51.5241&amp;lon=-0.12603&amp;layers=B0TFT |website=[[Google Earth]]|access-date=8 March 2018|type=Map}}
* {{anchor|ESmap}}{{cite web|title=Map of East Sussex from Lewes in the northwest to Alciston in the southwest, including Rodmell and Firle |url=https://tools.wmflabs.org/wiwosm/osm-on-ol/commons-on-osm.php?zoom=14&amp;lat=50.84972&amp;lon=0.07177&amp;layers=B0TF |website=[[Google Earth]]|access-date=8 March 2018|type=Map}}{{efn|group=Bibliography|The Roundhouse on Pipe Passage is at the west end of central Lewes. Asham House was in what became an industrial site on a west side road of the A26 south of [[Beddingham]]. Charleston Farmhouse is on a sideroad south of the A27 between Firle and [[Alciston]]}}

=== Audiovisual media ===
* {{cite AV media|last=Coe|first=Amanda (Producer)|author-link=Amanda Coe|title=Life in Squares|year=2015 |medium = T.V. series (3)|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b0649cyj|location=UK|publisher=BBC}} see also ''[[Life in Squares]]''
* {{cite AV media|last=Lee|first=Hermione|author-link=Hermione Lee|date=13 June 1997|title=Virginia Woolf |medium=TV |url=https://www.c-span.org/video/?87703-1/virginia-woolf|access-date= 7 March 2018|publisher=[[C-SPAN]]}}
* {{cite AV media|last=Stevenson|first=Juliet|author-link=Juliet Stevenson|title=Suicide letter to Leonard Woolf, March 28 1941 |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-ze0p4kDqHE|date=31 March 2015|access-date= 28 March 2018 |medium=Audio |publisher=[[BBC]] [[Newsnight]] (YouTube)}} 
* {{cite AV media |last=Young|first=Eric Neal (Director) |title=The Mind and Times of Virginia Woolf |year=2002|medium=Documentary |url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0457593/ |location= USA |publisher= Miramax}} [https://www.college.columbia.edu/core/content/mind-and-times-virginia-woolf-directed-eric-neal-young-2002 excerpt]
* {{IMDb name|941173}}
** {{cite web|title=Virginia Woolf (Character)|website=Character|publisher=[[IMDb]] |url=https://www.imdb.com/character/ch0009867/|access-date=11 March 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170227091430/http://www.imdb.com/character/ch0009867/ |archive-date=27 February 2017}}
* {{cite web|title=Greatest writers find their voice|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/7684201.stm |publisher=[[BBC]]|access-date=11 March 2018|date=22 October 2008}}
** {{cite AV media |last=Woolf|first=Virginia |date=29 April 1937|title=Craftmanship|medium=Radio |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/av/entertainment-arts-28231055/rare-recording-of-virginia-woolf|access-date=7 March 2018|publisher= [[BBC Radio]] Words Fail Me}}

=== Selected online texts ===
* {{Gutenberg author | id=Woolf,+Virginia }}
* {{FadedPage|id=Woolf, Virginia|name=Virginia Woolf|author=yes}}
;Audiofiles
* {{Librivox author |id=843}}
* {{cite web|title=The Legacy |url=http://cle.ens-lyon.fr/anglais/litterature/litterature-britannique/the-legacy-1944- |website=La Clé des Langues [en ligne]: Littérature britannique |publisher=[[École normale supérieure de Lyon]] |year=1944}}
* {{cite web|title=The Searchlight |url=http://cle.ens-lyon.fr/anglais/litterature/litterature-britannique/the-searchlight-1944- |website=La Clé des Langues [en ligne]: Littérature britannique |publisher=[[École normale supérieure de Lyon]]|year=1944}}

=== Archival material ===
* {{UK National Archives ID}}
* {{cite web|title=Virginia Woolf: Author and publisher |url=http://library.vicu.utoronto.ca/collections/special_collections/f65_virginia_woolf |publisher=E. J. Pratt Library, [[Victoria University, Toronto]] |year=2018}}
* {{cite web|title=Virginia Woolf collection of papers 1882–1984 |url=http://archives.nypl.org/brg/19159 |website=Archives and Manuscripts: [[Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature]] |publisher=[[New York Public Library]]|access-date=11 March 2018|year=2018}}
{{refend}}

=== Bibliography notes ===
{{notelist|group=Bibliography}}

=== Bibliography references ===
{{reflist|group=Bibliography}}

==External links==
* {{StandardEbooks|Standard Ebooks URL=https://standardebooks.org/ebooks/virginia-woolf}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Virginia Woolf}}
* {{Librivox author |id=843}}
* [https://findingaids.smith.edu/repositories/3/resources/405 Virginia Woolf Papers] at the [[Mortimer Rare Book Collection]], Smith College Special Collections
* [http://virginiawoolfblog.com The Virginia Woolf Blog]
&lt;!-- navboxes --&gt;
{{Library resources box|by=yes|onlinebooks=yes|viaf=39385478}}
{{sisterlinks|d=Q40909|s=author:Virginia Woolf|commons=category:Virginia Woolf|n=no|b=no|v=no|voy=no|mw=no|m=no|species=no|wikt=no|position=left}}

{{Virginia Woolf|state=uncollapsed}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Woolf, Virginia}}
[[Category:Virginia Woolf| ]]
[[Category:1882 births]]
[[Category:1941 suicides]]
[[Category:19th-century English women]]
[[Category:19th-century English people]]
[[Category:19th-century English writers]]
[[Category:20th-century British short story writers]]
[[Category:20th-century English women writers]]
[[Category:20th-century English writers]]
[[Category:20th-century English novelists]]
[[Category:20th-century essayists]]
[[Category:20th-century non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:Alumni of King's College London]]
[[Category:Bisexual women]]
[[Category:Bisexual writers]]
[[Category:Bloomsbury Group]]
[[Category:Bloomsbury Group biographers]]
[[Category:British anti-fascists]]
[[Category:British atheists]]
[[Category:British autobiographers]]
[[Category:British diarists]]
[[Category:British essayists]]
[[Category:British humanists]]
[[Category:British memoirists]]
[[Category:British pacifists]]
[[Category:British secularists]]
[[Category:British socialists]]
[[Category:British cultural critics]]
[[Category:British women dramatists and playwrights]]
[[Category:British women essayists]]
[[Category:British women short story writers]]
[[Category:Critics of Christianity]]
[[Category:Critics of Judaism]]
[[Category:Critics of new religious movements]]
[[Category:Critics of religions]]
[[Category:English anti-fascists]]
[[Category:English atheists]]
[[Category:English autobiographers]]
[[Category:English diarists]]
[[Category:English essayists]]
[[Category:English humanists]]
[[Category:English memoirists]]
[[Category:English pacifists]]
[[Category:English socialists]]
[[Category:English women dramatists and playwrights]]
[[Category:English women novelists]]
[[Category:LGBT memoirists]]
[[Category:LGBT writers from England]]
[[Category:Mental health activists]]
[[Category:Modernist women writers]]
[[Category:Modernist writers]]
[[Category:People from Kensington]]
[[Category:People with bipolar disorder]]
[[Category:Self-published authors]]
[[Category:British social commentators]] 
[[Category:Social critics]] 
[[Category:Stephen-Bell family]]
[[Category:Suicides by drowning in England]]
[[Category:Women diarists]]
[[Category:British women memoirists]]
[[Category:Writers about activism and social change]]
[[Category:Writers from London]]
[[Category:20th-century memoirists]]
[[Category:Dreadnought hoax]]
[[Category:English feminist writers]]
[[Category:Atheist feminists]]
[[Category:People from Firle]]
[[Category:British feminists]]
[[Category:English feminists]]</text>
      <sha1>aps4si8644x27bin3qli3bgdd51l010</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
